<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three propositions or speeches, which that excellent man M. Iohn Caluin, one of the pastors of the Church of God in Geneua had there To which also is added, an exposition vpon that parte of the catechisme, which is appointed for the three and fortieth Sunday in number. Translated into Englishe, by T.VV.</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 235 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17727</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121928</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857085</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857085</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22757</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17727)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 310:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three propositions or speeches, which that excellent man M. Iohn Caluin, one of the pastors of the Church of God in Geneua had there To which also is added, an exposition vpon that parte of the catechisme, which is appointed for the three and fortieth Sunday in number. Translated into Englishe, by T.VV.</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 82, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Thomas Dawson] for George Bishop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.W. = Thomas Wilcox.</note>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564. --  Catéchisme de l'Eglise de Genève --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶Three Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>or Speeches, which</hi> that excellent man M. Iohn Caluin, <hi>one of the Paſtors of the Church of God in</hi> Geneua <hi>had there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which alſo is added,</hi> an expoſition vpon that parte of the Catechiſme, which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the three and fortieth Sunday in number.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated into Engliſhe, by</hi> T. VV.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for George Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. 1580.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right worſhipfull,</hi> Syr Richard Knightley Knight, <hi>and the Right Honourable the Ladie</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth his wyfe. T. W. wiſheth all growth in goodnes, with conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and continuance in the truth of God for euer and euer, thorowe Chriſt our Lorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I (Ryght woorſhipfull and Honorable) enter into a deepe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of myne owne particular grieuous offences, but alſo of the generall ſinnes &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of the whole lande, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually committed againſt God and good men, I am wonderfully caſt downe in my ſelfe, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed (as it were) with heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for thoſe great iudgementes that by the reaſon of theſe our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities
<pb facs="tcp:22757:3"/> wee haue, as it were with gable ropes, pulled from God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our owne ſoules. But when I throughly weigh what ſlender meanes are vſed to bring men too God, and vnfeigned repentaunce, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their former euill wayes (that ſo the plagues hanging ouer our heades, may be vtterly remooued from vs and our countrey, or at the leaſt ſo leſſened, that we be not ſwalowed vp of the ſame) I am almoſt as a man altogeather paſt hope, that wee can bee ſet free or deliuered from thoſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and puniſhmentes, which the Lorde by manyfeſt ſignes and tokens from heauen, and by conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuall threatnings and outcries, of his faithfull miniſters, hath nowe a long time denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced againſt this proud and thankleſſe generation. For what between idle and Idoll
<pb facs="tcp:22757:3"/> miniſters on the one ſide, &amp; blind, wilfull, and ſuperſtitious people on the other ſide, iniquitie is grown to ſo great a height, that as men make little or no conſcience at all of committing ſinne, ſo they ſeeme to be ſunk deepe in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and are growne as a man woulde ſay, ſenſeleſſe of their tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, inſomuch that men can hardly tell what to pronounce vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe they ſhoulde ſay thus, that by our deedes wee alow that, which by woordes in popery, we doe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly condemne, to wit, that blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ignorance is the mother of deuotion.</p>
            <p>Is it not both ſtraunge and pitifull, and yet in my perſwaſion, I take it to bee for the moſt parte very true, that after twenty yeeres publique preaching &amp; profeſſing of the Goſpel vnder our gracious
<pb facs="tcp:22757:4"/> Soueraignes raigne, the people are verie litle, or no whit at all edified in the knowledge of fayth, &amp; leſſe builded vp (if leſſe can bee) in the fruites of obedience and holy life? Not that I deny the Goſpell, to haue taken good roote in ſundrye mens hartes: but this I meane, that that number is very ſmal, yea euen as it were a cottage in a vineyarde, or lyke a Lodge in a Gardeyne of Cucumbers, or like a beſieged Citie.<note place="margin">Iſaiah. <hi>1.</hi>8.</note> If any man would doubt of the trueth of this, the matter it ſelf is more manifeſt, than that it nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to bee prooued: for if a man woulde but make his eyes and his eares, witneſſes (as it were) of this matter, howe can he pretend igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? Who paſſeth thorowe any place of the lande that beholdeth not, &amp; heareth not, generally and in the greateſt number, peſtilent pride, miſchieuous murthers, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:22757:4"/> whoredomes, open othes, beaſtly blaſphemies againſt God, commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contempt of magiſtracie and all goodnes, beſides a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuch like abominations? So that a man may perceiue not a window onely, but a wyde wicket, or barne doore rather, ſet open to all maner of licentiouſnes and naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie behauiour. And ſurely if theſe faultes were in the meaneſt onely, they were very grieuous before God and man: but what are they then, when the handes of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be the chiefeſt in theſe ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities? Be it farre from vs to be Stoickes, who thought all ſinnes equall. Chriſtians ſhoulde know (and the rather becauſe the Lorde alſo hath reuealed the ſame in his worde) that ſome ſinnes bee more grieuous, than other ſome are in his ſight: yea that one and the ſelf ſame ſinne, is verie much aggraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:5"/> &amp; made more heynous, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in reſpect of the circumſtaunces, as tyme, place, perſon, manner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. And what I pray you is the cauſe, of this ſo great diſorder and licentiouſnes? Is not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and negligence in Prieſtes (as they call them) and people, the mother and nurſe of all theſe and ſuch like wickedneſſes? If wee might tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe Gods eſpeciall bleſſing once haue the pointes and principles of Chriſtian religion, diligently and purely propounded, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of maners, ſenſibly and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet foorth, and by the meanes of our Magiſtrates, Gods own diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, for the better fructifiyng of his worde, allowed of and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed amongſt vs, &amp; our poſteritie, we ſhould, no doubt, ſee, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe groſſe iniquities vtterly baniſhed, but alſo the very intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts
<pb facs="tcp:22757:5"/> &amp; prouocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to euil, quite and cleane remooued: but till then wee may not looke for any better fruites than theſe that we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready reaped and rehearſed. True it is, that God can bring light out of darkneſſe, and make his glory ſhine forth in our ſhameful falles: but none ought therefore to loue darkneſſe (nay wee muſte haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull works of darknſſe,<note place="margin">Epheſia. 5.<hi>11.</hi>
               </note> but reprooue them rather) or delight in ſin,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13.</note> but rather take heede that our heartes be not hardened through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulnes thereof. If any will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende that grace may abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.47.</note> their condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is iuſte: and he that knoweth his maiſters wil &amp; doth it not, ſhall bee beaten with many ſtripes. He that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not lie, hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, &amp; therfore no reaſon at al why we ſhold doubt of it: and he that doth what pleſeth him both in
<pb facs="tcp:22757:6"/> heauen &amp; in earth wil in time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme it (without ſpeed in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned repentance) vppon vs all both hygh and lowe, which alſo ſhould haſten our turning.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 6.3.</note> Wee ſee then that we haue no cauſe at al to dally and delaie, and to put the euill day farre from vs, as the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked do,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.</note> but rather while the Lord in long ſuffring forbeareth vs, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs to amendement by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly viſitations, that euerie one of vs ſhould in time thinke of and vſe, all the meanes of our earneſt and hartie conuerſion vnto him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.13.</note> and while it is called to day, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently hearke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his voice, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto vs out of his word, leaſt otherwiſe wee bee ſhut out of his heauenly reſt: for mine own parte (how vile ſo euer I bee) I may (I thanke my God for it) in ſinglenes of heart proteſt thus much, that it grieueth me to the heart, to ſee the
<pb facs="tcp:22757:6"/> great defectes and wantes, that I know in that behalfe: And that I haue ſome care (though not ſo great, as many other good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue, neither I able to doe ſo much as they) by trauaile in writings of mine owne, &amp; tranſlating of other mens labours, to helpe forwarde, the increaſe of knowledge, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and practiſe, that ſo Gods glorie may be aduaunced, and his Churche furthered in the way of life and ſaluation. Amongeſt the teſtimonies whereof (beſides that which I haue alreadie publiſhed to the view of the godly) I would haue this my ſimple &amp; ſmal tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation accompted alſo: wherein what I haue perfourmed, though I my ſelfe would ſay nothing, yet other men might both iudge and report, ſpecially if they were able and woulde conferre it, with the French copie. This they ſhall aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly
<pb facs="tcp:22757:7"/> finde, that where as fewe or almoſt no places of ſcripture were quoated therein, I haue added a great number, ſetting beſides in the marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſome ſhortnotes which do ſerue, both for the clearyng of ſome darke places, and alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the ſumme (as it were) of the whole matter. All that I haue done whatſoeuer it be, I offer vnto you (right worſhipful &amp; Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) &amp; in you, to the whole church of God in this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, beſeeching the Lord in mercy to remoue all my ſinnes, and ſo to make it profitable both to you and all thoſe, into whoſe handes it ſhall come. The conſiderations inducing me, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it vnto you, are indeed particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as firſt to teſtifie the vnfeigned good will, which I beare towards you in Chriſt, in whome (to bee ſhort) I haue a mynde cheareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to trauayle, what in melyeth,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:7"/> and by al the meanes that poſſibly I can, to builde you vp in ſincere knowledge, ſound zeale, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience of Gods bleſſed trueth, though the meanes and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie that I haue to performe the ſame be very ſmall and ſlender.</p>
            <p>Secondly to ſet out my duetifull thankfulneſſe, for ſundry kindneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and good turnes receiued from you, which I confeſſe to be more than I am able to requite the leaſt part, leauing the full recompence thereof too the Lorde (who hath faithfully promiſed in his woord and therefore will aſſuredly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it, ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully to reward it, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life, if he ſee it ſo good, but ſpeciallly in the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the righteous) and yet thinking it meete and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient to ſhew my ſelf at the leaſt thankful in words,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:8"/> by ſuch weake preſentes as I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to yelde.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.<hi>12.</hi>
               </note> Wherein I take this to be no ſmall comfort vnto mee, that I deale with them in whome I am perſuaded, this part of Gods image amongeſt the reſt, ſhineth foorth very clearely: to witte, that you accept of mee, and the thinges that come from me, according to that I haue, and not according to that I haue not. But the cauſes which haue led mee to publiſh the ſame for the benefite and behoofe of Gods Sainctes are as generall, ſo many, but chiefly three. Firſt, that thereby I myght giue ſome light of knowledge, to the poore ignorant people of our land, who knowe not, (becauſe I feare mee they haue ſeldome or neuer hearde the ſame) ſundrie excellent points of doctrine here propounded, and namely theſe great articles of our religion, to wit, the vnitie of the
<pb facs="tcp:22757:8"/> Godhed, &amp; the trinitie of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: the inſeparable vniting of the two natures in the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, from the tyme of his conception in the wombe of his mother: his offices, of kingdome, Prieſthoode and propheſie: Gods euerlaſting election, and his free iuſtification of vs in Chriſt, with ſuch lyke. If any man thinke theſe pointes ouer hygh for our rude people (as I knowe there are ſome men otherwiſe greatly to be reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, which ſtand muche vppon that) I would wiſh them to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not onely this, that the Lorde hath reuealed theſe pointes in his word, to the ende that they ſhould be taught vnto the people, but alſo to weigh howe that without the ſound knowledge therof, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for men euer to attain ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. So that they which ſtande ſo nicely vpon theſe matters, doe
<pb facs="tcp:22757:9"/> not onely bewray, great, either ignorance, if they can not preache them, or vnfaithfulnes, if they doe not vtter them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 20.27.</note> becauſe they keepe backe ſome part of the moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary pointes of Gods counſell, but alſo teſtifie what little hunger and thirſt they haue, for the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their brethren, who ought to bee as deare vnto them as them ſelues.<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>17.</hi>3.</note> Doth not Chriſt him ſelfe ſay, that this is lyfe eternall, that men knowe God to bee the onely very God, and him whom he hath ſent Ieſus Chriſt? And doeth not Paul pray,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.18.</note> that the Epheſians may knowe, the breadth, length, depth and height, that is all perfection if it were poſſible? Oh but it is not yet tyme to propounde them, ſay they.<note place="margin">Hebr. 5.<hi>12.</hi>
               </note> Surely then I know not whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it wilbe tyme. I feare me, leaſt that may be iuſtly verified in vs, which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the Iews,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:9"/> that whereas in reſpecte of time we ought to haue been teachers to others, yet wee haue neede, againe to haue the firſt principles of the woorde of God laide amongſt vs, and are become ſuch as haue need of milke, and not of ſtrong meate. Is it not a ſhame to be children al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes? and are not thoſe nurſes much to be blamed, that either ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not or will not in xx. yeeres ſpace teach their chyldren to ſpeake rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and to goe ſtrongly? Would to God wee might once ſet aſide the doctrine of the beginning of Chriſte,<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>6.</hi>1.</note> and be leade forwarde to perfection. And yet in all this I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe not of their curioſitie, that with vnwaſhen handes, and voide of reuerence (to the end they may be thought profounde, and deepe in iudgement amongeſt men) wil enter into vaine ſpeculations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe &amp; ſome other points
<pb facs="tcp:22757:10"/> of which ſorte are the Popiſhe Schoole Doctours, yea and many amongſt vs that to much do tread in their ſteppes. There is a meane (if we coulde ſee it, and GOD woulde geue vs grace to embrace and vſe the ſame) betweene fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall curioſitie, and beaſtly blindneſſe. It behooueth all, but ſpecially thoſe that profeſſe god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, as on the one ſide to know &amp; proue, what that good accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; perfect will of God is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.<hi>2.</hi>3</note> ſo to take heede on the other ſide, that they preſume not to vnderſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue that which is meete to vnder ſtand, but that they vnderſtand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſobrietie, and as GOD hath dealt to euery man the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſaith: and ſeeing ſecreate things belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the Lord our God to leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him alone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29, 29.</note> leaſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe entering into the curious ſearching of them out, we be ouer
<pb facs="tcp:22757:10"/> whelmed of his glory: and again ſeeing that the things reuealed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to vs, and to our children for euer, in care and conſcience to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour all the dayes of our life to a diligent perfourma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſame, rather then to entangle our ſelues with fables, genealogies and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous queſtions, which breede conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions and brawlinges, rather than godly edifiyng,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4.</note> which is by faith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that by this meanes I might ſtopp (if it were poſſible) the mouthes of brawling and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentious Papiſtes, who ſtande ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry muche vpon that Fable of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters being at Rome (the principall bullwarke of the Popes ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie) and that ſame diueliſhe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of mens merites, tendyng to the great diſhonour of almighty God and the woonderful diſgrace of our ſauiour Chriſtes obedience
<pb facs="tcp:22757:11"/> both whiche and ſundry other pointes in controuerſie betwixt vs and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe ſpeaches large<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ficientlie handl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, who either <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough alredy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe pointes: or elſe woulde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them through forgetfulneſſe too die out of theyr remembraunce: For the firſt ſort, may eaſily be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>futed, by the pitifull practiſe &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table experience, that the Lord hath ſhewed vs, &amp; daily doth ſhew vs to the contrary: a better proof we cannot haue in my poore opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, than that accurſed rebellion in the North, Cutbert Maines pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiſes in the weſt, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ouer of Buls and Bables, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a woonderfull number not onely of old ſubtil foxes and cruel wolues, which lie lurking in their
<pb facs="tcp:22757:11"/> holes, waiting for the darke night of ignoraunce and blindnes, wher in they may rauine to the ful, as heretofore they haue done, but of young cubbes alſo, ſundry of them little aboue twentie yeeres olde (a woefull thing to behold) who are not aſhamed, priuately in corners, and openly in great aſſemblies (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r maieſties Commiſſioners for ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Eccleſiaſtical, I am ſure can well reporte) boldly too ſpeake for, and ſtifly to defend after their beaſtly maner, ſundrie points and principles of that popiſhe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And as for the other who woulde haue Poperie weare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, without naming of it, I ſaye that they offende doubly: firſt in that they fight directly againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For let a man ſow what good and wholeſome ſeedes hee can in his garden, and haue not a care for
<pb facs="tcp:22757:12"/> the cleane keeping thereof, as that it may be throughly weeded, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time and ſeaſon requireth, no doubt, but that (as experience alſo teacheth vs) it wyll in ſhorte tyme be cleane ouergrowne, &amp; become (as we ſay) a Wilderneſſe or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, if not altogeather paſt hope of recouery, yet dangerous and chargeable to attempt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly in that they doe not enter into a deepe conſideration, of the corruption of mans nature, and Satans cunning in this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſhift.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19.20.</note> That man is inclined to loue darkeneſſe, and to hate the light,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.<hi>5. Gen.</hi> 8.21.</note> yea that he deuiſeth &amp; doth all the meanes wherby he may continue therein, is more plaine then needeth to ſtande vppon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that al the thoughts and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his hart are euill, and that euery day, yea euery houre of a
<pb facs="tcp:22757:12"/> day, and euerye moment of an houre, from his youth vpwarde. And what Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meaneth hereby, they that are acquainted with the depth of his aſſaultes, may eaſily perceiue, to wit, ſtill to keepe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their old Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and ſuperſtition. This rather reſteth in my iudgement careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be forſeene vnto, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be performed, that is, that as the doctrine of trueth, ſhoulde bee more often ſounded into the eares and heartes of the poore ignorant people, and that Romiſhe religion ſoundly &amp; with autority confuted by the Miniſters and preachers of the woorde: ſo all the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, are humbly and earneſtly to bee intreated, and that on Gods behalfe and the peoples, to drawe out the ſwoorde of iuſtice, and execute the ſame vppon the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient rebellious, and obſtinate ſort:
<pb facs="tcp:22757:13"/> which if it might bee, yet now at the length practiſed, no doubt but it woulde ſomwhat delay the heate of theſe luſty bloodes (as you would ſay) that ſpare not to broch and ſpreade abroade deceaueable errors (which the auncient among them, ſuppoſed great clarkes and gray headed men, dare not openly and in plaine termes aduouch for feare of ſome puniſhment) and bewray the hardhartedneſſe, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kred malice, and curſed hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, of that horned generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who then, either for feare of due pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhement, would renounce their religion, though it were but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblingly, or elſe declare their want of wit, and wilfulneſſe, in yeelding theyr bodies a ſacrifice to Satan, as Story, Felton, Maine and ſome other haue doone,</p>
            <p>The third &amp; laſt reaſon is, that
<pb facs="tcp:22757:13"/> I might in Chriſt comfort ſome, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I know to be ſore preſſed &amp; beaten downe, with the fearefull feeling of the weight, of their own greeuous iniquities &amp; transgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo in charitie reache out my hande, to helpe them what in me lyeth, out of the clawes and clouches of ſinne and Satan. It is very true that the Authour doeth not of purpoſe handle in theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, that moſt ſweete pointe: and yet notwithſtanding, ſhall the afflicted conſcience finde herein, many notable ſentences te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to that ende, which if they bee well weighed, &amp; rightly applied to the ſoule, will no doubt be both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and profitable too them: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable, in that they will ſerue to raiſe them vp in ſpirituall ioye, and aſſured hope, of the free pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and full forgiuenes of all theyr
<pb facs="tcp:22757:14"/> ſinnes, thorow Chriſtes death and bleſſed obedience: and profitable in this, that they ſhal inſtruct them to walke, with greater care &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of perfourmaunce, both of generall &amp; ſpeciall dueties, before God and their brethren, than here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore they haue done. Nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this number is very ſmal (for Satan and ſinne hold the moſt part of men Captiues in ſenſeleſnes of their euill) I thinke it good in this place to adde this warnyng: that my meanyng is not heereby to worke careleſnes, in the harts and heads of any whatſoeuer diſſolute perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, (who I know are ouer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, to ſnatch that to them ſelues, which doeth not belong vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and vnder that pretence to abuſe Gods goodnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude.</hi> 4.</note> and to turne his grace into wantonnes:) but to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter comforte of conſcience ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to thoſe that are caſt downe,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:14"/> with the true taſte and feelyng of their filthineſſe, and the wrath of God agaynſt them for the ſame: whoſe caſe though for a whyle it be miſerable in reſpect of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and lamentable and pitiful to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that are truly touched with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charitie, and vnfeigned good will in the Lord towardes them, yet is the ſtate of it ſelfe profitable, becauſe that thereby, as it were, by a bridle, the Lorde withholdeth his from running ryote, with the reſt of the world, and ſhalbe in the ende (aſſuredly) comfortable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that being exerciſed in that ſchoolehouſe of God, and feelyng the ioy and comfort of him, that is the father of mercyes, and the God of all comfort,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> they ſhall bee able, not onely to comfort them ſelues, but to comfort others alſo which are in any afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by that comforte, wherewith they them ſelues are comforted of hym.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:15"/>
            <p>So that, ſo farre of ſhould we bee, from diſliking either in our ſelues or others, this feeling eſtate of our owne wretchednes and miſerie, that wee ſhould rather eſteeme of it, as one of the ſpecialleſt bleſſings that can come vnto vs in this lyfe: as whereby indeed Gods glorie is greatly magnified, his mercy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilouſly manifeſted, wee oure ſelues rightly inſtructed, in care &amp; conſcience to walke before him, and others which are afflicted, in vs &amp; by vs Chriſtianlie comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thorow Chriſt. But touchyng this point, and the particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, that God hath left vs in his worde, to cheare vs vp, when we ſhalbe ſo caſt downe, I ſhal ſay more hereafter God willing, in a ſeuerall treatie that I haue begun (if the Lorde ſtrengthen me to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it) of that queſtion and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In the mean while, I beſeech
<pb facs="tcp:22757:15"/> all Gods children, and amongeſt the reſt, you (Right woorſhipfull and Honorable) as moſt deare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, to accept of that louingly, which I haue preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly don &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed vnder your names, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be: Wherof, this is all that I minde to ſay at this tyme, that as the Authors worthie name &amp; iuſt credite, can not but commend the matter: So theſe fewe lines that I haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as my bodely weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; inwarde grieues would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer mee) touchyng ſome pointes (wherein I might haue bene long and large I confeſſe) will bee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient I hope, to ſtirre vp the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader, the better to loue and lyke, and the more willingly and diligently to read and peruſe, this prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t treatiſe, that ſo he may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite in ſound knowledge and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed obedienee: which if it ſhall pleaſe God in mercy to graunt, I
<pb facs="tcp:22757:16"/> ſhall haue that which I greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and ſo ſhall thinke my poore paines well beſtowed, beſides all that, I ſhalbe thereby incouraged, to goe forwarde with ſome other work (as occaſion ſhal ſerue, &amp; the Lord ſhal inable me) either of this excellent mans, or mine own. The god of al grace bleſſe you both, &amp; al yours, with the whole houſhold of faith whereſoeuer, making vs al thorow the ſingle ſight, of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual &amp; bodily wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts whatſoeuer, in aſſured perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to repaire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, who hath a ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful ſupply for all diſtreſſes, that ſo we may in the end truely magnifie, the riche grace and mercy of this our good God in Chriſt. So be it. At Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, the 20. day of this Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. 1579.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips &amp; Honors alwayes readie and humble. <hi>T. W.</hi> The Lords moſt vnworthie.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:17"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A Propoſition, or ſpeach</hi> made by M. Iohn Caluin, vppon <hi>the beginning of the Goſpell accordyng</hi> to Saint Iohn, in which the deitie or Godhead of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt is excellently prooued.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> In the beginning was that woord, and that woorde was with GOD, and that word was God.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> This ſame was in the beginning with God.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Al things were made by it: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it was nothing made of that which was made.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> In it was life, and that life was the light of men.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> And that light ſhineth in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the darkneſſe comprehended it not.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His woorde Goſpel,<note place="margin">The word Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell what it meaneth.</note> ſignifieth the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that God hath ſhewed vs, of his loue in our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, when hee ſent hym into the
<pb facs="tcp:22757:18"/> worlde: which thing we ought well to marke, becauſe it is very much to know the vſe of the holy Scripture, euen in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the wordes it vſeth. It is true that wee ought not to ſtande ſimply or onely vpon the wordes: and yet for all that we are not able to comprehend how excellent Gods doctrine is, vnleſſe wee knowe the proceeding that it vſeth, and alſo what is the ſtyle and ſpeach thereof. And indeede wee are ſo muche the more to mark &amp; weigh this word, becauſe it is a very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon receiued ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the holy Scripture into the law &amp; the Goſpel:<note place="margin">Diuiſion of the Scripture.</note> &amp; thoſe that ſpeake thereof in that ſort, meane, that all the promyſes which are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Teſtament, ought too bee referred to this word <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> True it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr meaning is good, but for all that, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Scripture vſeth not ſuch maner of ſpeache,<note place="margin">If any man ſpeake, let hym ſpeake as the words of God. <hi>1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11.</hi>
               </note> and we ought to be ſober in that reſpect, and to yeelde ſuch a reuerence too Gods ſpirite, as to keepe ſuche a maner of ſpeaking as hee himſelf vſeth to teach vs withall. Behold thus muche then concerning the woorde <hi>Goſpell,</hi> which is a publiſhing that God
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22757:18"/> hath made vnto vs at the commyng of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte his ſonne, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring himſelf a father to all the world: as alſo Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh thereof in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> when he ſaith that Ieſus Chriſte came to preache the Goſpell vnto them that were nigh, &amp; to thoſe that were farre of from God: nigh, to wit, the Iewes, who were alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye entred into the Couenaunt with God: and far, to wit, of the <hi>Pagans</hi> and Heathen, who are as it were far remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from his Church. Nowe when wee ſhall haue looked euery where, we ſhall finde that this woorde <hi>Goſpell</hi> is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in any other ſignification. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde alſo wherfore men haue giuen this name or title to the iiii. hiſtories that are written touching our Lord Ieſus Chriſt howe hee came into the worlde, and was conuerſant therein: howe he dyed, roſe agayne, and went vp into heauen: men I ſay, haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name or title of the Goſpell to this. And why ſo? becauſe the ſubſtance of the Goſpell is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the perſon of God his ſonne as I haue already ſaid. The ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers
<pb facs="tcp:22757:19"/> had in deede the promyſes of ſaluation: they were alſo very well aſſured that God woulde be their father,<note place="margin">The difference betwene the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vnder the law, and vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the goſpel.</note> but yet they had not (in ſuch plaine ſort as we haue) the gage and pledge of Gods loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them, and of their owne adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For when Ieſus Chriſte came intoo the worlde, then God ſigned and ſealed his fatherly loue vnto vs, and wee had the full teſtimonie of life, and in deede haue alſo the ſubſtaunce thereof in Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</note> as I haue already ſayde. And this is the cauſe why S. Paule ſayth <hi>that all Gods promiſes are in him, yea and Amen:</hi> to wit, becauſe then God ratified and confirmed all that which he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before, &amp; had promiſed to men. So then it is not without cauſe that theſe foure hiſtories (wherein is declared vnto vs how the ſonne of God was ſent, that he tooke mans fleſhe, alſo that hee liued heere vppon earth amongeſt men) haue beene ſo named. Men then haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended all this vnder the worde <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8.</note> becauſe therein it is declared and ſet out vnto vs, how God hath made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and accompliſhed al that which was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22757:19"/> requſite for mens ſaluation, and that wee haue had the fullfilling of al, in the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſonne. Indeede S. Paul ſpeaketh of his Goſpell, but after what ſort? It is not as though he had writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an hiſtory of the Goſpell, but becauſe his doctrine was conformable and agreeable, to all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is conteined therin. So according to that which I haue already ſaid, when the Goſpell was preached vnto vs,<note place="margin">S. Paules E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the goſpell, &amp; in what ſence</note> it is a plaine manifeſting of Ieſus Chriſt to the ende that wee ſhoulde knowe that in him all thinges are perfected, and that we haue the trueth of that, which had bin promiſed in all times before. And yet for all this, S. Paules Epiſtles, are not cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the Goſpel. And why ſo? becauſe that therein we haue not a continual hiſtorie which declareth vnto vs after what ſort God ſent his ſonne, how it pleaſed him that in putting vpon him our nature, hee might haue a true brotherhood with vs, how he died, roſe againe, and aſcended in to heauen. This I ſay, is not largely laid out, with a continuall order and courſe of ſpeach in S. Paule, very certaine is it, that the doctrine which is conteined in his Epiſtles, is conformable and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="tcp:22757:20"/> with the doctrine of the Goſpell: But for all that, that worde <hi>Goſpell,</hi> is ſpecially attributed too theſe foure hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, for the reaſon which I haue alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy alleadged. Nowe where wee ſay that the ſubſtaunce of the Goſpel is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the perſon of the Sonne of God, this is not onely to ſay that Ieſus Chriſt came into the worlde, but that we ſhould know alſo what his office is, what charge God his father hath committed vnto him, and what vertue and power he hath, which thing wee ought too marke well: for from thence wee may gather the difference of the Goſpell according to S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wherin the <hi>4.</hi> Euangeliſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. <hi>Heb. <hi>4.15.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </note> and thoſe which the other three wrote. The iiii. Euangeliſts agree very well in this, that they declare vnto vs, howe the ſonne of God appeared in the worlde, that he became true and very man, like vnto vs in al thing, ſinne excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Afterwardes they declare vnto vs, howe he dyed, roſe againe, and aſcended into heauen. To bee ſhort, all that was committed vnto him, to drawe vs to god his father by, is declared and ſet foorth vnto vs therein. But there are two thinges whiche are peculiar too Saint
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22757:20"/> 
               <hi>Iohn:</hi> One is,<note place="margin">Iohn hath two things peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar too himſelfe from the other Euangeliſts.</note> that hee ſtayeth and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt, more then the other Euangeliſts doe: The other, that with a greater liuelynes he declareth vnto vs Ieſus Chriſtes ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power. True it is, that the other Euangeliſtes ſpeake wel of the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſte, but that is rather briefly &amp; ſhortly, as who haue collected ſome ſmall Summaries and Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes thereof.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.1.2.</note> But <hi>S. Iohn</hi> maketh a long &amp; large declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, as we ſee in the ſixth Chapter, where mention is made of that myracle which he wrought in the wilderneſſe, when hee refreſhed and fed ſo great a multitude. For there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon <hi>S. Iohn</hi> commeth to enter into ſpeach and to ſhewe howe Ieſus Chriſte is the bread of eternall life. We ſee then this doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt, which was declared at large by <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> and that with a more great dilating &amp; diſcourſing thereon, then is ſet out by the other Euangeliſtes, yea we ſee that they quite and cleane omitted that doctrine. So much alſo may be ſayde of the reſte: for after that hee hath touched ſome myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb facs="tcp:22757:21"/> and hiſtories, he alwayes commeth back to the doctrine, and taketh occaſion too enter into the matter too handle and ſpeake of the power of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 12. <hi>to</hi> 18.</note> as from the xii. Chapter til you come to the hiſtorie of the Paſſion he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treteth of nothing, but this doctrine. So then nowe wee ſee what difference there is betwene the Goſpel according to S. Iohn,<note place="margin">The Goſpel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to S. Io. giueth light to the other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes.</note> and the other three Euangeliſtes, inſomuch, that to ſpeake rightly, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell according to S. Iohn, is, as it were the key, too geue vs ſome entraunce and opening to the other. For yf wee reade S. Matthew, S. Marke, and S. Luke, we ſhall not ſo well know wherefore Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte was ſent into the worlde, as when we ſhall haue read S. Iohn. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reade S. Iohn, wee ſhall knowe afterwardes too what ende it ſerueth vs, that Ieſus Chriſte hath wrought, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that he hath taken mans fleſhe, and that he died and roſe agayne: Wee ſhall knowe I ſay, what is the ende and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of all theſe thinges in reading this Goſpell. And this is the cauſe why he ſtandeth not ſo much vpon the hiſtory,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22757:21"/> as we ſhall ſee by the order which he wil keepe hereafter. It is true, that theſe things rightly deſerue, to be more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diducted &amp; layd out: but becauſe there is great matter in the Texte which wee haue to expounde, I doe but touche theſe thinges as briefly as I can. Wherefore let vs content our ſelues with that which we haue ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marily &amp; ſhortly touched, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the office of Ieſus Chriſte:<note place="margin">Wherfore Chriſt came in to the world.</note> that is to ſay, that S. Iohn declareth vnto vs how he was ſent of God his father, to the end he might accompliſh and make per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the ſaluation of men. Hee declareth howe he tooke mans fleſhe, nnd howe hee dyed alſo, and roſe againe, that he is the pledge of Gods loue, that hee is (as it were) the ſoule of our redemption, &amp; that Gods promiſes are in hym ratified and eſtabliſhed. Moreouer wee muſt marke (as I haue already ſayde) that S. Iohn toucheth the ſtories more briefly then the other three Euangeliſtes doe,<note place="margin">The ſumme of the Goſpell ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to S. Iohn.</note> but for all that he ſtayeth him ſelfe more vppon the ſubſtance of the matter, that is to ſay, too declare vntoo vs what the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſte is: and what charge
<pb facs="tcp:22757:22"/> God the father hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto him: and to be ſhort, what is his vertue, his power, and goodneſſe towardes vs. As concerning the ſignification of the worde in it ſelfe, <hi>Goſpell</hi> is aſmuch too ſaye, as a good newes or glad tidinges: but this worde ought to be vnto vs as it were hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed or ſanctified, to the end to cauſe vs to hate the thinges of this worlde, and to the ende that we might knowe, that all our goodneſſe and our felicitie, ioye, and glory is in Ieſus Chriſt alone. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when we ſhall pronounce or ſpeake this woorde <hi>Goſpell,</hi> which is as muche to ſay, as good newes or glad tidinges: Let vs learn not to reioyce beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in the thinges of this worlde which are brittle and vayne: let vs not reioyce in delights,<note place="margin">Wherein true Chriſtians ſhoulde chiefly reioyce.</note> in pleaſures, nor in any thing whatſoeuer it be: but let vs be glad and reioyce in this, that Chriſte was ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that God is offered and geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too vs in his perſon: that Ieſus Chriſte is come too the ende that hee myght bee our reconciliation betweene God and vs that God accepteth vs for his children, to the end we ſhoulde not periſhe and be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22757:22"/> condemned. Behold how this word ought to be ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified or hallowed vnto vs, to the ende to cauſe vs reuerently to regarde that ineſtimable goodneſſe, which hath been brought vnto vs by our Lord Ieſus Chriſte. And it is expreſly ſayd, that this Goſpell is according to <hi>S. Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Goſpel is from Ieſus Chriſte. <hi>Iohn. <hi>7.16.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </note> too the ende we ſhould know, that it is not from a mortall man, but that <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> was one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the miniſter or meane thereof. From whom then ſhall wee ſay that wee holde the Goſpell? From <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> or from Ieſus Chriſte? Certainly from Ieſus Chriſte. And in deede Ieſus Chriſte v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this maner of ſpeach, as to ſay, that the doctrine is not his, but that he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it in the authoritie of God his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from whom it proceeded: and all this is to the end that wee ſhould beare ſo muche the more reuerence to this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and that we ſhoulde not receiue it, as a common thing, but as the pure trueth of God, which was preached and declared by his onely ſonne. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> then was indeede the meane or inſtrument that God vſed, euen as a Penne that wil write in a mans hande, but yet for all
<pb facs="tcp:22757:23"/> that wee muſt not receiue the Goſpell, which was written by him, as from a mortall man. Let vs nowe come to the Text. <hi>The worde</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</hi> The purpoſe of Saint Iohn is too declare vnto vs how the ſonne of god did not then beginne to bee, when hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared or ſhewed himſelfe in the worlde: neyther yet that then he began onely too ſpread abroad his power in euery place,<note place="margin">Chriſt is very God from all eternitie.</note> (for he was alredy from all time, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore al time, his power abroade alreadye in hymſelfe, and hee tooke it not from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other) but that there was a power which was in the worde of GOD from the beginning, which at the laſt was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, and we know it now, ſeeing Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath been ſent into the world. Wherefore S. Iohn mente too declare here that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt came into the world, he that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e was our eternal God, who alſo hath redeemed vs. But yet to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende that wee may the better vnderſtand the whole, wee muſt particularly and by peecemeale marke the thinges that are here ſpoken. <hi>The worde was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:22757:23"/> There is no doubte, but that hee heere calleth the Sonne of God <hi>The woorde.</hi> The reaſon is,<note place="margin">Why Chriſt is called the word.</note> becauſe it is that very wiſedome which hath alwayes byn in GOD, and his Counſell, and his power. True it is, that wee haue not in this place the thinges declared and ſet out, as they are in their owne great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and excellencie, I meane, euen as they are here propounded and ſet foorth vnto vs by S. Iohn. For albeit that the ſpirite of God ſpake by his mouth, yet ſo it is, that he hath not yet declared and ſet foorth the matters vnto vs, in theyr greatneſſe and maieſtie.<note place="margin">The Lord in ſetting out him ſelf &amp; Chriſt to vs, had reſpect to our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> And heerein we derogate nothing from the ſpirite of God, when wee ſay, that he hath not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in perfection ſet out the thinges which are heere ſignified vnto vs, for the holye Ghoſte therein applieth him ſelfe vntoo our infirmitie and weakeneſſe. And indeede, yf wee ſhould heare God, ſpeaking vnto vs in his maieſtie, it ſhold bee vtterly vnprofitable for vs, becauſe wee coulde comprehende or conceiue nothyng thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:24"/>
            <p>So then, becauſe we be carnall, hee muſt needes ſtut and ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer as it were, or elſe he woulde not be vnderſtoode of vs. By this then we ſee, that wee are too vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that God is as it were become little, and hath abaſed him ſelf, that he might declare hymſelfe vnto vs: And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo it is, tell me, how ſhould it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to expreſſe what Gods maieſtie is, If we ſpeake mens ſpeach and wordes? Is it not think you a farre vnequall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? S. Iohn then albeit he be the holy Ghoſts inſtrument, ſpeaketh not of theſe matters, according to their greatnes, and yet notwithſtanding hee ſpeaketh in a ſpeache, whiche is as it were vnknowne to vs. And therefore wee muſt conclude, that the ſecretes which are conteined in this place, are not ſo openly and plainly declared, as that wee are able too vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſame, in ſuch ſort as we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the matters of the worlde: but let vs content our ſelues with that which is heere ſimply declared vntoo vs:<note place="margin">God hath in his worde reuealed ſufficient for his children.</note> for our Lorde knewe that which was ſufficient for our good, and hee applied hymſelfe vntoo vs and our infirmitie, in ſuche ſorte
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22757:24"/> that hee hath not forgotten or omitted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which was good and profitable for vs to know. So let vs learne to keepe vs faſte too this puritie and ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of his doctrine, conſidering how the worlde in this behalf hath been fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed by fooliſh imaginations, and vaine ſpeculations, and by a certayne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueliſh boldneſſe: For when the queſtion hath beene to handle theſe matters, men haue ouerwhelmed themſelues in aſmuch as they ment (beſides the reuelation of of the doctrine) to ſearch out w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a certaine curioſitie and boldneſſe, the eternall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and beyng of Almightie God: as a man in the Papacie ſhall heare diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations that are made thereof, euen as if men diſputed of a flocke of Gotes, or I knowe not whereof. They haue no more reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a beaſt: Now we neede not ſeeke out a better witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the doctrine of the <hi>Sophiſters</hi> of <hi>Sorbone</hi> to knowe that the Diuell raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth there,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sorbone,</hi> is the name of the place, wher the brotherhood of the <hi>Sorboni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes,</hi> doe yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manine to this day in <hi>Parris.</hi>
               </note> and hath alwayes raigned there, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this. And this I ſay, that albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it theyr doctrine were not falſe, yet ſo it is that when men ſee they haue ſo little
<pb facs="tcp:22757:25"/> reuerence and regarde to Gods maieſty, wee muſt needes ſay that it is a diueliſhe doctrine, euen that I meane, which is at this day practiſed, by the <hi>Sophiſters</hi> and <hi>Sorboniſtes,</hi> in all the Popes Colledges. So then, let vs (as I haue ſaide) content our ſelues with that ſimplicitie, which is declared vnto vs by the holy ſpirite, for he toucheth and ſpeaketh of that which is good and profitable for our ſaluation: and as I haue already declared hee hath heere brought and deliuered vnto vs that which was meete and fit for vs to know.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> 1.17. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>man.</hi> 11.29.</note> Let vs come nowe to this true <hi>woorde.</hi> When S. Iohn calleth Ieſus Chriſte, <hi>That worde,</hi> it is as if he ſhould ſay: the eternall counſell of God, or the wiſdome that remayneth in him. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding we muſt marke that GOD is not like to men: when wee haue a Counſell it may alter and chaunge, but it is not ſo with GOD: for that which is in GOD is vnchaungeable.<note place="margin">Though man be wauering, yet God is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> Beſides the counſell which wee haue, is not our very Eſſence or ſubſtance: but the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell which is in God, is verily and truely
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22757:25"/> God: for God is not as a vaile or couer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wher there are ſhadowie places, as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> vſeth this ſimilitude,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 1.17.</note> we are as a ſhadowe that flitteth vp &amp; down, and we cannot abide firme and conſtant. But this is not in God: for that which is in him, is of his eſſence and eternitie. And this is the cauſe wherfore S. <hi>Iohn</hi> declareth, that this word is verely &amp; truly God. But as concerning the worde, we muſt not (as I haue alreadie ſaide) ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine a counſell or a wiſedome in God, which ſhould be like to the word of men. True it is, that we may well take ſome compariſon from our ſelues, but yet we ought alwayes to marke, the long di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and great difference, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and God:<note place="margin">An apt ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> for if the heauens be much higher than the earth, muche more muſt it needes be, that we ſhoulde knowe and confeſſe, that God is more high than we, yea there is no proportion or reſemblance as it were betweene God and men. So then when men ſhall bring or alledge vnto vs ſome ſimilitude taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the creatures, we muſt alwayes mark this great diſtance and difference, which
<pb facs="tcp:22757:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> is betweene God and vs.<note place="margin">There are two partes or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of a mans ſoule, to wit, vnderſtanding and will. See his Inſtitut. <hi>Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>15.</hi> Sect. <hi>5.7.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </note> As a man may very well ſay, that in the ſoule of a man, there is a certaine vnderſtanding, which is in ſuch ſort ioyned to the ſoule, that the ſoule can not be without vnderſtanding. There is alſo a will, not as when wee haue nowe one deſire, nowe another, but a certaine power (as a man woulde ſay) to wil, which thing man hath in him ſelf, for man is not as a ſtone, or as a pile of woode without ſenſe and reaſon, but hee hath imprinted in him this propertie, to will this or that. So then we may take and vſe ſuch ſimilitudes: but yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we muſt conſider, that ſpeach is here had of ſo high thinges, as of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie all mans vnderſtanding and witte muſt be abaſed and brought lowe: and we muſt handle them, and intreat of them in all humilitie, applying them to their true meaning,<note place="margin">Curioſitie and vaine imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions muſt be auoided.</note> and muſt not be ouer curious: wee then haue that fonde imagination which hath borne ſwaye and ruled here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore in the world: but we muſt come to Gods ſchoole, to hearken to that which hee ſhall ſpeake vnto vs, and to flye
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22757:26"/> from all that which men ſhall ſet out, and ſhalbe found contrary to that,<note place="margin">Gods voice muſt onely be obeied.</note> which the holie Ghoſt hath left vs. Nowe further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more we muſt alſo marke, that ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bene thruſt forwarde by the deuil, haue peruerted the meaning of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, affirming that this word was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els, but ſome certaine counſell, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation and purpoſe that God had to redeeme mankinde in the perſon of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt (who was a certaine forme,<note place="margin">A perillous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> as they call him, as when a man ſhall haue purpoſed to doſome worke, and ſhal haue conceaued the ſame in his ſpirite or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding) leauing not by ſo ſaying, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtingneſſe of eſſence or being to the ſonne of God. But we ſee alreadie, and ſhall ſee hereafter more largely, how and in what ſort Saint Iohn calleth Ieſus Chriſt that word of God, thereby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and ſet out his deitie, as I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie ſaide. And that ſo it is, beholde a plaine teſtimonie of God him ſelfe, for he ſaieth, that this worde was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: ſo then it muſt needes be, that it hath beene eternall and euerlaſtyng.
<pb facs="tcp:22757:27"/> It is true,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1.</note> that ſome will replie againſt it, becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>that God in the beginning created heauen and earth:</hi> and that now S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>that this worde was in the beginning,</hi> that it ſeemeth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, ſeeing that ſo it is, that the heauen, the earth, and other creatures had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, that we can not proue, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie or euerlaſtingnes of Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe it is ſaide that the worde was in the beginning.<note place="margin">An obiection anſwered.</note> But the anſwere is eaſie: to wit, that when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh of the beginning, we are to remember &amp; mark whereof he ſpeaketh: that is of heauen, of earth and other thinges, that haue indeed a beginning. But nowe let vs weigh and marke, that which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith: <hi>In the beginning</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was that worde.</hi> And where was the beginning? verely in God. And what is Gods beginning, I pray you? Certainely he had none: for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it muſt needes be, that God ſhould be framed &amp; made. So that when mention is made of the beginning of God, we muſt conclude, that it is ſuch a beginning, as hath not any tyme at all. There is then much to be ſaid, and great
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22757:27"/> difference alſo, betwene <hi>Moſes</hi> his place, when he ſaith, <hi>that God created all in the beginning,</hi> and this, when it is ſaid, <hi>that that word was in the beginning.</hi> For <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſpeaketh of the creatures, which had their beginning to be at a certaine time. But here Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh not of any thing but of God, which can not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his eternitie and euerlaſtingneſſe. Wherefore we muſt conclude, that this beginning, hath not any beginning. And hereby we ſee that Ieſus Chriſt hath bene alwayes. It is as much then,<note place="margin">Ieſus Chriſt is our God eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. <hi>1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</hi>
               </note> as if Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> had ſaide, that Ieſus Chriſt is our eternall God, who hath appeared and bene made manifeſt vnto vs in the fleſh, as alſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Nowe he addeth afterwardes: <hi>This word was with God:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay you muſt of neceſſitie ſeparate and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh him from all creatures. Marke the purpoſe of the Euangeliſt. We muſt not ſo much as imagine (ſaith he) that this word had any thing at all, like vnto crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: we muſt go out of the worlde, we muſt aſcend aboue the earth and heauen, when we thinke vpon this worde. A man
<pb facs="tcp:22757:28"/> might demaund,<note place="margin">A hard queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on anſwered.</note> Before there was ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heauen or earth, was it poſſible, that this worde ſhoulde be in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? yea indeede, for S. Iohn for a ful anſwere, ſeperateth this worde from all the creatures: as if he ſhould ſay, when I ſpeake vnto you of this worde, you muſt come to God, for it is in God. Let vs then regarde and conſider it, as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine eternitie or euerlaſtingneſſe, which is not in the creatures, neither in the heauen, nor in the earth, nor in any thing whatſoeuer. And notwithſtanding all this, yet ſo it is, that the Euangeliſt in this place ſetteth out vnto vs,<note place="margin">The father di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtincted from the ſonne, not in eſſence, but in perſon. <hi>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4.6. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.</hi>
               </note> a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene God and his worde. And what maner a one is this diſtinction? It is not of their eſſence, for he meaneth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that this worde is God: and we muſt conclude, ſeeing that wee haue but one onely God, and that there is but one ſimple eſſence or being in him, that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that is to ſay, this eternall worde whereof mention is made in this place, hath not beene ſeparated or ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from God his father, in reſpect of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22757:28"/> eſſence: and yet notwithſtanding there is ſome diſtinction. And how is that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? thus it is; becauſe we are not able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende that which is ſo high aboue all our vnderſtanding and reaſon, the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Doctors haue vſed the worde <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and haue ſaide, that in God there are three perſons:<note place="margin">Howe there are three perſons in the Godhead.</note> not as wee ſpeake in our common ſpeache, calling three men three perſons, or els as in the Popedom, they will bee ſo bolde as to point three Puppets or Munkeyes, and ſay, Lo the Trinitie: but this worde perſons in this matter, is vſed plainely to expreſſe and ſet out the proprieties, that are in the eſſence of God. The worde ſubſtance, or (as the Greekes ſpeake) Hypoſtaſis is indeede more meete and conuenient, becauſe it is a worde of holy ſcripture, and the Apoſtle vſeth it in the firſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of his Epiſtle to the Hebrewes, when hee ſaieth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.3.</note> that Ieſus Chriſt is the liuely image, and the brightnes of the glorie, yea the image or ingraued forme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance or perſon of God his Father. When he ſpeaketh in that place
<pb facs="tcp:22757:29"/> of the ſubſtaunce or perſon of God, hee meaneth not the eſſence or being, but he ſpeaketh of this proprietie which is in the father, to wit, that he is the fountaine of all thinges.<note place="margin">Gods word onely, muſt be the rule of our faith, in all pointes, but ſpecially in the article of the Trinitie.</note> But nowe let vs looke to their three ſubſtances or perſons, as we call them, and marke howe they accorde and agree, ſo farfoorth, as God teacheth vs concerning them (as I haue alreadie ſaid:) for we muſt not at any hand go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde theſe boundes and limittes. And therefore let vs haue an eye thereto, ſo farforth as ſhalbe requiſite, for the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the place. When men ſpeake of God, true it is that men of them ſelues are confounded, and knowe not what to thinke or imagine, ſauing that they goe aſtraie in their owne cogitations and thoughtes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaieth: and thereupon it falleth out, that they waxe thereof ouer proude, through their owne prudencie and wiſedome: and therefore God alſo doeth in ſuch ſort puniſh them, that they intangle them ſelues, in ſuche horrible labyrinthes &amp; mazes, that they can not at any hand come out. But when we will ſuffer God to guide vs vnto him
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22757:29"/> ſelfe by the holie ſcripture,<note place="margin">The Trinitie proued.</note> we ſhal know him ſo farforth as ſhalbe neceſſarie and meete for vs. For we ſhal come to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as to the fountaine of all thinges: and then we can not conceiue or thinke vpon the father without his counſell and eternall wiſedome: beſides there is a certaine vertue &amp; power that remaineth in him, which we ſhall alſo perceiue and feele verie well. Marke then howe we ſhall finde theſe three proprieties in the eſſence of God. And this is that which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ment to ſaye in this place, that <hi>that word was with God.</hi> If there were not ſome diſtinction, he could not ſpeake ſo, for that ſhould be to ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly to ſay, God was with him ſelfe. So then let vs knowe, that this worde hath ſome diſtinction, and is indeed to be diſtinguiſhed from the heauenly father:<note place="margin">Chriſt begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from before all beginnings.</note> for it is that worde, that was begotten from before all tyme, ſeeing that God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had his counſell and his wiſdom. And we muſt not for all that ſo much as imagine or thinke vpon a beginning: for we may not ſay, that God hath at any tyme beene without his vnderſtanding,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:30"/> counſell and wiſedome. So then wee muſt not ſette aſide, and ſeparate from God the proprietie of this worde, as to ſay, that we could iudge, that there had bene ſome certaine tyme wherein it had not bene with God: for this ſhould be to make an idole of it,<note place="margin">The Trinitie, deſtroieth not the vnitie: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth the vnitie infringe the Trinitie. <hi>Gregor. Nazi. in ſermo. de ſacro Baſil.</hi>
               </note> as it were. But as I haue ſaide, the three perſons are but one God: and yet for all that we muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them, becauſe there is a certayne and an aſſured diſtinction of them, as is in this place declared. And with al let vs remember an olde Doctours ſentence, which is verie worthie to be thought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe it is excellent. I can not (ſaith he) thinke vpon theſe three propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, that are ſet out vnto mee in God, but that immediatly my vnderſtandyng commeth backe againe to one: and on the other ſide, it is impoſſible for me to know one onely God, but that I regarde and looke vpon all the three proprieties, and ſee them diſtinguiſhed in mine owne vnderſtanding, according to the light, which is giuen me thereof in the holie ſcripture. Beholde howe the faithfull ſhall knowe God: knowing the father,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22757:30"/> they will come to his wiſedome, who is this word of which there is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this place, they will come alſo incontinently. to that vertue and power wherof we haue in parte ſaide ſomewhat. And when they ſhall haue once knowne theſe three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, they will not any more ſtraggle and wander hither and thither, but they will come to this one and onely eſſence, to knowe that there is no more but one onely God, yea ſuch a one and onely God indeede, as hath in ſuch ſort created the worlde, that he hath not left vndone any thing of all that, which was requiſite and neceſſary to accompliſh our redemption. Thus much then wee are to marke, as concerning that which is ſaide, that <hi>this worde was with God,</hi> to wit,<note place="margin">The perfection of Gods workes.</note> that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt ment to ſeparate Ieſus Chriſt from all creatures, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to declare vnto vs, the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is betwene him and the father. Now he addeth, that <hi>that word was God:</hi> and this he doth the more fully and better to expreſſe, that which hee ment,<note place="margin">Chriſt is very God.</note> to wit, that Ieſus Chriſt was not a thing created, which had had a beginning, but
<pb facs="tcp:22757:31"/> that he is our true and very God. This place hath bene ill vnderſtoode of ſome,<note place="margin">Read this with reuerence and iudgement.</note> and they haue alſo fooliſhly tranſlated it, as to ſay God was the worde: for if we ſhould ſay, that God is the worde, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhoulde be no more God, the holye Ghoſt ſhould be no more God. But S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ment to ſpeake altogether the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to wit, that this worde is God, as if he ſhould ſay, that Ieſus Chriſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his deitie and Godhead, is of the ſame eſſence with the father. So he ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not the father out from the deitie, but declareth that there is no more, but one onely eſſence in God: and although there be a diſtinction betweene God and his worde, yet muſt we alwayes come backe to this ſimple and plaine trueth that they are one God, which we muſt worſhip.<note place="margin">Arius, Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, &amp;c.</note> It is true that the old heretikes trauailed verie ſore, to peruert this place to the end they might not be inforced to confeſſe, that Ieſus Chriſt was our true God. But we ſee here, that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh ſo plainely, of the euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and eternitie of this word, that there is no place left, either for wrangling, or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22757:31"/> ſtarting into holes. He addeth afterward that <hi>this word was in the beginning with God:</hi> He had not before ſpoken theſe two wordes together: he had onely ſaide, <hi>this word was in the beginning:</hi> alſo, <hi>it was with God.</hi> But nowe he ioyneth both of them together. Marke then howe wee ought in ſuch ſort to behold Ieſus Chriſt that we ſhould continually beleeue, that he is verie God, and of the ſame eſſence with the father.<note place="margin">Chriſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> Indeede he was created in reſpect of his manhood, but we muſt paſſe further, to the ende we may knowe him to be our eternall God, who is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed our God, that withall he is alſo, the wiſedome of his father, which hath bene with God from before all tyme. Beholde then, what is the ſumme of this place. Nowe if we ſhall keepe and holde faſt this expoſition, (as it is ſimply &amp; plainly ſet downe vnto vs) it ſhalbe ſufficient for vs, to inſtruct vs to our ſaluation. And this verelie is all that that wee are to knowe touching this point: for if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin here fooliſhly to diſpute, that wil fall out vpon vs, which in this behalfe is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len vpon the Papiſtes, as I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="tcp:22757:32"/> ſaide.<note place="margin">Bleſſed are they, whom o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens harmes make to beware.</note> Moreouer let vs note, that this is a certaine fooliſh ſtudie and indeuour, to labour muche to confirme that which the Euangeliſt ſpeaketh in this place, by the doctrine of the olde Philoſophers, as there are certaine people, that let and trouble them ſelues in it. It is true that wee ſhall finde in <hi>Plato,</hi>
               <note place="margin">It is a fonde trauaile to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme diuinitie by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie.</note> that hee had ſome vnderſtandyng of God: for when hee ſpeaketh of God, he ſaieth that God alwayes had his vnderſtanding in him ſelfe: and almoſt all other Philoſophers ſpeake after this manner. Now theſe that are ſo curious and deſirous, in ſuche ſorte to make the Philoſophers agree with the holie ſcripture: ſuppoſe that they haue muche profited the Chriſtian congregation, when they are able to ſay, that the Euangeliſts, who haue ſpoken after this manner, haue not bene alone, but that the Pagans and Heathen them ſelues haue indeede knowne ſuch things. Verely this is much to the purpoſe: it is euen as if a man woulde put a vaile or ſhadowe, before brightneſſe or light it ſelfe. Beholde God, who inlightneth vs by the doctrine of his Goſpell,<note place="margin">A fit ſimilitude.</note> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22757:32"/> wee will come and put a vaile or ſhadow before it and ſay, he, this light &amp; bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will be more apparant and glitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng by that vaile. It is verie cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, that God woulde, that euen theſe thinges ſhoulde be knowne to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philoſophers,<note place="margin">Heathen Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome light, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d wherefore it was giuen them.</note> to make them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſo much the more inexcuſable before his Maieſtie: but that prooueth not this, to witte, that his doctrine ſhoulde bee confirmed by that which they haue ſaid: for verely wee ſee, that ſo much the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer they thought to come nigh vnto God, ſo muche the further off in that reſpect they remoued them ſelues. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was fulfilled this ſentence of Saint Paul which he vttereth againſt all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.</note> that all they that woulde bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſharpe ſighted and ſubtil witted, and did not ſeeke God in ſuche reuerence and humilitie as they ought, are fallen into a bottomleſſe depth of errour. And certaynely this is a iuſt iudgement of almightie GOD, when wee proceede ſo farre to defile his doctrine mingling it amongeſt the fooliſhe inuentions of men. But let vs nowe goe further.
<pb facs="tcp:22757:33"/> The Euangeliſt ſaieth: <hi>that all thinges were made by it,</hi> &amp; that <hi>without it nothing was made of all that which was made.</hi> After that he had aſſured vs, of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall eſſence of that worde of God, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a confirmation, thereby to ſet out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs his eternall deitie, to the ende we may be verie certaine of the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">The creation of all things by Chriſt, is a plaine proofe of Chriſtes Godhead.</note> 
               <hi>All thinges</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were made by it.</hi> The eſſence of God is knowne to vs, not onely by that which we can conceaue or comprehend thereof in our owne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, but alſo when it pleaſeth him to declare him ſelfe vnto vs by his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: for when the ſcripture handleth that, then doeth he make him ſelfe viſible, and not onely viſible,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om.</hi> 1.19.20.</note> but S. Paul paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth yet ſomewhat further, ſaying, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we were blinde, yet we may ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by feele him as it were with the hand. So then though we had our eyes ſhut, yet ſo it is that we may knowe this power of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.27.28.</note> And howe ſo? Becauſe it is here within vs. In whom is it that we liue, that we haue our mouing and being? It is in God, who hath breathed life into vs, &amp; by whom we ſubſiſt or ſtande. This
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22757:33"/> then is that which S. Iohn ſheweth vs, ſaying that <hi>all thinges were made by it.</hi> By this we knowe, that that woorde of God hath been from the beginning, who alſo is our God.<note place="margin">God applieth himſelfe to our rudeneſſe.</note> And howe know wee this? Certainely wee cannot climbe ſoo high, and therefore God is come downe euen vnto vs, God I ſay, with that his worde, ſo that wee may knowe him. And albeit that our vnderſtanding ſtretcheth not it ſelfe ſo farre, neither yet is able too aſcende aboue the cloudes, yet ſo it is that we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to know that this worde is truely God. And how ſo? <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all thinges</hi> were made by it. In it is it then, that all thinges haue beene, as the Apoſtle Paule in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> ſheweth the ſame.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3.</note> 
               <hi>Wee confeſſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the worde of God is eternal and euerlaſting.</hi> And why ſo? Becauſe ſo it is, <hi>that by this worde all thinges were made.</hi> And this is alſo the ſame that S. Paul ſpeaketh in the xvii.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17.</note> Chap. of the Actes of the Apoſtles, that GOD hath not manifeſted himſelfe vnto vs, without a large teſtimonye and witneſſe, becauſe we may behold him in al his creatures.
<pb facs="tcp:22757:34"/> So then, in aſmuch as all thinges were made by his worde, we muſt knowe that hee is our eternall God. There are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Heretiques that ſuppoſe,<note place="margin">He meneth <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetus</hi> &amp; his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herentes, as I take it. See <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitu. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap</hi> 13. <hi>Sec.</hi> 7.8.23. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3.</note> that this woorde of GOD, had beginning in the creation of the worlde, becauſe there was neuer any ſpeach had of the woord, vntyll ſuch time as the worlde was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: As <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>God ſaid; let there be light, and the light was made &amp;c.</hi> Nowe they woulde inferre heerevppon that that woorde then beganne. Is it ſo? we may rather contrariwiſe by that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that that woorde is eternall. For if a man beginne to doe ſome thing, wee cannot thereupon ſay, that hee was not before that. If this be true in creatures what wyll it be, when wee ſhall come to God? So then albeit that worde of God hath not ſpread abroad &amp; made manyfeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power therof, before the creation of the world, yet none can therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conclude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was not alredy before that time. And this is that which S. Iohn mente to ſet out and declare by this maner of ſpeach, wherein it is ſaide, that <hi>all thinges were made by this Woorde.</hi> Moreouer let vs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22757:34"/> marke, that when wee ſpeake of God the Father and of his woorde, wee ſay then, that God made al things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, &amp; that by his worde:<note place="margin">A good rule which ought well too be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred</note> &amp; this worde <hi>by,</hi> is attributed onely vnto Ieſus chriſt. True it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſpeak of God ſingly and by himſelfe, and without diſtinction of the perſons, we may well ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36,</note> that all thinges are by and from God: but when there is a diſtinction, as in this place ther is, behold then the proprietie which belongeth and agreeth to Ieſus Chriſte, to wit, that al things were made by him. And this is that diſtinction of perſons which I haue alredy ſpoken of, that is, that all thynges are of GOD the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but that Ieſus Chriſte is the meane therof. Marke then what S, Iohn ment: as if hee ſhoulde ſaye, that GOD by his woorde hath made all thinges. Wherefore GOD ſheweth that hee is the fountaine of them all, and that it muſt needes bee that hee ſhoulde make and create all thinges, but yet by the meane and power of that his woorde. <hi>And without it nothing was made of that whiche was made.</hi> Sainte Iohn
<pb facs="tcp:22757:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> commeth heere too repeate the ſame Sentence, not onely becauſe it is his cuſtome to repeate one &amp; the ſelfe ſame thinge after two ſortes,<note place="margin">Two cauſes of S. Iohns repe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tition.</note> but alſo by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of mens ingratitude and vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. For albeit that it ſayde vnto them, that God made all thinges by his woorde, yet they doe not at the firſte, conceiue, vnderſtande, or beleeue the ſame. Wee ſee that Gods Creatures touche vs not to the quicke, and that wee are ſo dull and ſo blockiſhe in our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that wee are not able too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend theſe things, euen in ſuch playn and ſimple ſort, as they are propounded and ſet out vnto vs. Wherfore S. Iohn, that hee might the better expreſſe the ſame vnto vs, addeth, <hi>without it nothyng was made,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The dulnes of mans wit in Gods matters, ſhould teach vs true humilitie.</note> 
               <hi>of that which was made.</hi> As if hee ſhoulde ſay, Surely wee are accurſed if wee doe not receiue this eternall word of God, ſeeyng that by it it is that wee haue beene created, yea that all the worlde hath beene made, the heauen, the ſtarres, and the earth, which bringeth forth for vs our foode and nouriſhment: to be ſhorte, that all good thinges haue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22757:35"/> beene geuen vs by the meanes of this word. So then ſeeing wee perceiue that our lyfe proceedeth from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, we muſt wholy keepe our ſelues faſt thereto, and caſt from vs all that, that men wyll ſet before vs to the contrary. This is heere a double expoſition, in reſpecte of the placing of the woordes, not that they are chaunged, but becauſe wee haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly diſpoſed and placed them. Our ſort reade it thus:<note place="margin">We muſt heede lye looke howe wordes and matters are pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> 
               <hi>That by that worde all thinges were made, and that without it nothing was made,</hi> and ende there their ſentence: afterwardes they adde, <hi>All that which was made, was life in it:</hi> But this declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not aptly ſet. It is true that the ſenſe which they geue is indeed almoſt all one: for they haue in a maner the ſame expoſition that wee haue: but the maner of ſpeache is very ſtraunge: for it is not ſayde of the creatures that they are life, but that is attributed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, as Saint Paule ſaith in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10,</note> that the Spirite is life, by reaſon of the freedome that hath beene beſtowed vpon vs by Ieſus Chriſte. To be ſhorte, though we ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:22757:36"/> viewe all the holy Scripture, yet wee ſhal neuer find that it is ſaid, that we are life in our ſelues,<note place="margin">There is a dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble life euen in this life.</note> but that God only hath life, and that not onely the ſpirituall life, but euen that life, from which all things haue theyr being,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28.</note> and by which wee liue, and that we haue life and breath in him, as I haue alreadie alleadged out of S. Paules ſaying. And by this wee ſee the trueth of this ſentence, to wit, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng of all that which was made, was made without that worde of God. And this is the order of the readyng that hath beene founde and obſerued, in all the moſt olde Greeke Doctours, and other expoſitors: neyther was there any but one alone that hath otherwyſe expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it. Furthermore we haue to note, that the <hi>Manichees</hi> laboured to peruert and wreſt this place,<note place="margin">The <hi>Manichees</hi> and their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on confuted.</note> (ſaying, <hi>All that was made in him was life</hi>) to prooue their fooliſh opinions: as that all creatures had life in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; were liuing, for example Stones, Trees, Corne, Otes: All this in theyr fantaſie was liuing, inſomuche that they durſt not eat bread, vnleſſe they were ſanctified of GOD before hande.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22757:36"/> And wherefore? hee muſt be good, that eateth this, would they ſay. The Diuell certainely poſſeſſed them, and yet not withſtanding they would alleadge pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, and abuſe them,<note place="margin">The Diuel and his inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do continually wreſt the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> to prooue their fooliſh ſpeculations withal. Nowe I ment indeede to touch this by the way, to declare that the Diuell hath alwayes indeuored to peruert, wreſt and wring the holy Scripture: but whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be, if wee ſearche and ſeeke after Gods trueth, wee ſhall finde it pure and ſimple as it is, and the Diuell ſhall not be able to deuiſe or perfourme any thing againſt it or vs, to turne vs away from it, becauſe it is ſhewed and ſet out vnto vs before our eyes, and it ſhal appertain to none but to vs, if wee will beholde it in his puritie, &amp; keepe it in ſuche ſort, as God hath reuealed the ſame vntoo vs. Then let vs come to the naturall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng. After that Sainte Iohn had ſayde that <hi>nothing was made of that which was made without this woorde:</hi> Hee addeth, <hi>that in it was life.</hi> Nowe heere hee myndeth to ſet out two diuerſe things: that is too ſaye, that as all was
<pb facs="tcp:22757:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> once created by the power of that worde of GOD: ſo all thinges continue and are preſerued by that power, and by the ſame meane. And theſe are <hi>2.</hi> matters which it behooueth vs well to conſider and way.<note place="margin">Two thinges worthie to bee marked.</note> The one, that we haue our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and lyfe by this <hi>woorde:</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that we are vpholden and maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby, and that not wee only, but all the worlde: Alſo, that the world was not onely created at the beginning by this woorde, but alſo that it ſhoulde bee no more or continue any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, vnleſſe it were preſerued in it owne eſtate, by the ſame meane. And therefore as I haue ſaide, let vs marke and keepe faſte, theſe two thinges as they are in this place pointed out vnto vs with the finger by S. Iohn.<note place="margin">Al things in the worlde are vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by Chriſt.</note> In the firſt place then he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto vs, that <hi>nothing of that whiche was made, was made without this worde.</hi> And howe then? Mindeth hee to accept I knowe not what, that was not made? Seemeth it, that he woulde ſay, that the Angels were not created? No, no, he meaneth no ſuch thing: but mindeth to declare that we haue nothing at al which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22757:37"/> dependeth not wholy of God, and hath not it being altogeather in him.<note place="margin">Touching An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</note> It is true that the Angelles haue a very noble and excellent nature, but yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng they ſubſiſt and haue theyr bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng by this word, and are founded in it: otherwiſe they could not continue and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide: As alſo ther is nothing in the world but it is preſerued by this very woorde. Now heere wee are taught and iuſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, howe great our pouertie and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe woulde bee, vnleſſe that God vphelde vs by his grace. And this is it that the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 104.29.</note> 
               <hi>that ſo ſoone as God ſhall withdrawe his ſpirite fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, behold we returne to pouder and duſt, and vanyſh away altogeather.</hi> It is true that hee ſpeaketh in that place of creatures &amp; bodyly thinges: but ſo it is, that we ſee how all the reſt alſo is vpholden, by the vertue and power of this woorde. Nowe euen as wee cannot ſubſiſt or bee, but by that woorde of GOD: ſo we muſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe marke, that it is by the meanes thereof, that wee haue begunne to haue life. And who is hee that declareth the ſame vnto vs? The Euangeliſt. This is
<pb facs="tcp:22757:38"/> alſo the ſelfe ſame whiche the Apoſtle ſayth in the firſt Chap. to the <hi>Hebrues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>that the ſonne of God is the brightneſſe of the glory, or the Image of his ſubſtaunce and perſon of God his Father, and that he vpholdeth all thinges by his worde.</hi> Hee vſeth there the woorde, <hi>woorde,</hi> but yet in ſuch a ſignification, that hee meaneth not onely the power of the ſonne of god, but alſo a certayne wonderfull diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a very fitte and ſeemely order, which he hath ſet in the things created, becauſe he is the wiſdom of God &amp; wee may beholde him in all the creatures becauſe he vpholdeth all thinges by his vertue &amp; power. Mark the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how we haue life and moouyng, and after the firſt day of our lyfe wee continue in the ſame, to wit,<note place="margin">Mans life, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance thereof is from God alone.</note> becauſe that God preſerueth vs: for in reſpect of our ſelues wee muſt needes peryſh euery minute of an houre, if this were not that that woorde of GOD mainteineth vs. Behold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in what ſenſe the Euangeliſte ſayth, <hi>that that woorde was life:</hi> that is, that not onely al things were made by it, but that they muſte of neceſſitie alſo be grounded thereuppon. and that it mainteine them in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22757:38"/> Now he addeth afterwardes, that <hi>that life was that light of men</hi> And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it that hee addeth this? It is for <hi>2.</hi> cauſes. The firſt is, that after that we haue knowen the might of God, and the power of that his worde, both on high, &amp; beneath, and euery where, we muſt then come to ourſelues: for this is good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that we ſhould and that with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diligence hehold that, which toucheth vs very nigh. As howe? I ought too knowe Gods goodneſſe in this, that hee preſerueth, Horſes, Oxen, Otes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 36.6. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 104.27. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.11.</note> as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſpeaketh to vs therof, ſaying that it is hee that giueth nouriſhment, and food to euery beaſt. I ſee on the other ſide the Earth, which by the commaundemente and bleſſing of God bringeth foorth her fruites. If I looke then vpon beaſts, I ought to knowe the goodneſſe of GOD w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> declareth it ſelf euen towards Aſſes, &amp; Dogges, but much more towards mee. God commeth to me, that I might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly feele his power: hee geueth mee bread wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am nouriſhed, &amp; ought I not to be touched to the quick for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny benefits &amp; bleſſings, It is true that I ſhould.
<pb facs="tcp:22757:39"/> Beſides alſo when men ſet out Gods workes, they ſpeake expreſly of men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that God doeth ſet out his moſte great and excellent power rather in vs then in other creatures.<note place="margin">Gods power appeareth ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally in man.</note> God the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede be magnified, both in heauen and in earth, and in all his woorkes that we ſee: but yet much more in a man, becauſe hee hath imprinted his owne Image in vs, rather then in all the reſt of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For he hath not ſayd of the Sun, the Starres,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26.</note> or any other creature how excellent ſoeuer it be, I wyll make nowe a chiefe woorke, which may bee to myne owne Image and likeneſſe. So then the Euangeliſt after that he had ſpoken of the power of that woorde of GOD, which ſpreadeth it ſelfe to all creatures, hee commeth to men. And in this hee ſheweth vnto vs, that if men beholde the goodneſſe of God in euery place where they looke, they cannot but much more conſider and beholde the ſame, within theyr owne perſons. And foraſmuche as God hath doone vs this honour, that we are magnified &amp; made excellente in our ſelues, inſomuche that the very <hi>Pagans</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:22757:39"/> and Heathen haue called Man a little world,<note place="margin">Man a little world, and why hee is ſo called.</note> becauſe we may ſee in him a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall worke that ſurpaſſeth all the reſt, good reaſon is it, that we ſhoulde knowe &amp; confeſſe in it, the vertue and power of God. It is true that wee may beholde God in all his creatures, but when hee manyfeſteth him ſelfe in man, then wee ſee him, as it were by face and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: whereas looking vppon him in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, wee ſee him darkely, and as it were on the backe partes. So then albeit that it bee ſaide, that God is made viſible vnto vs in his creatures, yet it ſo falleth out, that in them we ſee but as it were, his feete, his hundes, &amp; his backe: but in Man wee ſee as it were his face.<note place="margin">God is viſible in his creatures chiefly in man, but in none can Gods maieſtie be perfectly ſet out.</note> Not that it is his face, ſo that we can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him there in imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I meane not ſo, for I ſpeke not now of diuine and heauenly things, but only of this, that it hath pleaſed God to bee knowne in this world high and to low. Behold then the ſumme of that which S. Iohn ſayth, to wit, that <hi>that life was that light of men:</hi> as if he ſhoulde ſay, It is true, that there is indeede a certaine life ſpread abroade
<pb facs="tcp:22757:40"/> ouer and in all creatures. And what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner a one is that, euen that all things are made and preſerued by that woorde of GOD:<note place="margin">Mans ſoule a very excellente thing.</note> but yet there is a more excellent matter in man, to wit, the ſoule, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng and reaſon. For a man ſhall not be without ſenſe and feeling, as ſtones: hee ſhall not bee without vnderſtandyng and reaſon as bruite beaſtes: but he hath a more excellent life, yea euen to beholde the thinges which are aboue and beyond the worlde. Nowe conſequently he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: <hi>that that light ſhineth in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that the darkneſſe comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it not.</hi> Hee expreſly putteth downe that, becauſe that that light which God placed in man, is as it were altogeather put out: and indeede if we ſhoulde iudge according to that which wee nowe can ſee in mortall men, we ſhal not much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and eſteeme the grace of God.<note place="margin">Sinne defaced Gods image in man.</note> For albeit that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was created to the image of God, yet ſo it is, that through ſinne he hath bin diſfigured and defamed. What is it then that wee ſee in men? Wee ſee there an image of GOD which is alto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geather
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22757:40"/> defaced and marred, becauſe that the Diuell hath defiled it through ſinne. But albeit that men following al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather that whiche Satan prompted them too,<note place="margin">Satan neither by force nor fraude, can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt the light.</note> haue quenched and put out the light of God: yet ſo it is notwithſtanding that the Diuell was not able by his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie to bring ſo much to paſſe, that this light of God, ſhould not yet ſhine foorth in the middeſt of darkeneſſe. And this is it that Saint Iohn minded to declare, as if he ſhould ſay, It is true (my children) that if that whiche was firſte geuen vnto men had continued and abidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wee ſhould haue ſeene nothing now, but the glory of God ſhining in euery place, in ſteede that now we behold his Image woonderfully defaced: and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, it ſo falleth out that we may perceiue in Man ſome brightneſſe that God hath left him,<note place="margin">Some ſparkes of light remain notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding mans foule fall.</note> and ſome little ſparke of that his light. And this is that which the Euangeliſt ment to declare. I leaue vntouched other thinges becauſe the time ſuffereth vs not to ſpeake any more thereof, and becauſe I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy beene ouerlong.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:41"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding wee are to marke that men haue ſo much light of the knowlege of God, as is ſufficient to wynne them, and make them inexcuſeable before him.<note place="margin">Men are not what they thinke of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but what God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth of them.</note> Let vs indeuer to make our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue of our ſelues what wee will or can, yet beholde God, who pronounceth, that wee are all darkeneſſe. And how ſo? let vs not attribute that vnto GOD, but to our owne fault. Nowe then, either God muſt inlighten vs with his brightneſſe, or elſe otherwiſe ther ſhalbe nothing but darknes in vs, and it cannot be auoyded but wee ſhall ſtumble and fall downe, yf wee will but once lift vp our ſelues to go forwarde one ſtep, without his guiding and gouernment. And yet ſo it is (as I haue already ſaide) that God hath not ſo deſtituted vs, that wee are altogeather forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining of his gifts. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo it is, there is yet ſome ſeede of religion in men, they haue yet ſome remnauntes of theyr fyrſte creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſee, that euen in the moſt wicked and reprobate: there is ſome impreſſion and printe of the Image of God, and this is to make them ſo muche
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22757:41"/> the more inexcuſable:<note place="margin">Mans light maketh him without excuſe before God, as <hi>Rom. <hi>1.20.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </note> forſomuch as they haue not profited thereby, their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhalbe therfore ſo much the more greeuous, and without doubt it ſhall bee doubled vpon them. Beholde then howe notwithſtanding that our nature was ſo corrupted we doe yet reteine ſome little ſparke of that grace, which God put in our father Adam: So that this ſentence is verie true, that <hi>that light ſhineth in darkeneſſe.</hi> Nowe further the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt ſaieth, <hi>that the darkeneſſe comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it not.</hi> Wherin he ſheweth how great the vnthankfulneſſe of men is.<note place="margin">Mans malice the cauſe of his owne blindnes.</note> Beholde God, who maketh his brightnes to ſhine in vs, and his worde to lighten vs, and yet notwithſtanding we darke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; dimme the ſame through our malice. It is true, that the Goſpell it ſelfe, is a manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and declaration of this light, but yet that malice and vnthankfulneſſe which is in vs, putteth it out, as muche as in vs is, vnleſſe God remedied and redreſſed it, making a chaunge in vs by his power and infinite goodneſſe. And this is that which Saint Iohn ment to declare in this place: and with all he beginneth to
<pb facs="tcp:22757:42"/> prepare vs to that, which he will ſpeake afterwarde, that is to ſay, to what ende this word (which is Ieſus Chriſt) was ſent vs of God his Father: that is, to the ende he might be manifeſted in the fleſh, for our ſaluation.<note place="margin">The myſterie of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion very great and needfull.</note> Hee ment then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare howe great the myſterie of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption was, and what neede wee had of it, in ſaying, that <hi>we haue not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the brightneſſe that was in vs:</hi> as if he ſhoulde ſay, It could nothing at all haue profited vs, to haue the light that ſhineth in vs, vnleſſe we had withal bene redeemed, and that this worde had exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and performed the loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, in repairing his image, which was defaced in vs through our ſinne, and wholie diſfigured in the firſt man. Marke I ſay howe Saint Iohn mindeth to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare vs to know the effect of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note place="margin">The ſight of our owne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is a good meane to make vs feele the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of our redemption.</note> and beſides hee ment alſo to ſhewe vnto vs, howe that the worde of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth it ſelfe in his creatures, in as muche as all thinges are preſerued by his ſtrength and power. And with all hee exhorteth vs to knowe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, the graces that GOD hath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22757:42"/> beſtowed vppon vs, more excellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede than vppon other creatures, to the ende wee myght magnifie and prayſe him: moreouer to knowe,<note place="margin">The endes of our light and knowledge.</note> that ſeeing hee hath from the beginnyng imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his owne liuely image in vs, and hath made vs feele his power, it is good reaſon wee ſhoulde learne, to holde our ſelues faſte to this word, and to confeſſe both generally and particularly, the good thinges that God hath done for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde, to the ende that the lyght which hee hath plentifully communicated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, of his grace and goodneſſe onely, may not be quenched or put out through our malice, but that Ieſus Chriſt may in ſuch ſort dwell in the middeſt of vs, that being guided and gouerned by the holie Ghoſt, we may haue ſuche acceſſe to the father, that he may at the length bring vs into his heauenly glorie. Thus I haue handled theſe thinges as ſhortly as was poſſible for mee,<note place="margin">What men ſhould looke at in expounding the ſcripture.</note> reſpecting alwayes to touche the marke, whereat the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt in this place aimeth: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng if there bee anye thing that hath beene omytted becauſe a man
<pb facs="tcp:22757:43"/> cannot remember all, let euery one ſpeak thereof that, which God ſhall haue giuen him in that behalfe: and if there be any doubt, propound the matters, to the ende that putting them out, they may be made cleare and manifeſt, and that the Church of God may thereby bee more and more edified, when thinges ſhall not remayne in doubt, but ſhall be vnderſtoode accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their true meaning, after that we ſhall haue diſputed and reaſoned vpon them, as is ſeemely, and according to God and godlineſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:22757:43"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſecond Congregation</hi> or ſpeach of Maſter Iohn Caluin, <hi>propounded and deliuered out of the ſecond</hi> Chapter of the Epiſtle of Sainct Paul to the Galathians, verſe the eleuenth, &amp; ſome other fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> And when Peter was come to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochia, I withſtood him in the face, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was to be reprooued.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> For before that certaine were come from Iames, he did eate with the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles: but when they were come, hee withdrewe him ſelfe from them, and ſeparated him ſelf, fearing them which were of the Circumciſion.</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13</hi> And the other Iewes likewiſe<note place="margin">Or vſed diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation.</note> played the hipocrites with him, in ſo muche that Barnabas alſo, was ledde awaye with them to their hipocriſie.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14</hi> But when I ſawe, that they walked not the right way, to the trueth of the Goſpell, I ſaide vnto Peter before all men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If thou which art a Iewe, liueſt
<pb facs="tcp:22757:44"/> as the Gentiles, why conſtraineſt thou the Gentiles, to doe like the Iewes?</p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15</hi> We which are Iewes by nature, and not ſinners of the Gentiles,</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16</hi> Knowing that a man is not iuſtified by the workes of the lawe, but by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, wee alſo haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued in Ieſus Chriſt, to the ende that we might bee iuſtified by the fayth of of Chriſt, and not by the workes of the lawe, becauſe that no fleſh ſhalbe iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the workes of the lawe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint Paule purſuing that matter, whiche we haue ſeene hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, declareth, that not onely hee was not ſome ſmall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Diſciple amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the other Apoſtles, but that euen in their preſence hee vſed a certaine ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne and chiefe authoritie, yea ſuche a one, as our Lord Ieſus Chriſt had giuen vnto the twelue, which hee had appointed to be as it were his Lieuetenauntes, to the ende to take and keepe poſſeſſion of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22757:44"/> his kingdome throughout all the world. Here S. Paul declareth,<note place="margin">Apoſtles, and why they were ordeined.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee was not in an inferiour degree and ſtate, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the other Apoſtles, but ſhewed him ſelfe to be of the ſame eſtimation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt and degree. Nowe hee prooueth that, becauſe hee feared not Peter, who was one of the auncienteſt amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as wee haue heretofore ſeene.<note place="margin">We may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue one an other, and the inferiour the ſuperiour, as occaſion is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> True it is, that wee may reprooue one another, and that hee which ſhall be the leaſt, may indeede vſe reprehenſion towardes him, which ſhall bee the moſt high and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. For God hath not ſo ſhortened his ſpirit, that the great ones, and thoſe that haue receiued more large graces, may not be humbled. He will ſtirre and raiſe vp ſometimes litle children, to blame and reprooue vs. So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that ſhal reprooue an other that ſhall bee aduaunced aboue him, ſhall not exerciſe by that meanes an ouerſight or ſuperioritie ouer him: But that which is rehearſed heere ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to an other ende: for Sainct Paul declareth that hee had ſuche libertie and freedome, by reaſon of his office.
<pb facs="tcp:22757:45"/> And ſo it behooueth vs to marke the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,<note place="margin">Our reproofes ſhalbe more gracious, when our duetie bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to vſe them.</note> ſtate and condition, when he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: for hee doeth it not as a common perſon, but as hee that was called to mainteine the pure doctrine of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and franckly reprooueth Peter, who was of great reputation in the company of the Apoſtles, ſo that a man might think him to be chiefe or firſt: yet Saint Paul ſetteth him ſelfe againſt him: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde then howe his calling to this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.<note place="margin">The Pope bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen faced and beaſtly.</note> And in this place we ſee, how the Pope was ſhameleſſe: and with all wee may ſee to his beaſtlineſſe, ſeeing he hath exempted himſelfe, from all reprehenſion and reproofe: for marke the wordes that he vſeth,<note place="margin">Distinct. <hi>4.</hi> Cap. Si papa. Clemens. lib. <hi>5.</hi> de Haeret.</note> that to him it belongeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue all the worlde, but that none may be aboue him. Beholde here a pride both deuiliſhe and full of ſacriledge, when a mortal creature wil ſhake of euery yoke, and ſay, I am more then others: for if a holie reproofe proceede from none but Gods ſpirit, it is as much as if the Pope ſhould lift vp his hornes and ſay, that hee oweth God nothing, and ought not to confeſſe him his ſuperior, to doe him any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22757:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> homage or ſeruice, after what manner or faſhion ſoeuer.<note place="margin">What we may learne by the Popes blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> But ſeeing God hath blinded him ſo farre, it is to the ende wee ſhoulde knowe, that the deuill hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed all, in that ſame ſeate of abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whatſoeuer it be, wee ſee howe the Apoſtles gouerned and behaued them ſelues, that is, that euerie one yelded him ſelfe apt to be taught, and obedient, and that hee confeſſed his owne faulte, to the ende hee might bee corrected therefore. This is then the rule,<note place="margin">To ſuffer the word of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is a good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of true Chriſtianitie.</note> that it behooueth vs to holde, if we deſire to be acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for Gods ſeruaunts, and to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as members of his Church. By what right or title may the Pope ſay, that hee is Saint Peters ſucceſſour, when he wil not folow him, nor confirme him ſelfe to his example, in any manner whatſoeuer it be? Hee is vanquiſhed by his owne mouth. But on the one ſide, wee are not onely taught (as I haue alreadie ſaide) out of this place, to condemne him, and his doings: but alſo to hold our ſelues in, and to keepe our ſelues vnder, in ſuche ſort that he which ſhall be the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, ceaſe not for all that to ſubiect him
<pb facs="tcp:22757:46"/> ſelfe with all humblenes:<note place="margin">The greateſt in the miniſtrie muſt be ſubiect to admonition as well as the meaneſt.</note> and that when hee ſhall haue faulted, that hee humble and caſt downe him ſelfe, and ſuffer him ſelfe to be reprooued. And moreouer we haue to ſee, what manner of reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or reproofe this was: For if Sainct Paul, in generall ſhould ſay, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued Peter, it ſhoulde bee ſome what farre off, and it woulde ſeeme, that hee would exalt him ſelfe, vnder the ſhadowe of theſe controuerſies and diſputations which hee had with the falſe Apoſtles. But it is apte and fitte for the purpoſe, that hee alledgeth ſuche a rehearſall: for he reprooueth not Saint Peter, becauſe that either in his life, or in his doctrine hee had ſtraied and wandered:<note place="margin">When mens perſons ſhalbe touched, to Gods diſhonor, then it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them (if they be cleare) to ſtande vpon their credite.</note> no that is not the argument and matter, whereof Saint Paul nowe treateth or ſpeaketh: but he ſheweth, that that wherof the falſe Apoſtles accuſed him, as though therein he had bent him ſelfe againſt the whole Churche, that in that reſpecte hee main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined euerie thing which he had taught the Gentiles, and that before Peter and the whole Churche. Wherefore wee muſt conclude, that Saint Paul hauing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22757:46"/> ſhutte Saint Peters mouth, in maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng that doctrine, whereof there was great queſtion, remooued all diſputation about it, inſomuche that it might not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes be lawfull, for Saint Peter any more to diſpute of it, or to mooue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny controuerſie about it. This then is that which wee haue to holde and learne for the ſeconde point: for this cauſe hee ſaieth, that <hi>Peter, before that ſome came from Iames, was conuerſant with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans or Gentiles</hi> (as ſome call them:) <hi>and notwithſtanding becauſe that ſome were come from Ieruſalem, hee withdrewe and ſeparated him ſelfe from the company of the Gentiles, fearing indeed to offend them that were of the Circumciſion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the tyme, well weighed.</note> But before wee come to the matter, let vs marke, when it is here ſaide, that Peter came with the others, that it was a long tyme after he came to <hi>Antiochia,</hi> and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it is eaſie to iudge, that this was before Sainct Paul arriued or came thither, to determine and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſentence touching this verie queſtion. For Sainct Luke reciteth, that becauſe the Iewes ceaſed not
<pb facs="tcp:22757:47"/> to trouble the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and there to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther companies, that Saint Paul and Barnabas went vp to Ieruſalem to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande of the Apoſtles, whether the Gentiles ought to be ſubiect to the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the lawe: and they concluded no. If Saint Paul had ſaid and alleged, that he ought indeede to content him ſelfe with that, which had beene determined and reſolued vpon, then this great abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie would followe thereon, that Peter had feared to grieue and offende Iames, or els to enter into diſputation with him, and trouble him, and that Iames woulde haue taken the concluſion of that matter againſt him on his owne ſide, as wee ſee in the Actes, that is to ſay, that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ought to bee in that libertie: which could not be: for it is expreſly ſaide, that Peter came to <hi>Antiochia,</hi> a long time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt, and yet it was before this concluſion was made, that the Gentiles ſhoulde not bee ſubiect to the ceremonies of the lawe. And whereto tendeth all this?<note place="margin">The Romiſh Biſhops beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</note> To declare the beaſtlineſſe of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome:</hi> who affirme that the ſeate of <hi>Antiochia</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:22757:47"/> was the firſt, and <hi>Rome</hi> the ſeconde,<note place="margin">Doctors agree not, about the tyme of Peters being at <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochia.</hi>
               </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Saint Peter reſted there and died there. Nowe ſome ſay hee was there ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeeres: and other ſome twentie and fiue yeeres: but we ſee, that Saint Paul was not conuerted ſo ſoone, after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt from the dead: beſides, and that after his conuerſion, hee was a long while ſome tymes heere, and ſome tymes there. So that a man may eaſely iudge, that Peter reſted and remained not in <hi>Antiochia,</hi> as the Pope ſaieth: this is a merie ieſt late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly founde out. So much alſo is there to be ſaid, touching his Biſhoppricke of <hi>Rome.</hi> Thus we may ſee,<note place="margin">The Pope al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth but ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles for his headſhip ouer the Church.</note> that all the goodly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours which the Pope pretendeth, and laieth for him ſelfe, that he ſhould be head of the Church, are indeede ouer fooliſhe, and nothing els but little childrens ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. And moreouer we ſee alſo, that S. Iames was not onely a Diſciple, as ſome would make him, but that hee was in the degree, and of the company of the Apoſtles: for Saint Peter woulde not haue ſo much reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced and feared him, if in degree he had bene inferiour to him
<pb facs="tcp:22757:48"/> ſelfe.<note place="margin">Peter, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome haue laboured to cloake his ſinne, offended greatly.</note> But let vs nowe come to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall matter. It is certaine, that Saint Peter committed a fault, becauſe hee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted and withdrew him ſelfe from the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles. True it is, that men haue ſought diuers cloakes to couer and excuſe him withall, becauſe hee was moſt bounde to his owne creation. For as it hath beene alreadie ſaide,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.7.</note> euen as Saint Paul was called to preache the Goſpel to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, ſo was Saint Peter the miniſter of circumciſion: whereupon it ſeemeth to ſome, that he ought to haue more regard to his owne nation, ſeeing he was bound thereto, and that according to Gods own intent and purpoſe.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12.</note> But in that God dyd ſo diſtribute and deuide the offices, hee ment not thereby to breake the vnitie of the Church: for there is no more but one bodie. Wherefore needes muſt it be, that the Iewes ſhoulde bee ioyned with the Gentiles: ſo that it is a follie to ſay, that Sainct Peter ought to mainteine the Iewes parte, becauſe God hath called him to be a miniſter amongeſt them: for that was vpon condition that they ſhall nouriſhe amitie and friendſhippe amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22757:48"/> the members of the Church.<note place="margin">Reaſons, proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter offended.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can not otherwiſe ſay, but that he faulted and that fowly: Adde alſo that Saint Paul ſpeaking in this place, as the inſtrument of the holie Ghoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth him. Beholde a ſentence that can not bee called backe, and againſt the which it is not lawfull to plead. It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo expreſly ſaid, that <hi>Peter and thoſe that ioyned with him, walked not the rightway into the trueth of the Goſpell.</hi> This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be concluded, that Peter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a fault. And indeede there might haue followed a great offence of that which hee did, and that was, the aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; eſtraunging of the Gentiles from the Iewes. Seeing then that he ſo much diminiſheth the number of the faithfull, and indeede teareth the Church, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it in pieces, what may wee iudge of that? And beſide, it behooued, that this doctrine to wit, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ceremonies of the law were aboliſhed, ſhould ſpecially bee mainteined.<note place="margin">A ſecret obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſufficiently anſwered.</note> And albeit the Iewes were permitted to vſe them, vntyll ſuch time, as that by litle &amp; litle, the libertie which
<pb facs="tcp:22757:49"/> our Lord Ieſus Chriſt purchaſed for vs, was knowen, yet for all that, there ſhould not haue bene any bondage therein to lay that yoke vppon the Gentiles necke, as though that the ceremonies had bene gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them for euer. It behoued them that that ſhould bee indeede concluded and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued vpon. But Peter beginneth to cal it into doubt and queſtion. Beſides hee was variable and inconſtant: and we ſee that for to pleaſe men, he declined &amp; went aſide from the good and right way, which thing alſo is plainly &amp; expreſly accurſed.<note place="margin">Sinne is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, for men ſometymes fall into it euen then, when they they thinke to doe well.</note> Certaine it is that S. Peter in ſo doing, ſought not his owne profite, for all his whole ſtudie and indeuour was to ſerue God, yet ſo it is, that for all that, hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth him ſelfe, and turneth aſide from the good way. And why ſo? fearing leaſt he ſhould offende the Iewes: and herein he ſheweth him ſelfe ouer muche affected towardes men. Seeing that it fell out to him, to goe aſide and ſtraie, let vs looke to our ſelues, &amp; let vs remember the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which was ſpoken before, that <hi>if we deſire to ſerue mens appetites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>wee can not ſerue our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> This is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22757:49"/> then that which wee haue to note in this place, when it is ſaide that Peter feared to offend the <hi>Iewes.</hi> True it is that wee ought to feare offences: but whatſoeuer it bee,<note place="margin">Offences muſt be auoided, but ſo muſte incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie alſo.</note> this meaneth not that in reſpecte of men and for theyr ſakes, we muſt bow euery way, and that men ſhall turne vs &amp; wind vs as a Ruſh, as we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ſay. For it is not in our power, to diminiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of Gods righte &amp; authoritie at our fantaſie and pleaſure, but that which he hath pronounced, muſt alwayes abide firme and ſtedfaſt, &amp; men muſt attempt nothing againſt it, after what ſort ſoeuer it bee. Wherefore when the queſtion is to nouriſh concorde and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>itie among vs, wee muſt alwayes haue that which God alloweth, that is, wee muſt be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and learne to obey his woorde. And this ought indeede to bee well marked, becauſe at this day wee ſee that theſe which ſwim betwene two waters,<note place="margin">Meane men painted out and anſwered.</note> thinke it good to do both this &amp; that, &amp; enter in to diſputations alſo about the ſame: ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this is not of great importance and weight, wee may eaſily yeelde them and graunt them that. And yet for all that,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:50"/> who ſeeth not, what great ſacrilege is committed, if men goe aſide from this doctrine of S. Paul?<note place="margin">No color muſt cauſe vs to run from the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of the Goſpell.</note> &amp; therfore ſo much the more ought one heedily to mark this poinct, that is to ſay, that it is not lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, vnder any ſhadow or colour whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, to decline or ſtarte away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods pure trueth. And Beholde wherefore S. Paule maketh mention of this trueth. This meaneth not that we ſhoulde looke to haue in or vnder the Goſpell any fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly libertie: but it teacheth vs that if men wyll haue a Goſpell to the halfes, that then they doe nothing els, but falſifie and corrupt the ſame: As doe theſe that will ſay: Let vs hold the principall: and then for theſe ſmall matters and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces it ſkilleth not:<note place="margin">An obiction an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> wee may diminiſh this, or take away that, becauſe they are not of any great importaunce or weight. Such men doubtles are falſifiers &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupters of Gods word. And why ſo? For we ought wel to weigh this word, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not enough to haue the Goſpel in a hotch potch,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.6.</note> and in parte, but wee muſt haue it ſound and whole, or elſe it is corrupted. Behold <hi>a little leauen, leueneth the whole lumpe of dough:</hi> and we are commaunded
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22757:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>to beware of leauen:</hi> that is to ſay, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all mingle mangle, thereby to diſguiſe and diſfigure in any maner whatſoeuer, the puritie of the doctrine of God. This woorde then ought to be as it were ingra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen in our heartes,<note place="margin">The doctrine of the Goſpell muſt not bee clipped.</note> more then if it were written in letters of golde: to wit, that there is a certaine puritie in the Goſpel, &amp; that it is not lawful for vs to turn from that, but that wee muſt haue the doctrine pure and ſimple, inſomuche that men ſhoulde not attempt to leſſen the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit at all, or to diminiſhe any thing therfrom. Nowe concerning that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> S. Paul ſaith: that <hi>he reprooueth Peter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was to be reproued:</hi> This meneth not that he was reprooued in ſuche ſort, as ſome haue imagined. It is true that the worde may import, that hee was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued, but we know that Participles are ſometimes taken for Nownes: and ſo doeth S. Paul expound it, that Peter was culpable and faultie, and that his offence was as if it were altogeather known.<note n="*" place="margin">Amongeſt the reſt <hi>Ierom</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of you may ſee large diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in the <hi>2.</hi> Tome of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> woorkes and namely, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. <hi>8.9.10.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </note> But I ſpeake this becauſe this place hath beene muche debated vppon amongeſt the ancient writers: &amp; becauſe ſome haue ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly maintained it, that
<pb facs="tcp:22757:51"/> Peter offended not, neither was ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, becauſe they wold not perſwade themſelues, that S. Paule did ſo openly ſet him ſelfe againſt Peter, or that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into controuerſie ordiſputation with him about it. For it ſeemeth vnto them that if S. Paule ſhoulde finde any thing in Peter, to bee ſpoken againſt, that hee ſhoulde haue told it him betweene them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and ſecretely,<note place="margin">Muche a doe made to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the true meaning of the holy Scripture</note> leaſte otherwiſe hee might geue offence, and ſtirre vp conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion in the Church, and kindle a fier, that wold not be eaſily quenched. They haue this colour, and therevpon they haue thought, and this was doone by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betweene them, and that S. Paule and S. Peter were well agreed togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as though Peter ſhoulde haue ſaid when wee ſhalbe in companye with the people, thou ſhalt reprooue me, and I wyll make as though I were well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therewith, and then afterwarde wee ſhal not be troubleſome or greeuous one with another, and I wylbe content to be vanquiſhed and ouercome, and that thou alſo ſhalt haue the victorie and glory. But who ſeeth not that this is too to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22757:51"/> muche inforced, and is indeede nothing elſe, but the turning topſie turuie of S. Paules Texte. Wherefore there is no doubt of this, but that S. Paul declareth in this place, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter was to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned and blamed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Peters proc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tors anſwered.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19.20 <hi>Act.</hi> 16.3. <hi>Act.</hi> 21.26.</note> And he addeth afterwardes the reaſon of it: <hi>that he and all that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him, did not walke with an vpright foote according to the trueth of the goſpel.</hi> Thus much then for reaſon. Now they that thought that there was ſuche an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greemente betweene S. Peter and S. Paule, grounded them ſelues vpon a fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous &amp; vaine reaſon, to wit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> S. Paul confeſſeth in another place, yea in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry other places that he was as a Iewe amongeſt the Iewes, and as a Gentyle among the Gentyles: that is to ſay, that he conformed and faſhioned himſelf to al men. True it is: but this was doone for the edification of the Church: &amp; beſides this was not to annihilate &amp; diſanul the libertie of Chriſtians, or els to breake the vnitie and concorde of the Churche. Whereas we ſee altogether the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in S. Peter. Firſt he made a diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Churche, as if hee had torne it in
<pb facs="tcp:22757:52"/> peeces as I haue already ſaid. He troad vnderfoote the liberty of Chriſtians, and indeuored to inforce eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles to take the yoke of the lawe vpon them, &amp; to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into ſubiection and bondage. There was no edification in it, but rather that which had beene buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp before, was as it were pulled downe. Let vs conclude then, that in that behalfe S. Peter had no agreement at all with S. Paules dooinges. And when S. Paule ſaith that <hi>he became a Iewe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the Iewes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">How S. Pauls woords <hi>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.20</hi> are to bee vnderſtoode.</note> hee meaneth not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe then thus, that hee framed hym ſelfe vnto them in theſe thinges where in hee might, that hee myght by little and little drawe them too more greate and large knowledge, as alſo he himſelf doth afterwardes declare. So then there is no doubt, but that this reproofe was made in roundneſſe and trueth, and that there was no diſguiſing in it nor cloſe, complot, or ſecrete agreement betweene the Apoſtles. And indeede Sainte Paule doeth ſufficiently declare how that it coulde not ſo bee, for hee vſeth a woorde when hee ſayeth that Peter trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22757:52"/> the Church, by his feigning or coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfeiting, that is too ſay, hypocriſie,<note place="margin">S. Paule plaid not the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite in reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Peter.</note> which alſo is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon inough amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs. For now if Saint Peter was reproued of his hypocriſie, S. Paul alſo himſelfe ſhould haue been an hypocrite, ſeeing he had couenaunted and had made as a man woulde ſay, a ſecret bargayne with him: as to ſay, we will deceiue the company: for it ſhal ſeeme, that I am of one opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and thou of an other, and let vs reaſon vppon this difficultie, and diſpute this harde queſtion: and when they ſhall ſee that thou ſhalt bee ouercome, they ſhall haue theyr mouthes ſtopped vp. If it had ſo beene, wee ſee that their manner of proceeding had beene indirect and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart, &amp; there ſhold haue byn therin an occaſion, rather to haue turned them that were ſounde in iudgement fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Goſpell, then to haue builded the weake. To be ſhort it is a matter too to plaine, that Saint Peter commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a fault, and alſo that by good right and reaſon, the Apoſtle Sainte Paule reprooued him, becauſe he was culpable and faultie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:53"/>
            <p>Nowe after that we haue ſeene the fact or deede, let vs come to the reaſon whirh is added. He ſayth: <hi>If thou which art a Iewe, liueſt as the Gentyles, and not as the Iewes, wherefore conſtraineſt thou the Gentyles to do like the Iewes?</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Paules rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof weighed.</note> Marke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sainte Peters faulte, that is, that hee wrought thereby great hurt againſt the Gentyles, when hee withdrewe hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from them, for it was a certain kind of inforcement or conſtraint. And why ſo? For if the Gentiles had beene moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to diſpite or anger againſt hym, beholde the Churche then ſhoulde haue beene aſſembled together in companies and ſet one againſt another. But we haue declared, that as our Lord Ieſus Chriſt is the head of the Churche, ſo it behoueth vs to be ioyned togeather in him, as the members of one body. So that now there remayned nothing elſe,<note place="margin">Chriſte as the head, and the faithful as the members make but one body.</note> but that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyles ſhoulde eyther take and vſe the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the law, or elſe it muſt needs be, that there ſhould bee open warre and contention, betweene them &amp; the Iewes, and ſo they ſhoulde bee as it were two troupes or companies, one of them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22757:53"/> againſt another. And this is that conſtraint or inforcement wherof Saint Paule ſpeaketh heere.<note place="margin">This is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble kinde of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement.</note> Wherin we muſt marke that we do not onely enforce peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple when wee alwayes take them by the throate, but alſo when they are not able to eſcape, but that they muſt of neceſſitie ſubmit them ſelues to that which is laid vpon them: Behold this is an inforced conſtraint, yea a certaine kinde of tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, which we vſe and practiſe. Some wyll ſay S. Peter thought not vppon that: But let it be certaine that he failed through ignoraunce:<note place="margin">It is a good thing vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly to confes our faultes.</note> yet hee was repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of his errour, and indeede he harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not himſelfe in his ſinne, neyther made many replies agaynſt S. Paule, as though hee woulde reſiſt him but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that he was blame worthie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon we haue to note that wee muſte not ſet a rule or law ouer our neighbour. For S. Paule in another place (to wit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. <hi>14.10.</hi>
                  </hi> This muſt not be vnderſtoode of lawful magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie, but of vniuſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</note> 
               <hi>Rom. <hi>14.</hi>
               </hi>) teſtifieth that <hi>wee muſte all appeare before the iudgement ſeate of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> It belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs to bee iudges: it belongeth not to vs any more to vſe iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t one
<pb facs="tcp:22757:54"/> ouer an other: but let vs in ſuche ſort go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern our ſelues, that God may haue al au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thority ouer vs, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt to enforce his neighbours, ſeeing hee hath no ſuch rule and gouernment, for that ſhould bee as muche as in vs lyeth to dimniſh the authoritie of God, when euery one of vs wyll be a iudge.<note place="margin">Faith in Chriſt by the doctrine of the Goſpell, freeth both Iewes &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles from all Iewiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> And thus muche ſhortly touching thus rehearſall or ſtorie. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon S, Paule taketh occaſion to enter into the matter, and largely to lay it out as wee ſhall ſee afterwardes: whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo hee beginneth and ſaith: <hi>wee are Iewes by nature, and not ſinners amongeſt the Gentiles, notwithſtanding knowing that wee cannot bee iuſtified by the works of the lawe, we haue beleeued in our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, who hath beene our onely remedie, becauſe that no fleſhe can bee iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by the works of the law.</hi> Wherfore ſeeyng that it is ſo, ſo farre of is that the Gentiles ought to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to keepe and vſe the Ceremonies, that euen the Iewes themſelues are feared from them if ſo bee it they come and haue recourſe to our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, and imbrace the faith of the Goſpell. And Paule rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22757:54"/> in this place, from the greater to the leſſe: for hee maketh compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Iewes and the Gentiles. For God had ſet ſuche a diſtinction and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference that the Ceremonies were as it were, a wal betweene them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſians.</hi> 2.14.</note> as hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thereof in the ſecond Chapter of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians.</hi> Behold then God, who diſtinguiſhed his people from the Gentiles, and put the Ceremonies. as it were a wall betweene them: as though he ſhoulde ſay, you haue a ſigne and a marke, that you are not of their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and company, becauſe they knowe the ſeruice whiche hee requireth, and the waye alſo whiche they ought too keepe. This ought to bee marked in the firſte place, that the Ceremonies of the lawe were ordeined and ſet out for the Iewes. And this is that which the Apoſtle S. Paule ſayeth, <hi>wee that are Iewes by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               <note place="margin">What the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle meaneth by the worde na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> Now this worde <hi>nature</hi> importeth not the common creation of all men: for the Iewes came from Adam, and deſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded from Noah alſo after the flood. So that there was in that reſpect a common nature betwene the Iewes &amp; the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles.
<pb facs="tcp:22757:55"/> Moreouer it is certayne, that in Adam, all both Iewes and Gentyles are accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; corrupted:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51.5.</note> was not Dauid a Iewe? and yet notwithſtanding hee confeſſeth, that from his mothers wombe he was a ſinner, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued in iniquitie. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when S. Paul ſpeaketh thus of the Iewes, &amp; ſheweth that they are Iewes by nature, hee meaneth that they are not peruerſe and corrupted, not conſidering them,<note place="margin">There is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nature in men. <hi>Ephe. <hi>2.3.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </note> as deſcending from Adams lyne, or race, but as comming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abrahams race. Wherefore to make a ſhort reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there is a double nature. The firſt is common to all: the ſecond is ſpeciall or particular. For when S. Paule ſaith in another place to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that <hi>wee are by nature the children of wrath,</hi> then hee doeth indifferently comprehende and meane, aſwell the Iewes as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyles. Behold then, that aſwel Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s race as others are ſubiecte to Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and that of nature as S. Paule ſayth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 11.16, 21</note> But in the xi. Chapter to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> he ſaith that <hi>the Iewes are the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural braunches of the holy roote or ſtock:</hi> when he ſaith naturall branches of a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:22757:55"/> roote, it is a ſpeciall priuiledge that God gaue, to that race of Abraham, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he adopted and receiued the ſame to him ſelfe. And why ſo? For God hath not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared that he wyll bee the people of Iſraels Sauiour, but a Sauiour of all that Line or Stocke. And thus much concerning this <hi>woorde.</hi> Alſo this worde <hi>ſinners,</hi> is not there to bee taken, as wee commonly vnderſtand it,<note place="margin">What the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle meaneth by this woorde ſinners. <hi>Iohn. <hi>9.31.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </note> but it ſignifieth in this place prophane perſons, and ſuch as are altogeather defiled before God, as when it is ſayde <hi>that hee heareth not ſinners:</hi> and yet we know indeede that he heareth them. And indeede, the doctrine that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath taught vs, muſt needes be inuiolable, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth vs to haue our mouthes wyde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to confeſſe our ſinnes, whatſoeuer come of it, for otherwyſe wee ſhoulde be lyars, as S. Iohn ſaith in his Canonical Epiſtle, to wit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.8.10.</note> 
               <hi>that if we confes not that we are ſinners the trueth is not in vs:</hi> yea and it is of neceſſitie required that God couer our ſinnes. So then ſinnes is often times taken for a Prophane man, and one that is reiected of GOD, as alſo in
<pb facs="tcp:22757:56"/> this place. But nowe let vs come to that which Saint Paul ſaith: we are Iewes by nature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 32.8.9.</note> wee haue a ſpecial priuilege: for in aſmuch as GOD hath choſen the raſe of Abraham, beholde howe wee are placed in a degree of honour. God could haue doone this to all the worlde, but as it is ſayde in <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſong, God caſt his worde, to ſeparate his owne inheritance from other nations. And this is it that S. Paule meaneth in this place, to wit, that the Iewes had a certain ſpecial dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and were not of that common ſorte or order that the Gentiles were, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in theyr firſt nature, and were as it were, reiected and accurſed. This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction is more plainely ſet out in the thirde Chapter of the Apoſtle Sainte Paules Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans.</hi> For after that he hath declared, that all were condemned before God, and that there is neither Gentile nor Iew, but he ought to confeſſe that, he demaundeth this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Shall not the Iewe then haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more preferment, yes they ſhal,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for God hath declared himſelf to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They haue the law &amp; that ſeruice which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:22757:56"/> was appointed them, they had alſo his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſes.</hi> Behold great honours that God beſtowed vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when he declared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that they were his purchaſed people, his inheritaunce, and as it were,<note place="margin">Al both Iewes and Gentiles haue neede of Gods grace.</note> his treaſure, that they were vnto him a prieſtly kingdom, and that he eſtabliſhed his ſeruice in the middeſt of them. Mark how the Iewes had great preheminence aboue the Gentiles, &amp; are they more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent for that? He addeth afterwardes, No. For if we ſhold be al examined, ther ſhoulde not be one alone amongſt vs that ſhoulde be founde iuſt before God. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold then how they are condemned with the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles, &amp; all are deepely plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſe. We ſee then how the Iewes are not polluted and prophaned, as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles are. And by what meanes is this? By the grace of God. This is without the men: &amp; yet they haue all one &amp; the ſelf ſame beginning, &amp; beſides they are al cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupted in their perſons, becauſe that they are ſinners both the one &amp; the other. But whatſoeuer it be, Paul declareth in this place, that if there bee any that ought to bee partakers of this benefite of Gods
<pb facs="tcp:22757:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> mercy, that they are the Iewes. And why ſo? He ſayth in another place, that is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſians.</hi> 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>Epheſians</hi> the ſeconde Chapter, that <hi>they were nigh to God, &amp; the Gentiles far of from him. When he ſpeketh of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, hee ſaith that hee came and preached reconciliation, that wee mighte haue acceſſe vntoo the father, and this</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>was publiſhed aſwell too them that were nigh, as to them that were a far of.</hi> He ſayth that the Gentiles were far of, becauſe God had abandoned &amp; forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them, as it were for a whyle: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde then the Iewes who were nigh,<note place="margin">None can com to God, but tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe the grace of Ieſus chriſt.</note> &amp; yet had not acceſſe to God through the lawe, but through the grace of Ieſus Chriſte, publiſhed by the doctrine of the Goſpell. Wherfore we muſt knowe that the workes of the lawe are debated: For to the Iewes it is that God ſpok, and yet the Iewes haue not their ſaluation therin And what? Shal the Gentiles, to whom God ſpake not, and who had no promiſe, ſhall they (I ſaye) haue theyr refuge and recourſe to the lawe? We ſee then Saint Paules purpoſe, which is to ſhewe that none can bee iuſtified but by faith. Hee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22757:57"/> in this place theſe wordes, to iuſtifie the fayth of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and the makers of the lawe: we muſt inlarge theſe pointes before we can comprehend and perceiue Sainct Paules purpoſe, and the ſubſtance of that which he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. This worde <hi>to iuſtifie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What the word iuſtifie, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</note> ſignifieth as much as to be abſolued before God. It is true, that if we would heape vp all the teſtimonies of the ſcripture, ſeruing for this purpoſe, it could neuer at al, or hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be one, and beſides we coulde not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch the whole matter at this tyme. It is true that for this preſent tyme, if it be poſſible, wee will take and alledge two places onely, to ſhewe and ſet foorth that which we haue ſaide. Saint Paul, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the eight Chapter of his Epiſtle to the Romanes: <hi>What?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33.</note> 
               <hi>may not wee ſtande before God</hi> (ſaieth hee) <hi>ſeeing hee iuſtifieth vs? and who is it then that ſhall condemne vs?</hi> Certaine it is, that in that place, this word to <hi>iuſtifie,</hi> importeth not that God maketh vs iuſt, but this it is, that he receiueth vs to mercy and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning vs our ſinnes, hee holdeth vs and accompteth vs as iuſt, albeit that we be
<pb facs="tcp:22757:58"/> not ſo indeede. The compariſon ſette a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, declareth the ſame: God iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth vs, who is it that ſhal condemne vs? If theſe two wordes be well weighed, to iuſtifie muſt needes bee contrarie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, and that is then to abſolue. So to be iuſtified before God, that is the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or loſing, that he giueth vs, when it pleaſeth him to receiue vs to mercie, as is declared vnto vs in the Romanes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.6.</note> where Saint Paul alledgeth this place out of the two and thirtie Pſalme: <hi>Bleſſed is the man, whoſe iniquities are pardoned, and whoſe ſinnes are couered: hee ſaieth there that wee are iuſtified without the woorkes of the lawe.</hi> And why ſo? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our ſinnes are pardoned vs, &amp; that through Gods free goodnes. The other place is declared, in the thirtenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Actes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 13.38.39.</note> to wit, <hi>that we can not be iuſtified by the workes of the lawe,</hi> but <hi>by the grace of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The Gentiles then are iuſtified: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what ſort? <hi>From all thinges fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the lawe of Moſes could not iuſtifie them,</hi> that is to ſay, coulde not abſolue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:22757:58"/> Moſes lawe had many markes &amp; ſignes to teſtifie their reconciliation to GOD.<note place="margin">The ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the law, could not iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie.</note> There was waſhinges, ſprincklings, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfactions, and all the reſt: But all this was not or ſerued not, to iuſtifie, that is to ſay, to acquite and diſcharge men, in ſuch ſort that they ſhould bee accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iuſt. So when in this place it is ſaid, that the Iewes founde not any thing in the lawe, whereby they might be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he meaneth by iuſtified, obteinyng of grace and fauor before God, &amp; in ſumme, approbation and allowance before him. And thus muche concerning one worde.<note place="margin">What is ment, by the faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</note> Nowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, is not that whereby Ieſus Chriſt belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but that by which we belieue in him. And howe doe wee belieue in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt? that is in receiuing and applying him ſuch a one vnto our ſelues, as he hath beene ſent vnto vs from God his father. But he hath ſent him,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> as ſayth Saint Paul, to be <hi>our righteouſnes, our wiſdome and ſatiſfaction.</hi> When then we ſhall receiue our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt for our righteouſnes, beholde howe the faith
<pb facs="tcp:22757:59"/> that wee haue in him iuſtifieth vs. And howe is hee our righteouſnes? hee decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it in an other place, in the ſecond E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of the Corinthians,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</note> where he ſaith, <hi>that hee that knewe not what ſinne ment</hi> (that is to ſay, was pure and innocent from it) <hi>was made as ſinne for vs, to the ende that wee might bee iuſtified in him.</hi> Marke then what this ſpeach the fayth of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt importeth:<note place="margin">We ought to come to Chriſt, becauſe he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone hath all thinges in him that we neede.</note> that is to ſay, the aſſuraunce that wee haue through the fayth, that we are reconciled to God his father, and that wee finde in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, euery thing that we haue neede of: to bee ſhort, that God iuſtifieth vs without our ſelues, in that ſatiſfaction and recompence, which hee findeth in the ſacrifice of his deare ſonnes death and paſſion. And thus farre concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this worde. There remaineth yet this worde, workes of the lawe, whereby ſome haue vnderſtood barely, the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as Circumciſion, the waſhings, the ſacrifices, the ſprinkeling of beaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bloud, and ſuche like thinges.</p>
            <p>And there is ſome ſhewe thereof at the firſt ſight, becauſe that the founteine of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22757:59"/> this queſtion which Sainct Paul hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, proceeded from this,<note place="margin">Theſe wordes, workes of the lawe, conteine not onely the ceremonies, but all that God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the law.</note> that the Iewes would be circumciſed, and obſerue the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the lawe. Wherefore it ſhould ſeeme by this, that the workes of the lawe, were nothing els, but the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies thereof. But they import (as wee ſhall ſee in a more large declaration thereof) ſomewhat more, to wit, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſpeach is comprehended all that which God hath commaunded. True it is, that the firſt occaſion which Sainct Paul had, to enter into diſputation and queſtion about the matter, was to ſet out the abuſes which were in theſe outwarde thinges:<note place="margin">Pilgrimages, feaſtes, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of dayes, &amp;c. wicked in a double reſpect.</note> as at this day wherein wee are at controuerſie with the Papiſtes, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching pilgrimages, feaſtes, the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of certaine dayes, &amp;c. Wee doe not onely handle this queſtion and point, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that theſe three things &amp; ſuch lyke be commaunded of God yea or no, but we come ſomewhat further and ſay, that this is not onely not to ſerue God, but that it is blaſphemie to ſay ſo. Wee ſee then, that when men will ſpeake of ſome ceremonie, or ſome ſuperſtitious obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:60"/> they ſhall come to the generall rule, becauſe they are thinges ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, yea thinges that can not be ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: So much alſo is there to be ſaide concerning the woorkes of the lawe. For when the Iewes would that men ſhould obſerue Circumciſion, and that it ſhoulde continually abyde whole and ſound, that proceeded from an errour: for they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that Circumciſion was Gods ſeruice, and that it was a meritorious woorke to bee iuſtified by: and it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they helde ſo muche alſo, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the reſt. But that is contrarie to trueth, for <hi>Circumciſion was a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the grace of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>and a ſigne of faith,</hi> as Saint Paul ſpeaketh thereof, in the fourth of the Romanes. Beholde then how the Iewes, were turned verie farre, from the true inſtitution of God, when they attributed ſuche an vſe to the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the lawe. And this is the cauſe alſo, why Saint Paule ſtayeth ſo muche vpon this worde.<note place="margin">Two ſortes of Papiſts, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts touching merites.</note> And moreouer it is not without cauſe, that hee ſtandeth alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the word promiſe: For the Papiſtes themſelues confeſſe indeed, that they me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22757:60"/> nothing, but by reaſon, and in the ſtrength of the promiſe: When they ſay that they deſerue heauen through Gods grace, they meane thereby that they are not able to doe all, but yet ſundrie tymes, you ſhal haue them ſpeake thus proudly, that they merite or deſerue the whole. They ſay, that it is not by their works in their own nature, but that God hath fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med firſt ſuch a preparation or diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in them: and ſo there is nothing touching faith: and yet behold wherfore S. Paule addeth this word faith, becauſe they eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh and erect of workes, and Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, their owne merites.<note place="margin">Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and mens merites, cannot ſtand togither. <hi>Rom. <hi>4.13.14.16.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </note> Now needes muſt it fall out, that in the meane ſeaſon this promiſe ſhould be diſanulled, if men ſtaie them ſelues vpon workes, as Saint Paul ſaith in the place already alledged out of the Romans. And yet for all this, he putteth not downe without good cauſe and reaſon, this worde, woorkes of the lawe. Sometymes when hee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth them not, hee doeth it, to ſhewe, that he ſpeaketh generally &amp; without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, as in the place erewhile alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, hee ſayeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.</note> that GOD iuſtifieth
<pb facs="tcp:22757:61"/> without workes: hee eſtabliſheth not the woorkes of the lawe, but ſaieth without woorkes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuitie.</hi> 18.5. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.12.</note> But bicauſe he hath to do with the Iewes, whoe might alwaies alledge and ſay: And what? Shall this promiſe that wee haue (too wit, hee that ſhall liue according to the lawe, ſhalbee iuſtified, &amp; this is our life) ſhal this I ſay bee vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable? ſhal al this bee without cauſe and voide? Mark howe the Iewes might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. Saint Paule therefore vſeth a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention heere, and cutteth the throate, (as a man woulde ſay) of al that they are able to obiect: as though hee ſhoulde ſay: albeeit woorkes are of the lawe, yet ſo it is, that they are not able to iuſtifie. But now let vs come to the principal point or matter.<note place="margin">Neither Iewe nor Gentile can be iuſtified by the lawe.</note> It is ſaide, that the Iewes, that had al the promiſes of God, and the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teſtimonies, that he had choſen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from amongeſt al the reſt of the worlde, were yet notwithſtanding inforced too ſeeke their iuſtification and righteouſnes in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Which ſeeing that ſo it is, too whome ſhal the Gentiles repaire nowe, to obteine grace in? ſhall they goe to ſeke it in the lawe, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22757:61"/> they are further eſtraunged than the Iewes? No. Wherfore we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude,<note place="margin">Aſſured perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Gods mercie through Chriſt, is the meane of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note> that the Gentiles haue no other meane, to obteine pardon before God by, and to ſtande vpright in his iudgement, than to be apt to learne, and to humble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, when the queſtion is to appeare before him, hauing true certainty and aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his mercy, thorow our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. And marke what this ſpeach meaneth, <hi>but in the grace of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> Wherein alſo the error of the Papiſtes is once again ouerthrowne.</p>
            <p>For when they ſay, that they are iuſtified by fayth, they confeſſe themſelues ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: but this is but in parte, for they can not ſuffer or abide this ſaying, thorowe fayth onely. No not a whit, and therefore it is very likely that we ſhal neuer agree in this poynt.<note place="margin">A verie fit ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude.</note> For they meane that our woorkes are in parte the cauſe of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and ſo make thereof a hotchpotch and mingle mangle, that is neither fleſh nor fiſhe, as men ſay: that is, that part of our woorkes, and parte of our fayth, are the things that iuſtifie vs. And when S. Paule ſaieth, that it is not, thorowe the
<pb facs="tcp:22757:62"/> workes of the law, but by the onely faith of Ieſus Chriſt, is not this a doubt, that the Papiſts flye and ſhunne verie much? So then, Sainct Paule declareth, that there is neither Iewe nor Gentile, that can be found iuſt in Gods ſight, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in and through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who is our righteouſnes, and that we are made partakers of this righteouſnes, euen by the doctrine of the Goſpell: for as the Apoſtle S. Paule ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3.4.9.</note> in the tenth Chapter of his Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans: God accepteth vs not, for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation or keeping of his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor through the lawe, but in &amp; by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp from the dead to iuſtifie vs. I ſee, that I haue bene alreadie ouer long, and therefore I will not goe any further at this time:<note place="margin">Maſter Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uins wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full humilitie.</note> the reſt ſhalbe expounded ſome other time: notwithſtanding the brethren may adde hereunto, that which I haue omitted, and alſo redreſſe that which they ſhal know to be more fit for the purpoſe, than I haue alreadie declared, reſpecting and bearing with my infirmitie &amp; weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which thing alſo I pray the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22757:62"/> towards me. Now wee will giue thanks vnto our good God, for the fauor he hath ſhewed vs, when it pleaſed him to draw vs to the knowledge of his Goſpel, beſeeching him, that hee woulde in ſuche ſort open the eyes of our vnderſtanding, that wee may knowe,<note place="margin">An excellent prayer for true humilitie and lowlines of heart.</note> what an excellent thing it is to humble our ſelues vnder the obedience of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, to the end that none of vs lift vp his hornes, ſo muche as to will, to make him ſelfe free of him ſelfe, and by his owne ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power, but that he ſuffer himſelfe to be vanquiſhed and ouercome, and that altogether wee may abide in ſuch ſort to bee ſubiected and brought in obedience vnder Gods word, that theſe which ſeeme to be the moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and famous in the Church, may not lift vp, &amp; glorifie them ſelues, but that they may receiue correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, admonition, &amp; reproofe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt: and that al that may ſerue, to the ende we may atteine to this marke, that GOD may beare rule ouer vs all, as he that is our creator and hath chiefe rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, both in heauen and earth: and ſeeyng we knowe that wee can not here
<pb facs="tcp:22757:63"/> on earth,<note place="margin">No perfection in this world.</note> be like vnto Angels of heauen, that wee may learne vnfeignedly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue &amp; imbrace the doctrine of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, wherein our ſaluation is included and comprized: And ſeeing wee knowe alſo, that there is nothing in our nature but that which deſerueth a curſe, that we may learne to ſeeke our righteouſnes out of our ſelues, which righteouſneſſe hath bene purchaſed for vs, by our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and that we may clearely beholde the ſame in this holy Goſpel, through a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fayth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:63"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſeconde Propoſition</hi> or ſpeache, of M.I. Cal. vpon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde to the Galat.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="15">15 We which are Iewes by nature, and not ſinners of the Gentiles:</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16</hi> Knowing that a man is not iuſtified by the workes of the lawe, but by fayth in Ieſus Chriſt, wee alſo haue belieued in Ieſus Chriſt: to the ende that wee might be iuſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the workes of the lawe, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that no fleſh ſhalbe iuſtified by the workes of the lawe.</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <hi>17</hi> Nowe if in ſeeking to bee iuſtified by Chriſt, we our ſelues alſo are founde to be ſinners: is Chriſt therfore the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of ſinne? Be it not ſo.</p>
                  <p n="18">
                     <hi>18</hi> For if I build againe the things that I haue deſtroied, I make my ſelfe a trangreſſour, or treſpaſſour.</p>
                  <p n="19">
                     <hi>19</hi> Verelie, I haue beene through the lawe, dead to the lawe, to the ende that I might liue to God: becauſe I am cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified with Ieſus Chriſt, to the ende I might liue to God.</p>
                  <p n="20">
                     <hi>20</hi> So I liue, and yet nowe not I, but Chriſt liueth in me: and in that, that I
<pb facs="tcp:22757:64"/> nowe liue in the fleſh, I liue in the faith of the ſonne of God, who hath loued me, and hath giuen him ſelfe for me.</p>
                  <p n="21">
                     <hi>21</hi> I doe not aboliſhe or take away, the grace of God: for if righteouſnes be by the lawe, Chriſt then is dead in vaine.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue ſeene &amp; heard howe this doctryne ought to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, to wit, that we are iuſtified by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt. But nowe it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to handle the reaſon that S. Paule bringeth, to wit, that neceſſitie inforceth vs to ſeeke this righteouſnes which is giuen vnto vs, thorowe the grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: for if there were any other meane thereof,<note place="margin">No righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be found in any, either in heauen or in earth, but in Ieſus Chriſt alone.</note> men might receiue and take it, but when we knowe, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wee haue ſought aboue and beneath, and that we haue made our circuites and iourneyes as it were, both in heauen and in earth, and yet notwithſtanding behold we are ſhut vp, and that there is no righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes in any man lyuing: thereupon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:22757:64"/> we may verie well and ſafely conclude, that we muſt be ſaued through the grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, or els y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are all loſt &amp; condempned. This then is that wherupon S. Paul ſtandeth at this time. So this ſaying ought well to be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Iewes ſtoode in neede to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine righteouſnes through faith: <hi>becauſe that no fleſh ſhalbe iuſtified by the woorkes of the lawe.</hi> And indeede it is certaine,<note place="margin">No way of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance from Gods curſe but Ieſus Chriſt.</note> that we ſhall neuer come with a good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, if this be not rightly imprinted in our hartes: to wit, that the curſe of God holdeth vs faſte locked vp &amp; incloſed, and that we can not any maner of way come out of it, but by this meane. Euen as a ſicke partie, when his diſeaſe preſſeth &amp; wringeth him, and that he is not able any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to indure it,<note place="margin">A fit ſimilitude well purſued and applied.</note> he will ſubmit him ſelfe to the Phiſition, and wil binde and tye him ſelf to receiue theſe things, which ſhalbe ſharp &amp; bitter vnto him. He that is mery &amp; maketh good cheare, will not goe to ſeeke the Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when he is wel diſpoſed to drinke and to eate, and that hee findeth him ſelfe to haue a good appetite or ſtomacke: euen
<pb facs="tcp:22757:65"/> ſo is it with vs:<note place="margin">None can come rightly to Chriſt, but ſuch as are woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Gods iudgements.</note> for vntill ſuche time as Gods iudgement haue in ſuch ſort woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs, that we be as it were poore ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered &amp; loſt people, &amp; to be ſhort, that we be as it were drowned or ſwalowed vp in death, wee will neuer come in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. It is true that this doctrine may well be receiued, and that they which ſhall heare thereof, will bowe their eares and hearken, when ſome ſhall ſay to them, that there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther righteouſnes, but the grace of God. There are verie many ſcoffers and ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that allowe this, but it ſhall not bee in trueth, for there is nothing but hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and diſſimulation amongeſt them. Let vs then holde this faſt, that we muſt beginne at this ende, when wee woulde knowe wherein our ſaluation ſtandeth: and howe ſo? For wee muſt of neceſſitie ſtriue to atteine that:<note place="margin">Feeling of death in our ſelues, bringeth vs to life before God.</note> we muſt I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne at death, to the ende that that may leade vs to life. And this is the cauſe wherefore Saint Paule largely laying out the matter which wee haue to handle in this place, ſummoneth and proceedeth againſt all mankinde. On the one ſide he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22757:65"/> ſheweth, that though the Gentiles had not the lawe written, yet that theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience did ſuffice to condemne them, and that God exerciſed in the ſame his iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, to their condemnation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12.14.15.</note> and that theyr owne very thoughtes were ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Summons, to bring them before the heauenly iudgement ſeat, to declare vnto them that they were altogeather accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. On the otherſide, concerning the Iewes, if they woulde glory and boaſt in the lawe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1.2.</note> that is it that doeth condemne them, as S. Paule ſaith. Thereupon he concludeth, that it behoueth euery mouth to bee ſtopped and ſhut vp, and that wee ſhoulde confeſſe, that there is nothing in vs but confuſion and ſhame of face, and that if wee ſhoulde yeelde vp an accounte before God,<note place="margin">They that flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them ſelues in theyr ſinnes, had neede to be rowſed vp.</note> wee ſhoulde be ſo muche the more drowned in diſpayre. And indeede becauſe that men rocke them ſelues a ſleepe as it were in their owne hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, S. Paule doth in a maner thunder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, that iuſtifie themſelues and flatter themſelues, ſaying: Thinkeſt thou that God accepteth mens perſons? Thou preſumeſt indeede to condemne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
<pb facs="tcp:22757:66"/> and who or what art thou? Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, duſt: &amp; yet thou takeſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of iudging, and wilt needes haue this authoritie, when thou thy ſelfe canſt not be exempted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iudgement of God. Mark then how it behooueth vs to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked and ſtirred vp, that we ſeeke not our righteouſneſſe any where elſe, nor by any other meane, but onely by our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, and that we learne right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to examime our life, and not onely to goe beyonde, a certaine free and willing condemnation of our ſelues, as tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſours of the lawe, and blame worthie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God,<note place="margin">Before Gods mercy can bee ſweete vnto vs we muſt be wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully caſt down in our ſelues.</note> but to bee altogeather confoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded and moued with ſuch an aſtoniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we ſhoulde not knowe on which ſide to turne. Beholde I ſay, howe wee may geue opening and entertainement to the doctrine, which is handled in this place by S. Paul. And ſo let vs wel and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weigh theſe woordes, <hi>That no fleſh ſhalbe iuſtified by the woorkes of the law:</hi> and alſo let vs marke, that this is it that ought to bring vs too our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, and to the faith of the Goſpel, to the end that through the grace of GOD
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22757:66"/> we may at the laſt be ſaued. And moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that which ſome ſtand ſo much vpon, touching theſe wordes, <hi>The workes of the law,</hi> as though S. Paul ſpake of nothing but the Ceremonies, that I ſay hath bin in part reprooued and handled, and wee haue declared, that ſo to take the woorde is an ouerfoule folly. And indeede Paule meneth no other thing in this place, then that which is ſaide in the hundred fortie and third Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 143.2.</note> when Dauid beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth GOD that <hi>hee woulde not enter into iudgement and accounte with him:</hi> (for hee addeth the reaſon) <hi>that no man liuing ſhalbe iuſtified in his ſight.</hi> Dauid ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not in that place of the woorkes of the lawe, but it is to ſhewe that if GOD woulde exerciſe the office of a Iudge, that then our lyfe ought to bee aunſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thereto: And to knowe wheather wee ſhoulde bee acceptable before him or no, what ſhoulde bee doone in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe? Shoulde wee not be paſt hope? Yes indeede, and why ſo? For there ſhall not bee founde any liuing creature, that can be iuſtified. And what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that woorde? that is to ſaye,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> that any man can bee founde ſo iuſte in Gods ſight,<note place="margin">None is of him ſelfe iuſt before God.</note> that thereby he can be abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and diſcharged before him. So then when Paul ſpeaketh heere of the workes of the lawe, it is not to this ende that the diſcourſe w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> he maketh ſhold be reſtrained to the ceremonies onely: but he ſpeketh expreſly (as wee haue already declared) of the woorkes of the lawe, becauſe that the deceiuers which at time ment to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the puritie of the Goſpell, did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes alledge &amp; ſet out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ceremonies. Now Paul ſpeaketh here as of the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remedy that ſerueth to draw men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> condemnation, as alſo mention is made thereof in the fifteenth Chapter of the Actes of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10.11</note> and in that place it is ſaide, that wee cannot be iuſtified by all that which is conteined in the lawe of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> but that we muſt come vnto the faith of Ieſus Chriſt. In the lawe of <hi>Moyſes</hi> there were waſhings, ſacrifices, &amp; to be ſhort many means to be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled to God by.<note place="margin">He that hath Chriſte and his merits hath al.</note> But what? all that was but a figure and ſhadowe, to bryng the people to Ieſus Chriſte. It followeth then that when wee haue the ſatiſfaction that is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22757:67"/> purchaſed vnto vs by Ieſus Chriſte his death, we haue all: neither neede we the law to ſupply any thing whatſoeuer:<note place="margin">A ſhifting and vaine obiection anſwered.</note> and though we had all, that it were poſſible to finde out of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, we ſhould haue nothing at all: And yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it ſhould ſeeme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment or reaſon is not ſufficient &amp; ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: for albeit that we be not fully iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by the works of the law, yet a man might ſaye, that wee are in part iuſtified therby: which if it be true, we are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather iuſtified by faith, for there is in it, but one part of our righteouſneſſe. Beholde howe the Papiſtes are abuſed and deceiued: for they wyll not ſay, that wee are able, without the grace of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, to obteine ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that wee are able to glory and boaſt before God of our ſelues, as though wee had in our ſelues all that which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, to obteine euerlaſting life by,<note place="margin">Papiſts ſhiftes and ſubtilties.</note> they wyll not ſpeake ſo: but they will ſay, that wee are ſinners, that there are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities and weakeneſſes in vs, and that we haue in our ſelues manyfolde im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perfections, and that our Lorde Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:22757:68"/> Chriſte muſt of neceſſitie remedy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe them, and that in the vertue of his death and paſſion our ſinnes are pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: but yet for all that they ſay, that we may haue a portion of righteouſneſſe in vs, which righteouſneſſe they call parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, or parted, becauſe it is as it were parted betwene god &amp; man: &amp; moreouer they ſay, that the remiſſion and forgeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is beſtowed vppon vs, when we are to obteine pardon of our ſinnes,<note place="margin">A moſt horrible blaſphemie.</note> is not free, but that ſatiſfactions on our behalfe muſt be added thereto. And this is that which hath cauſed them to deuiſe theyr Maſſe, Trentals, Diriges, Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mages and ſuche like. Beholde alſo the fundations wherupon they builded their Purgatorie.<note place="margin">Maſſe, Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, and ſuche baggage, vpon what grounde the ſtand.</note> To be ſhort we ſee, how the Papiſtes wyll indeede confeſſe, that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte is neceſſarie for them, but they meane onely in parte, and to ſupplie that, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they themſelues want. And yet they attribute to them ſelues thus much, that they are able to purchaſe fauour before GOD, that they are able to merite and deſerue at the leaſte ſome part and portion of theyr ſaluation, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22757:68"/> that when they ſhall haue offended, that they are able to amende and repayre the faulte, and that by theyr ſatiſfactions and works as they cal them of ſupererroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now it ſhould ſeeme that this argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment did fight againſt S. Paule. Marke his ſentence: we are not iuſtified but by faith, for alſo a man is not iuſtified by the woorkes of the lawe. Some might reply after this maner. Let vs put the caſe, that though we be not wholy iuſtified by the woorkes of the law,<note place="margin">A popiſh and peeuiſh reply.</note> yet this meaneth not but that we may haue ſome part and por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of righteouſnes therin. It followeth then, that wee are not altogeather ſaued by our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, but that this is a ſupply or an addition. But Sainte Paule ſuppoſeth that which is true, that for aſmuche as GOD in forbidding to commit whoredome hath alſo forbidden, to robbe, to lie, and to blaſpheme, and all the reſt, that he that faileth in one point is culpable and guiltie of the whole, as S. Iames ſaith in the ſeconde Chapter.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> 2.10.</note> And the better to perceiue and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this, we muſt come to the promiſes, and to the threates of the lawe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:69"/>
            <p>Concerning the promiſes:<note place="margin">Promiſes.</note> It is not ſaid, He that ſhal do ſome part of theſe things ſhall lyue in them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 18.5. <hi>Rom</hi> 10.5</note> but it is ſaide hee that ſhall doe theſe thinges. God then requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a ſounde and full accompliſhment of the lawe: otherwiſe there is no righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. And who is hee that fulfilleth the ſame? Truely there hath not beene yet any ſuch founde. It followeth then that this promiſe is indeede of no force, ſeeing that men faile in the performance of pointes put downe with the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Threates.</note>Now let vs come to the threates which ſhalbe declared more largely here after: but yet now we may in one worde ſee that which God pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 27.26. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.10.</note> Curſed be he, that ſhall not perfourme all theſe things. When he ſaith, that we are cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed if wee accompliſhe not all the whole lawe, and doe not ſatiſfie the leaſt point or title, and the vttermoſte farthing, as men ſay, behold how Saint Paules ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is forcible and ſtrong, that is, that there is no partiall righteouſneſſe as the Papiſts imagine and affirme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God will not haue his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cut and hewen in peeces and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22757:69"/> but declareth vnto vs, that we are al debters and faultie, becauſe we faile and fall before him. Marke then howe wee muſt come to our Lord Ieſus chriſt. And moreouer it is certaine that when a man ſhall take all that hee hath or is able to bring before GOD, there is nothing in him but a curſe.<note place="margin">All that man hath of himſelf is accurſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</note> For all that which the Papiſtes haue imagined and forged touching theyr freewyll, theyr meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous works or workes of ſupererrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all that I ſay, is nothyng elſe but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and illuſions of Satan. So then in the firſt place wee cannot be iuſtified, becauſe we cannot haue of our ſelues ſo muche as one good thought. And beſides, although God ſhoulde haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued vs by his ſpirite, and albeit wee ſhoulde deſire too obey him: yet ſo it is that as wee trauaile in our iourney and way, wee ſhall ſtumble much and take many falles,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</note> yea there wyll bee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny croſſe wayes, in ſuche ſorte, that wee ſhall continually fayle and faulte in our dueties. Seeing then it is ſo we muſt not put our confidence and truſte in the woorkes of the lawe, neither in all that
<pb facs="tcp:22757:70"/> which is conteined therein. And behold howe wee ſhall haue the perfecte accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of all righteouſneſſe in the grace and fauour of our Lorde Ieſus: and marke withall,<note place="margin">Perfection and fulneſſe of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is to be founde in Chriſt onely.</note> how we ought to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande this ſentence. Nowe thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sainte Paule maketh an obiection becauſe that this doctrine hath alwayes been ſubiect, to many ſlaunders and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies: For the Diuel ſeeketh nothing more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to blinde, &amp; to make bs beleeue that wee are able to purchaſe and get e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life through our merites. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde wherefore it is, when men preach, there is nothing but the free goodneſſe of God that ſaueth vs, that there are ſo many replies made: The reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to our fleſhly vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and reaſon:<note place="margin">Mans nature excellently pain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted out.</note> for wee are alwayes in cumbred with vayne fantaſies, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede puffed vp with preſumption and pride, and bring both that and many other faultes from our mothers wombe with vs, ſo that it is very harde vtterly to roote it out of our hearts. We cannot then be perſwaded that our ſaluation con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſteth altogeather in the mercy of God,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:22757:70"/> and indeede there was neuer yet anye of the Philoſophers that knewe it. The Gentiles verily and Pagans did vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that they were all ſinners &amp; that they had neede of ſome remedy therfore. They had theyr Sacrifices, their waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges and perfumes, as alſo had the Iewes? But what? They alſo ſtaied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues vpon their merites. Beholde then why S. Paul now bringeth this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſaith, <hi>If we alſo,</hi> that is to ſay, the Iewes: For this woorde <hi>alſo</hi> weigheth much in this place, as if he ſhoulde ſaye, not onely the Gentiles are knowne to be ſinners, and theyr iniquitie is layd open: But alſo euen we, who are the elect and choſen people of God, who hath the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of adoption, who haue this dignitie more than all the worlde hath, that God acknowledgeth vs for his inheritaunce, wee, I ſay are ſo much the greater ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, by howe much we beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt. But he ſpeketh this in the perſon of theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">All Expoſiters are not by and by to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> that were not able to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande this doctrine, neyther yet woulde quietly receiue it. It is true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this place is otherwiſe expounded by ſome others
<pb facs="tcp:22757:71"/> but there is neither ſalt nor ſauour in it: and that is the cauſe why I buſie not my ſelfe there in. They ſuppoſe that S. Paul ment to ſay thus much,<note place="margin">Mens mouths accuſtomed to wicked ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> that if we be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſinners, when we beleue in Ieſus Chriſt, it followeth thereon that Ieſus Chriſte hath not brought righteouſneſſe too vs, but this is far from the purpoſe, as wee may eaſily perceiue, by the anſwere ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned. To be ſhort, Saint Paule mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth too abate and beate downe in this place, that blaſphemie, which was then in many mens mouthes: that is to ſaye, that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte ſhoulde be the authour of ſinne, yf that the Iewes themſelues, ſhoulde be founde ſinners when they beleeue in him: For when the Iewes truſted in their Ceremonies, and ſatiſfactions of the lawe, they ſuppoſed indeede that they were diſcharged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and did ſanctifie themſelues. As wee ſee alſo that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> attributeth that vnto hypocrites, to boaſt themſelues in ſuche ſorte to be holy, that they ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed al other to be prophane, polluted, and filthy people in reſpecte of themſelues. Beholde then this fooliſhe preſumption
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:22757:71"/> wherewith the Iewes were, as a man woulde ſay, made drunke: to wit,<note place="margin">Some ſuppoſe them ſelues in good ſtate whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</note> that in not comming at all too our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, they thought that they were pure and cleane from al ſinne. But when they come too beleeue in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, then they vncloth themſelues and ſpoyle them ſelues of all regarde of that whiche they thought indeede to belong vnto them, as good and profitable. For they are caſt downe in them ſelues, and theyr iniquitie was made manifeſt, which before was hid and ſecrete: So that it ſeemeth that this promiſe of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte ſhould be vaine, &amp; that hee ſhoulde bee the author of ſinne. But Saint Paul aunſwereth: Be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo, deteſting as it were ſuch a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mie, as he hath begunne to ſpeake. But before we come to aunſweare this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that wee may well abſolue it, wee muſt declare, that this is repugnant and contrary too all the doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell. For what is that,<note place="margin">The ſumme of the Goſpell.</note> which is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto vs thereby, but this, that wee may in full truſt appeare before God to
<pb facs="tcp:22757:72"/> call vpon him, and to bee hearde of him. And this is wrought by the meane of Chriſtes righteouſneſſe. It followeth then, that the doctrine of the Goſpell ſheweth vs howe wee are iuſtified before God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.9.10.</note> ſo far of is it, that it eſtabliſheth ſin. And as it is ſaid, that when the holy Ghoſte ſhall come, it ſhall not be onely to reprooue the world of ſinne, but of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe alſo, to the end that we ſhould not ſeeke it in any, but in him, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is, that is to ſay, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Wherfore this ſolution is general when S. Paule ſayth, that <hi>if hee builde that which he hath deſtroyed, he ſhalbe a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſour,</hi> that is to ſay, he ſhall do againſt nature. But afterwardes hee commeth ſomwhat more nigh to the matter, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that it cannot ſo be, and that it is a falſe obiection: <hi>For I am</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>dead vnto the law through faith, and am raiſed vp with Ieſus Chriſte, to liue with God:</hi> He ſheweth heere, that when they that ſuppoſed for a ſeaſon that they were iuſt, bewrayed them ſelues to bee ſinners, and were conuicted thereof, and that their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:22757:72"/> in ſuche ſort appeareth, that they remaine aſhamed,<note place="margin">True fight of ſin, and vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned humblinge for the ſame, proceedeth not properly from Chriſt, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law.</note> to the end they might bee truely humbled and caſt downe, that this proceedeth not from Ieſus Chriſte, but rather from the miniſtery of the law. Nowe true it is, that Saint Paule is in this place briefe and ſhort, and this ſhort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe maye happily make him ſeeme darke. But wee maye take that, which is more fully declared in the vii. Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and make it to ſtande vs in ſteede of a key, for the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and vnderſtanding of this place. There Saint Paule demaundeth whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the law bee the cauſe of ſinne. No,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7.12.</note> ſayth hee, and reiecteth it as a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. The lawe is good, iuſte and holy: But this is it, ſinne is diſcouered by the lawe, and after that ſorte indeede it kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs. The lawe bringeth and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto vs a doctrine of life, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> alſo proteſteth and witneſſeth, ſaying,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>Beholde life:</hi> and yet Saint Paul ſaith, that it bringeth nothing but death. Yea indeede, but that is by reaſon of our faulte. The Lawe then killeth vs, not by it ſelfe but by circumſtaunce,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:73"/> becauſe it is vnto vs as a glaſſe, to cauſe vs to beholde our owne condemnation. Nowe purſuing his purpoſe hee ſayth, that when the lawe condemneth vs not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.8.9.</note> it is as it were dead: For ſin (ſayth he) lyueth not when the law is dead. And yet this ſhoulde be darke, if it ſhould not be opened and declared. When he ſaith that ſinne liueth not, when the lawe is dead it is to ſhew, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are negligent and careleſſe, and that they rocke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a ſleepe in vaine flatteries and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, ſo long as they are not reprooued by the lawe.<note place="margin">The preaching of the law moſt neceſſarie, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for theſe dayes wherein men are grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to lewdneſſe of conſcience.</note> Behold then ſinne which is dead, when the lawe is blotted out or defaced, that is to ſay, ſo long as men doe not examine them ſelues by Gods lawe, and according to that which he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, and call not themſelues to an account to knowe, whether they dutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behaue themſelues or no, they forget themſelues and enter not deeply into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues: For this muſt ſtande true, that ſo long as they are not carefull and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, theyr conſcience is ſenſeleſſe &amp; void of feeling. And after this maner is it the lawe being dead, maketh ſinne alſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:22757:73"/> to die. But doeth the lawe liue?<note place="margin">Howe the lawe is ſaid to liue.</note> That is to ſay, hath the lawe her force and power to ſummon vs before God, to cauſe vs to ſeeke what manner of men we are, to the end that we ſhould not flatter our ſelues: Then behold ſinne, which is as it were raiſed vp againe, where as before wee made no accompt of it, yea it maketh warre againſt vs, and perſecuteth vs ſo farre, that we are brought to all extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. But then we die (ſaith Saint Paul:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9.</note>) for hee addeth, I was aliue without the lawe. In ſaying that hee was aliue, hee meaneth it not of a common life, but that he was ſaued: for this worde life, is put and vſed, for righteouſnes and ſaluation. I liued (ſaith hee) that is, I thought my ſelfe to bee iuſtified, and to bee accepted before God, and to haue obteined euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life. And why ſo?<note place="margin">We are not in the beſt ſtate when wee ſo thinke our ſelues: neither are we in the worſt, when God maketh vs ſee our vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</note> becauſe hee had caſt the law verie farre away. But when the law once had her courſe, &amp; I thought well vpon it, I ſaid, alas: am I not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted and vanquiſhed? Doe I not nowe know what manner of man I am? Can I nowe eſteeme my ſelfe innocent? No verely: for ſo farre off is it, that I can do
<pb facs="tcp:22757:74"/> ſo, that I finde within my ſelfe a bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe depth of ſinne: So then when I knewe the lawe, the lawe ſlue me. And this is that, which the Apoſtle now mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth when he ſayth, <hi>that it is by the lawe that he is dead.</hi> Nowe to dye to the lawe may be taken after two ſortes: as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes it is taken for iudgement, becauſe that then wee can perceiue nothing but damnation. And alſo wee may take theſe wordes to dye to the lawe, in this ſenſe, as not to come nigh to it, nor to haue any thing to do therwith:<note place="margin">A good leſſon for miniſters, to teach them to haue care both what they ſpeake, and how they ſpeak.</note> for S. Paul abſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as muche as was poſſible for him, from making his doctrine odious &amp; hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full among the Iewes. If he had ſaid: I am dead: it had not bene right. But when he ſayth, <hi>I am dead to the lawe,</hi> that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, that we are no more any thyng at all, and that we finde not in it any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ioy. Nowe he ſayth, that this is, by the lawe, and not by Chriſt: we ſee how he turneth away this ſlander: Ho, our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie is vncouered, it followeth then, that Chriſt bringeth and manifeſteth ſinne.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:22757:74"/>
            <p>Many men ſay, that this commeth from Ieſus Chriſt and not from the lawe, but we may ſee the contrary: for if the lawe be dead, it foloweth that we alſo die with it, becauſe wee are condemned in Gods ſight: we ſee that all the promiſes that are conteined therein, cannot make vs glad and reioyce: wee ſee, that in ſteade of being accepted of God, we are accurſed and altogether confounded. Seeing then that ſo it is, that the law,<note place="margin">The lawe, and not the Goſpel, condemneth.</note> when Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth not, killeth vs and inforceth vs to dye with it: we will not, nor we cannot impute that to the grace of God, and to the faith of the Goſpell, but wee will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impute it to that which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe ſaith vnto vs, we ſhalbe iuſtified, and we ſhall obteine ſaluation, when we ſhall haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed all that, which it ſheweth vs &amp; teacheth vs. For looke how much more high the lawe lifteth vs vp, ſo muche the more ſhal we fall, into moſt deepe pittes and whirlepooles: wherfore we are farre remoued from this righteouſnes of faith by the lawe: we died then to the lawe,<note place="margin">The promiſes of the law haue a condition ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned.</note> in as much as God adioyneth this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to all the promiſes thereof: to witte,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:75"/> that if we keepe it, and doe according to that which he ſaieth vnto vs therein, wee ſhalbe recompenced. Nowe beholde all we are dead and loſt. And why ſo? for this is not ſufficient that God ſpeake, but we muſt looke to the conditions, as whether we be anſwerable to that which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth vs, and then we ſhal finde, that we goe altogether a contrarie courſe or backward, as it were. It foloweth then, that when hee ſhall haue ſhewed vs the way, we ſhall behold our ſelues accurſed, condemned, and plunged in the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pitte of hell. Nowe we haue the true ſenſe and vnderſtanding of this place. But hee addeth afterwardes the meane, that is, <hi>that hee hath beene deade with Chriſt:</hi> but with all, hee immediatly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnto vs the doctrine, that was, <hi>to the ende he might liue to God.</hi> He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth then,<note place="margin">This is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing death, and a dead lyfe.</note> that there is a liuing death, as there is alſo a dead life. The life that he calleth deade, is that falſe preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with which men deceiue them ſelues, when they imagine that they are iuſt and righteous before God. They liue, but it is in their owne fantaſie, and that life is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:22757:75"/> nothing els but dead: for becauſe they ſeeke not the mercy of God, that is the reaſon, why they ſuffer them ſelues, to go wholie to deſtruction.<note place="margin">To know that God knoweth our ſinnes, and to haue a ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble feeling of his iudgements for them, is the readie way to come to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the grace of Chriſt.</note> Now there is alſo a quickening, or a liuing death, when we dye, being confounded in our ſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God knoweth our iniquitie &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and that we are ſcattered to bee in that life, as it were condemned cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures. And this is that, that bringeth vs to life. And this is that alſo, which I haue ſaide heretofore, that we ſhal neuer ſeeke after the grace and fauour of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, tyll ſuch tyme as we bee wounded with the iudgementes of God, and that ſo deepely, that we are not able to indure any longer, neither knowe on which ſide to turne vs. We haue then yet nowe at the length, the vnderſtanding of this place: that is, that Saint Paule declareth,<note place="margin">Three eſpeciall pointes of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note> that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt placeth vs not in condemnation, but that it is the lawe which doeth that: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides we learne, that albeit we dye to the lawe, when we are dead with Chriſt, yet that notwithſtanding we obteine a newe life, and moreouer, he declareth, that this
<pb facs="tcp:22757:76"/> newe lyfe of ours, is without our ſelues. And in that hee fayeth, <hi>In that that I nowe liue, I liue not any more</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>my ſelfe, but Ieſus Chriſt liueth in me,</hi> he ſetteth out and declareth this matter, which wee ought wel to marke, and hold faſt: for without this ſaying, wee ſhall neuer purely and ſimply perceiue, what this meaneth, to bee iuſtified, by or tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe fayth. For diuers haue deceyued them ſelues, when they haue found theſe wordes, that we are iuſtified, by the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the lawe:<note place="margin">A double error.</note> for they meane when wee are iuſtified, that our Lorde draweth vs out of the corruption in which we are, and that hee reneweth vs by his ſpirite, to the ende that we ſhould ſerue him: and alſo they declare, that the good woorkes which the Chriſtians doe, are no more from the lawe but from them ſelues. And ſo that indeede, which ſeemeth to haue eſtabliſhed and ſtrengthened Sainct Paules doctrine, doeth nothyng els, but corrupt, peruert, and marre the ſame: for they make this diſtinction,<note place="margin">A doltiſhe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</note> that there are certayne woorkes of the lawe, which are the workes that men doe of their free
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:22757:76"/> will, and of their owne motion and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, as where they ſuppoſe to merite and deſerue. And they ſay that men are not iuſtified by ſuche woorkes, that is to ſay, by morall woorkes and dueties, as men call them: but yet notwithſtanding they woulde bee iuſtified by ſpirituall workes, that is to ſay, that we know, that God guideth vs by his ſpirit. But if it were ſo, all Saint Pauls doctrine ſhould be ouerthrowen: let vs then hold faſt the word, which is here to be expounded, that is, that we liue not in our ſelues, but in Ieſus Chriſt: that is to ſay, that our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is without our ſelues. Not that we haue not the aſſurance thereof in our ſelues, for the ſpirite, is a pledge vnto vs therof, as S. Peter ſaith,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.</note> &amp; we haue the ſeale of our adoptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorow the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, in as much as the certaintie of Gods grace is ſealed vnto vs thereby. And moreouer, Ieſus Chriſt dwelleth in vs, who is alſo the matter of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but the queſtion is not in this place, touching men, &amp; what they can do: wherfore let vs mark wel, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter of our ſaluation is not in our ſelues, but in Ieſus Chriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:22757:77"/> And that is the cauſe why Saint Paule ſayth, that wee liue not any more in our ſelues but in Chriſt:<note place="margin">A good diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the hypocrites, and the true faithfull.</note> for he maketh here an indirect compariſon, betweene the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, who deceiue them ſelues in a vaine ouerweening of them ſelues, and the faithfull, who are altogether beaten downe, and ſpoiled of all preſumption: for they that thinke they haue ſome dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and glorie and boaſt them ſelues in their merites, or meritorious workes as they call them, ſuch are they that liue in them ſelues. And why ſo? they ſuppoſe to bring ſomewhat to God that may make them acceptable before him. They goe not out of them ſelues I warraunt you,<note place="margin">A place full of great profit and comfort.</note> when they will warraunt them ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the iudgement of God. But the faithfull, who are inſtructed to knowe what manner of men they are, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them ſelues, and confeſſe that they are voide of all hope and truſt, as it were in them ſelues, and beyng ſo famiſhed and ſtarued as it were, they come to our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and knowe that the matter and ſubſtance of their ſaluation is in him. Beholde then, howe and after
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:22757:77"/> what ſort, wee liue no more in our ſelues, but in Ieſus Chriſt, that is to ſay, that we ſhould know and confeſſe, ſeeing that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt bringeth vs ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, that we muſt hold it of him alone, and fetch it from none other. And indeed if the death of Ieſus Chriſt bee the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of our ſinnes, it followeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon that we are debtters to God.<note place="margin">A moſt ſtrong reaſon.</note> Now ſeeing that ſo it is, beholde our owne righteouſnes taken from vs, and we ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of it, I meane thereby, the griefe and vexation that wee might conceiue by it. To be ſhort,<note place="margin">Marke theſe pointes well.</note> whoſoeuer ſhall knowe and feele what is the good will of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and wherefore he was ſent vnto vs from God the Father, and alſo the graces that he maketh vs partakers of by the Goſpell: ſuche a one aſſuredly ſhall knowe, that his life is not in him ſelfe, but rather that hee hath nothing in him indeed, ſaue the matter of death and damnation. Hereupon Saint Paul paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth further and ſayth: <hi>In that that I now liue in the fleſh, I liue in the faith of the ſonne of God.</hi> This is to ouerthrowe yet another replye, that men might make:
<pb facs="tcp:22757:78"/> for vpon that which hath bene handled,<note place="margin">A queſtion.</note> a man might bring in and mooue a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thus: what is this life, you ſpeake of? and what is our ſaluation, ſeeyng that we are poore miſerable ſinners, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about with ſo many infirmities, yea and that wee liue in the fleſhe, that is to ſay, wee are in this worlde, with bruite beaſtes, and are nouriſhed and ſuſteined with corruptible foode, and yet you ſaye ſtill our lyfe is in Chriſt?<note place="margin">An anſwere to the queſtion. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.6.</note> Sainct Paule handleth this in an other place, when he ſayth, that we are alreadie ſet in heauen, and that wee are entred into the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that inheritance, which is promiſed vs. And yet it ſeemeth to ſome, that all this ſhoulde bee but forged and deceipt. Marke then, how vnder the ſhadow and colour, that we are nowe farre remoued from God, wee are polluted and defiled, as Saint Peter alſo ſpeaketh thereof.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1.2.</note> It ſhould ſeeme, that this ſhould be nothing but ſhadowes of that, which is ſet out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in the Goſpell, to wit, that our lyfe is in Ieſus Chriſt, and that we are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of all his graces, &amp; ſo by conſequent of his righteouſnes. Nowe Saint Paul
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:22757:78"/> ſheweth, that this temporall lyfe hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not, but that we may alwayes lyue, that is to ſay, may alwayes haue full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. And why ſo? He bringeth vs here, the worde of fayth: which is a word, verie worthie to be well weighed, for he meaneth and ſheweth by the worde fayth in this place, that ſelfe ſame thing, which is deſcribed and ſet out at large vnto vs in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Hebrewes, where it is ſayde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.1.</note> that fayth is the euidence of things that are not ſeene, and the ſubſtance or ground of thinges that appeare not, and yet are hoped for. Wherfore ſeeing that faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth that which is inuiſible, &amp; cannot be ſeene, let vs not diſmaie our ſelues, or wonder at this, that we liue in death, and that we are in heauen, &amp; be citizens of the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, although we ſhould dwel in this world, &amp; ſhold walk &amp; creepe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth with bruit beaſts. And this alſo is that which S. Paule ſpeaketh wel of,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24.</note> in the eight of the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for that which he ſpeaketh there of hope, may alſo be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode &amp; that rightly of faith, becauſe they are things that cannot bee ſundred:
<pb facs="tcp:22757:79"/> for hee ſayeth, that we hope not for thoſe thinges which we ſee: for I ought not to hope for that, which I holde in my hand and haue in poſſeſſion, becauſe that I beholde, ſee, and enioy the ſame: but I hope for that which is helde from me. Wherefore our ſaluation muſt needes be hidde, otherwiſe wee ſhould haue neither fayth nor hope,<note place="margin">Our mortalitie and weake ſtate here, hindereth vs not, from the enioying and poſſeſſing of eternal life.</note> which is alſo declared vnto vs in this place. Albeit, then that we be in the fleſhe, that is to ſay, that we haue a mortall lyfe, ſubiect to ſo many infirmities, as nothing more can be, yea ſuch a lyfe, as is but a ſhadowe, &amp; which paſſeth into ſmoke, yet for all that, wee ceaſe not to haue an abiding and eternall life, which is grounded &amp; ſetled on Gods righteouſnes: and therefore it behooueth vs to repaire to fayth, that is to ſay, to that apprehenſion or taking holde which we haue,<note place="margin">Gods word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealeth mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters beyond the reach of our reaſon.</note> of thinges which appeare not, and to that certeintie and ſight that wee haue, of thinges which are not ſeene: for we beholde in the worde of GOD, as it were in a glaſſe, that which is hyd from our witte, and can not be atteined vnto, by our vnderſtanding. Behold then how
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:22757:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> this place of Saint Paul muſt be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. Nowe preſently hee addeth, <hi>who hath loued me, and giuen him ſelfe for me.</hi> Here Saint Paul yet better declareth, and more fully, howe it is that we liue by fayth, and out of our ſelues, that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde hath giuen him ſelfe for vs. Nowe by this worde, he bringeth vs backe, to the death and paſſion of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Our prayers are not profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, tyll we bee waſhed in Chriſtes blood, from our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he concludeth, that when we will call vpon God and preſent our ſelues before him, we muſt be plunged (as it were ouer head and eares) in the bloud of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that wee may be waſhed from our ſpottes, and that we muſt fetch from thence our cleanſing, that wee may be abſolued and loſed from the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation wherein we are. And as he ſaith, that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt gaue him ſelfe for him, ſo he declareth the cauſe, for he commeth to his founteine of the free loue of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6.7.8.9.10.</note> True it is, that in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces this loue is aſcribed to the father: as God hath not ſpared his ſonne: yet that hindereth not, but that Ieſus Chriſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs alſo, as it is ſaide in the eight
<pb facs="tcp:22757:80"/> Chapter of the Epiſtle to the Romans. Marke then what we haue to learne and beare away, when it is ſayd that our lyfe is out of our ſelues: that is, that we ſhall finde the matter of life in Ieſus Chriſt, who hath ſuffered, to the ende that wee might bee diſcharged before him. And after wee haue knowen this,<note place="margin">Chriſtes free loue the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all goodnes to vs ward.</note> to wyt, that the ſatiſfaction which our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt hath made, is our righteouſnes, we muſt come alſo to the fountaine, from whence all proceedeth, that is to ſay, to that free loue of his, in as muche as hee hath loued vs. And yet further this was not done, becauſe he was moued thertoo, by any thing that hee knewe to be in vs: but it was his onely mercy, by which we haue beene redeemed: yea it behooueth vs, to be in ſuche ſort voide of all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes in our ſelues, that we muſt not ſo much as preſume or thinke, that hee had reſpect to our perſons, or that he found ſo much as one droppe of goodnes in it.<note place="margin">Not one drop of goodnes in man, till Chriſt beſtow it vpon him.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold howe we are made partakers, of the bloud of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that I haue alreadie ben ouer long: but I wil go no further, And becauſe this
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:22757:80"/> place deſerueth to be better handled, I will pray my brethren, to ſpeake thereof euery one of them, that which hee ſhall know to be meet for the edification of the Church.<note place="margin">An effectuall prayer for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and true feeling of our own wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and miſery.</note> Now we wil tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k this our good God, for the knowledge which hee hath giuen vs of his holie word, praying him, that he would more and more increaſe vs in it, and make vs profit in this doctrine: and that we may be taught in ſuch ſort to be caſt down, that we may not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that wee are poore faultie perſons before him, and that wee bring nothyng but condemnation with vs, but that wee may alſo learne to deteſt and hate our ſinnes, and to be in ſuch ſort afraid of his iudgement, that being paſte hope in our ſelues, wee may confeſſe &amp; that earneſtly the miſeries &amp; corruptions that are in vs, to the end we may imbrace our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, &amp; altogether ſticke faſt vnto him, &amp; not to mingle our filthines w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his puritie &amp; holines: but that we may know that he is the roote,<note place="margin">Chriſt the roote and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all righteouſnes.</note> &amp; the fountaine of all righteouſnes, &amp; that there is in him ſuche perfection, as nothing can bee ſayde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, neither added thereto. And that with all, we may beat back &amp; ouerthrow,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:81"/> the falſe opinions of theſe,<note place="margin">The holy Ghoſt knitteth Chriſt, and his people together.</note> that ſlaunder the Goſpell, in ſuch ſort that we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue to our ſelues and ſhewe foorth to others, that we are vnited and knitte to our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt by his ſpirite, and that wee may more and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and proceede in his feare, vntyll ſuch tyme, as wee haue well learned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our ſelues, &amp; bee brought into the right and good way, that we may at the length be made partakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly grace,<note place="margin">Prayer for the inlightening of the ignorant.</note> which is purchaſed for vs, thorow Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Alſo that it wold pleaſe this good God, to ſhewe the ſame grace to all theſe, which are yet far ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from this foode and paſture of lyfe, to the ende that they may with vs, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his name, and ſing foorth his praiſes. That he would caſt his eye, and looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the troubles which are at this day in the poore kingdome of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> &amp; that it would pleaſe him to redreſſe the ſame, in ſuch ſort, that we may knowe and feele, that he worketh therin, by his ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power, and that he would reſtore and ſet vp theſe things that are nowe broken downe, and to declare by effect, that it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:22757:81"/> belongeth to him, to gather together the diſſipations and ſcatteringes which are in his Church, and to reſtore that which hath beene altogeather paſte hope, and that by that meanes, wee may haue matter and occaſion to yeelde him perpetuall thankes therefore, in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:82"/>
            <head>An expoſition of that part <hi>of the Catechiſme, which is</hi> appointed for the three and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth Sunday.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee haue nowe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde and open the laſt petition,<note place="margin">The ſumme of fourth and fifth petitions.</note> that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in that prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte hath geuen and taught vs. Heretofore it hath beene declared, howe and after what ſort we ought to pray for all that which concerneth this our life. And beſides (becauſe forgeueneſſe of ſinnes, is the key that openeth to vs, and giueth vs entraunce, when wee are to come vnto him) that wee ought to aſke pardon of him, &amp; to call vpon him, which petition alſo hath beene opened.</p>
            <p>But nowe it remayneth, that God in pardoning vs our ſinnes, do keep vs alſo in time to come, for theſe 2. peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are not diuided, as thinges contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them from an other, becauſe that in aſking pardon and forgeuenes of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:22757:82"/> God, we do it for the faults that we haue committed againſt him,<note place="margin">Gods mercy is a cloake for our miſchief &amp; ſin.</note> for we muſt not vnder the ſhadowe of Gods mercy, take an occaſion to do euill, nor yet take liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnder that colour, to diſpenſe with our ſelues, and too continue alwayes in our wretchedneſſe and ſinne: but when euery one of vs, ſhall loke into him ſelf, and ſhall finde him ſelfe to bee culpable and blame worthy before God, it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs then to ſigh and mourne, and to aſke pardon and forgeueneſſe. Nowe when God hath ſo receiued vs into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and buried our faultes, yet this we are to do, to pray him, in time to come, to reſtraine vs, and keepe vs from euil, that wee may bee wholy ſtrengthened by his power,<note place="margin">The ſumme of the ſixth and laſt petition.</note> to the ende that we fall not anye more. And this is that which we haue nowe to intreate of.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>Now we demaunde what followeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>Leade vs not into temptation, but deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from euill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:22757:83"/>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you make but one petition or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>No, for the ſeconde part or member, is but an expoſition of the firſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>What is the ſubſtaunce and meaning of this petition?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>Wee deſire that God leaue vs not to our ſelues, to fall into wickedneſſe, neither ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs to be ouercome of the Diuel, and the wicked luſtes of our owne fleſh, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually fight againſt vs: but that he wold geue vs power to withſtand them, holding vs vp with his hande, and keeping vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in his ſauegard, that he might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect, defend, and guide vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Forgeuenes of ſins paſt, ſhould not make vs careleſſe in time to come.</note>As I haue alreadie ſaide, after that wee haue cried and ſighed for our ſinnes and obteined mercy for our fourmer ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities and tranſgreſſions paſt, and that we know that God hath forgotten them &amp; calleth not them any more to account, wee muſt then reſpecte and conſider the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:22757:83"/> time too come. For wee knowe that wee may fall euery minute of an houre, conſideryng the frailtie and weakeneſſe which is in vs. Behold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a petition w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is worthie to be eſteemed. Some there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue bin heretofore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would diuide it in to two, thus, <hi>Lead vs not into temptation,</hi> One: <hi>But deliuer vs from euill,</hi> an other. But this is vnaduiſedly doone:<note place="margin">The meaninge of this, Lead vs not into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> For in ſaying, But deliuer vs, we meane more fully to expreſſe, that which wee had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared before. Wee pray then in the firſt place, that GOD woulde not leade vs into temptation. And what is the meaning thereof? That wee bee not vanquiſhed and ouercome of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. And what remedy haue we for that? that is, that God ſhoulde bee with vs therein, too mainteine, vpholde, and warraunte vs: For if he ſhould not main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teine vs, all were doone with vs, and we ſhould be poore comfortleſſe &amp; hopeleſſe creatures. So then this is but ſingly one requeſt or demaunde, conſiſting of theſe two partes that be therein conteined.</p>
               <p>Nowe we demaunde what is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaunce and meaning thereof: the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb facs="tcp:22757:84"/> is, that God would not ſuffer vs to fall into wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">Mans weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and his in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>finite aſſaultes ought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke him to ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt and hartye prayer.</note> and inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And ſo wee confeſſe, that wee ſhould not knowe howe to goe forwarde one ſtep w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out fallyng, and that euen as there are infinite temptations that doe aſſault vs, ſo wee ſhoulde be vanquiſhed and ouercome at euery ſtroke, vnleſſe God had pitie of vs, and ſtrengthened vs. Nowe that wee may the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and vnderſtande this, wee muſte knowe, that it behooueth vs, to requeſte of God, that hee ſuffer vs not to bee ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed and ouertaken of the Diuell, and of our owne fleſhly luſtes. Beholde the Diuell who is our enimie, hee ceaſſeth not to make war againſt vs, as it ſhal by and by be declared more largely and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:<note place="margin">A fit ſimilitude to ſet out mans frailty, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tans ſtrength.</note> We are not able to reſiſt him: it is as if a flee, woulde take vpon him too fight with a Lion: yea we are leſſe than a flee in compariſon and reſpecte of the Diuell: For what are wee? What are our weapons and armour? and what is the ſtrength and power that wee haue? Nowe hee is the prince of the worlde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.11.</note> and ſo by conſequent ruleth aboue vs: ſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:22757:84"/> that wee ſhoulde bee his pray, were it not that God doeth mainteine and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt vs. And beſides that, there are the luſts of our fleſh, which fight againſt vs: wee neede not to goe very farre too ſeeke our enimies, they are within alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: the Citie is taken, as men ſay. So that you may ſee that we haue very great neede to come vnto God, and to pray him that he woulde not ſuffer vs to be vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and ouercome of temptation. For if wee were not ſtrengthened from him,<note place="margin">Death, yea eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall death, at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of our ſteps, if God keepe vs not.</note> wee ſhoulde be more then miſerable, and wee coulde meete with no other thing at euery ſteppe but death, yea eternall and euerlaſting death. Wherfore ſo often as wee are too make this requeſt, let vs thinke what neede wee haue to doe it: for wee neuer pray to God, in good earneſt and hartily, yea with ſuche an affection as is requiſite &amp; meete, vnleſſe we knowe what neede wee haue that God pardon vs, and afterwardes that hee take care of vs. There are diuers that are very well ſkilled to pray, but it ſhalbe nothing elſe to them, but a Ceremonie. So then let vs marke, that our praiers ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:22757:85"/> not be ſo ſtedfaſtly and aſſuredly groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as they ought to be, vnleſſe euery one of vs enter and goe downe deeply intoo himſelf thus, Goe to, who art thou? How many faultes haſt thou committed?<note place="margin">Dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our ſelues muſt goe before prayer.</note> And what wilt thou demaunde of God now? That hee woulde receiue thee to mercy, and after that thou knoweſt thy frailtie, that thou be alwayes watchfull and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in time to come, to preaſe vntoo him, that hee leade thee not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Marke then what great neede wee haue of this petition, when wee ſhall haue ſomewhat narrowly conſidered of our ſelues what maner of men we are, and what our weakeneſſe is, and that we ſhould be ouercome a hundred times in a day, of ſo many enimies as wee haue, if this were not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth betweene them and vs,<note place="margin">God is our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender againſt al our enimies</note> and ſetteth himſelf againſt them as our defendour. And why ſhoulde we marke this? Let vs beholde and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Diuels might, power, and wil. He is a roaryng Lion, ſaith Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who deſireth nothing elſe, but wholy too ſwallowe vs vp and deuoure vs. And what are wee?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> euen a Flee, as I
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:22757:85"/> haue already ſaide. Afterwards when we ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, that the Diuell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not to aſſault vs a farre, neither maketh his preparation, or layeth his furniture againſt vs, on the one ſide, or on the other, but findeth matter in our ſelues, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to vanquiſhe and ouercome vs, that is to ſaye, all our affections whiche are ſo many enimities and hatredes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt GOD, as Sainte Paule ſaith in the eight of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.</note> When I ſay, wee ſhall haue thought vppon this, wee ſhall afterwardes with a good zeale pray vnto God, that he leade vs not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptation. And moreouer becauſe wee doe not ſufficiently perceiue, howe much we ought to ſuſpect and feare our owne luſtes, it is ſaide that they fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, and woulde ouercome vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, were it not that GOD gaue vs ſtrength to reſiſt and withſtand the ſame &amp; kept vs alwayes vnder his ſauegarde and defence,<note place="margin">Howe daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous our owne luſts and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are.</note> that wee might be defended by him: For if he did not beare a ſtrong hand ouer vs, and raine vs hardly vp, it is certaine, that wee coulde not tell how to goe one ſteppe without fallyng, and
<pb facs="tcp:22757:86"/> that into a mortall and deadly fall, as we haue already declared.<note place="margin">Two good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why wee ſhoulde wholy ſubmit our ſelues to Gods gouernment and guiding.</note> So then let vs learne to commit our ſelues wholy into the guiding, gouernment, and ſauegarde of almightie God, becauſe we are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to gouerne our ſelues, and that if wee woulde take it vpon vs, our preſumption ſhoulde bee a cauſe, to make euery one of vs in ſo doing, to breake our necks. And thus much concerning the firſt anſwere. And nowe we demaund further.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>By what meanes is this brought to paſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>When he doeth guide and gouerne vs by his holy ſpirite, thereby cauſing vs, too loue goodnes &amp; to hate euil, to follow righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and to the ſinne: for by the power of the holy ſpirite, we ouercome the Diuel ſinne, and the fleſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture leadeth vs to.</note>We haue ſaide that beſides that wee are frayle and weake, we are giuen to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. So long then as God ſhall leaue vs in our nature, we ſhal loue ſinne and hate
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:22757:86"/> goodnes, we ſhal hate righteouſnes, and loue euill. This prayer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhortly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thus much, that God would change vs. For ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he rightly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider himſelf as he is, ſhal finde that vntill ſuche time, as God haue taken him into his defence, he is ſetteled, and that with delight and pleaſure in ſinne: for we bring ſuch cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs from our mothers wombe, that all our ſenſes, our thoughts, and our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, are continually geuen to euil.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5.</note> Nowe if God did not ſtrengthen vs, and holde vs as it were by the hand: whither ſhall wee come? Wee haue not onely this frailtie to cauſe vs to fal, but we alſo haue this inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; redineſſe to euill. Behold then a poore &amp; miſerable ſtate. for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Diuel is a Tyrant: who hath rule, and authoritie ouer vs, vntyll ſuche time as God deliuer vs and ſet vs free,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.16.</note> euen as ſpeach is had therof in the viii. Chap. of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt according to S. Iohn.</p>
               <p>This petition then, conteineth in ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, thus much in it ſelf, that God wold in ſuche ſort chauge vs, that whereas
<pb facs="tcp:22757:87"/> nowe wee are inclined to euill, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thereto, yea that wee runne to it, and are ſetled in ſinne, that he woulde renew vs, and place in vs ſuch a print of his goodneſſe, and of his feare, that wee may hate the euyll, &amp; loue the good, which we ought to aſpire and come to. But how doeth hee woorke this?<note place="margin">Gods ſpirite an effectuall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of our newe birth.</note> By the power of his Spirite. And this is the cauſe why theſe two woordes, the <hi>Spirite</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh</hi> are ſo often ſet one of them againſt another in the Scripture. Now this woorde <hi>fleſhe,</hi> is not taken according too the common ſpeache, but it is taken for man, inſomuch that all that wee bryng from our mothers wombe,<note place="margin">Fleſh and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite what they meane.</note> is called fleſh. And what meneth this word <hi>Spirite?</hi> It is nothing of that belongeth vnto vs, that is to ſay, of that we haue of our naturall inheritaunce: but it is the grace of God by the which we are renued, Wherefore it behooueth, that God manifeſt his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer vs and in vs, in ſuche ſorte, that wee be refourmed from euil to good,<note place="margin">The Spirite a pleadge of our electio.</note> and that he ſo take vs to himſelf, that by this meanes he ratifie and confirme the adop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion which hee hath made, in electing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:22757:87"/> and choſing vs for his children. And the ſpirite of God woorketh with a certaine power, which declareth it ſelfe in vs. But here the queſtion is of drawing vs out of the Diuels tyranny, and of placing vs in ſuch libertie, that wee ſhoulde knowe, learne, and ſtriue, freely and with a good affection, to ſubdue our appetites and luſtes. And now then wee haue to marke that in praying God, not to lead vs into temptation, we muſt come to the meane whereby we may ouercome it, that is that wee may bee renued by his ſpirite. Now we cannot be allowed for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, except we haue well practiſed this ſentence of S. Paul, when he ſaith: that if we will proteſt &amp; publiſh our ſelues to be Gods children,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.27.</note> wee muſt beleeue alſo in the holy ſpirite, whiche crieth in our mouth. By that hee declareth, that when it pleaſeth God too receiue vs to mercy, and when he wyll take vs for the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his Churche, that then hee woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mightily in vs, for that purpoſe, by his ſpirite. Thus then wee ſee, what is our defence, by which God warraunteth vs againſt all the aſſaultes of the Diuell
<pb facs="tcp:22757:88"/> and all the corruptions which are in our ſelues. Now we demaunde againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>Haue all men neede to pray thus, and to be guided ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, for the Diuell watcheth continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> euen as a roaring Lion readie too deuoure vs, and wee on the other part bee ſo feeble and fraile, that hee woulde out of hande beate vs downe and ouercome vs, if God did not ſtrengthen vs and geue vs the victory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs come nowe more largely to declare, that which hath beene ſhortlye touched: that is to ſaye, that it is not in vaine nor through a Ceremonie, that we make this requeſt vnto GOD, but that neceſſitie ought to inforce vs thereto.<note place="margin">Words in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er without fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, is but hypocriſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And this is very requiſite to bee well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode, for there are diuerſe Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites that will eaſily enough pronounce and haue it often in theyr mouthes ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Leade vs not into temptation:</hi> But
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:22757:88"/> yet they knowe not wherefore they ſaye ſo. Beholde euen the Papiſtes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: it is not to be doubted, but that al they that ſay theyr <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> as they cal it, carry euen theyr owne condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with them before GOD. It is true that they that ſpeake Latine, and were neuer at Schole, knowe not what they ſaye, euen as well men as women, but what ſoeuer it bee, yet ſo it is, that euen that, ſhalbe called to a reckoning &amp; accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before God: For they make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues beleeue that they haue theyr free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyll, to guide them ſelues eyther well or yll. True it is that they wil not deny but that the grace of GOD ſupplieth theyr want, and that they are weake of themſelues, and that GOD muſt ſtretch out his hande vnto them. They wyll confeſſe ſo muche:<note place="margin">Papiſts ſay and vnſay all with one breath.</note> yet for all that ſo it is, that they preferre and highly eſteeme theyr owne vertues, and haue alwayes in theyr mouthe this woorde <hi>Freewyll:</hi> and wee can doe good and euill, wee can eaſily follow the good way, and gouerne our ſelues in ſuche ſort, that when God
<pb facs="tcp:22757:89"/> ſhall helpe vs but a little, wee can of our ſelues inforce our ſelues, and rydde our buſineſſe:<note place="margin">Howe true this is, See <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.13.</note> To be ſhort, both the wyll &amp; the deede is in man, at the leaſt in part as they ſuppoſe.</p>
               <p>So then in praying it is certaine that they knowe not too whom they directe them ſelues and theyr prayers, and that ſo many times as they ſhal haue mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled vp theyr <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> it is for nothing elſe but to make them without excuſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore GOD: For they ſhewe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to bee lyars in that, when they ſay, <hi>Leade vs not into temptation,</hi> and it ſeemeth them: that it is in theyr power too eſcape and too diſpenſe with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Wherefore ſo much the more diligently ought we to marke and weigh this pointe,<note place="margin">All haue neede of the grace &amp; glory of God.</note> to witte, that all haue neede to bee ayded from GOD, and that not onely in ſome one reſpecte or other, but alſo to bee fully and wholy gouerned by hym, becauſe they are able too doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of them ſelues, and they ſhoulde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery minute of an houre bee vanquiſhed and ouercome, vnleſſe that GOD did ſtrengthen them againſt aſſaultes.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:22757:89"/>
               <p>Let vs take then the moſt valiant men in the world,<note place="margin">The beſt are not able to ſtande without God.</note> and thoſe that ſeeme to be the moſt hardie, bolde, and couragious, and it is certaine, that euen in the leaſt of their combats and aſſaultes, they ſhould be ouerwhelmed, vnleſſe God dyd reach out his hande to them, and that they were vpholden by him. And indeede, they that haue proceeded further, and haue attey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned more than others, ought alwayes to conſider how temptations doe ouercome mens infirmitie &amp; weakenes. When we ſhall ſee, that one is fallen into theft, an other into whoredom, an other into coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, and other faultes and wicked deedes, they are ſo many glaſſes ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, to make vs knowe and feele our owne frailtie.<note place="margin">Gods children may take profit by the falles of their fellowes, and of other men.</note> And thus we ought to be mooued, when ſome ſhall ſpeake too vs and ſay: Such a matter is fallen out to ſuche a parte, and to ſuche a one: and to pray, O Lorde, lead vs not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And wherefore? our ſluggiſhnes and ſlouth is repreſſed thereby, &amp; we are with all thereby prouoked, to pray and beſeech him.<note place="margin">Mans pride beaten downe.</note> And wee ſhalbe altogether without excuſe, if we thinke that wee are
<pb facs="tcp:22757:90"/> not of the ſame lumpe, and are ſubiect in tyme to come, not onely to fall ſo farre, but alſo to doe woorſe, if wee wyll of our ſelues goe out and place our ſelues in the fields, and that without trayning and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. Nowe the trayning and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment is, as I haue alreadie ſayde, Gods holy ſpirite who is the true guide, whereof wee haue neede euen as a little childe,<note place="margin">A fit ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> that is daded (as we ſay) guyded and lead of the Father, by the arme or hande. Marke then for the concluſion of this point, that this requeſt is neceſſary for all: and that when we ſhall pray vnto God in ſuch ſort, that we muſt haue this ſentence well imprinted within vs, that we can doe nothyng at all, and that vntil ſuche tyme, as God haue manifeſted his ſtrength and power, wee ſhould be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come at euery blowe: to be ſhort, that the deuill ſhould beare rule ouer vs in all ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and that wee haue no other reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, but to ſay, O Lorde ſtrengthen me, and afterwardes I may reioyce in my ſelfe, as Saint Paule ſheweth vs an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample thereof in himſelf, ſaying: I wyll reioyce my ſelf in him that ſtrengtheneth
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:22757:90"/> me. Nowe Saint Paul vſeth an excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is to ſay in God. Hee confeſſeth that he is able to doe nothing, as alſo we are admoniſhed and taught by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ieremie, who ſaieth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.23.24. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17.</note> Let not the ſtrong man glorie in his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, the wiſe man, in his wiſdome, the rich man in his riches: but whoſoeuer wil glorie, let him know that I am he that maketh ſtrong, that giueth wiſedome, that inricheth, and who am indeede the glorie and reioycing of men.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.31.</note> And this is that which wee haue to learne concernyng this pointe. And moreouer to cauſe vs the better to feele this, let vs know what a one the deuil is: he is as I haue ſayd a roaring Lyon,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.6.</note> and who hath power and will inough wholy to deuour vs, were it not that God ſetteth him ſelfe betweene vs two: for our ayde and defence ſhall neuer bee founde in all that which wee can bryng of our owne, whatſoeuer it be: wherefore God alone muſt bryng vs, and giue vs the victorie, or els otherwyſe, wee ſhalbe torne all in peeces. But nowe tell me,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:22757:91"/>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>What meaneth this Worde Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>The wilie guiles and ſubtill aſſaultes of the deuill, which hee vſeth to take vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, euen as our natural vnderſtanding, is readie to be deceiued, and to deceiue our ſelues, and our will, is rather readie, to giue it ſelfe ouer to euil, then to God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>Thus becauſe this word, Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is obſcure and darke, we aſke what it meaneth and ſignifieth: for there are dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and it may be, euen in this compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, that haue prayed God not to leade them into temptation, and dyd yet neuer knowe what they aſked of God. But that is to prophane &amp; abuſe the prayer which our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt hath giuen vs.<note place="margin">To pray and not to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, is to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe prayer.</note> It is true, that men wil eaſily and ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceiue, that Temptation commeth of Tempting, and euerie one will indeed ſay, I am tempted on this ſorte and on that, but yet this is not all: behold ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why we muſt haue a ſhort declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:22757:91"/> of the woord.</p>
               <p>Nowe temptation in ſumme impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all the wylle guiles that the Diuell hath to deceiue vs by.<note place="margin">What the word Temptation meaneth.</note> And hee findeth vs ready enclined thereto: for wee are not onely ſubiect to bee deceiued, but there is none of vs all, that boweth and bendeth not himſelf therto. Though we ſee others to bee deceiued, yet wee wyll not leaue of to followe theyr wayes and ſteppes: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde a marueilous blindneſſe, and yet notwithſtanding this is ouercommon. So then, the more that the Diuel findeth vs apt and diſpoſed to euill, the more doth he therefore applie and vſe the meanes, to prouoke and ſtirre vs vp thereto.</p>
               <p>There are two ſortes of temptations.<note place="margin">Two ſortes of Temptations, outward and inward.</note> One ſorte may bee called outwarde, and the other are within. The outward temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are thus, as when the Diuell, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadowe or colour of ſhewing vs a goodly and fayre houſe, or a fielde, or ſome ſuche like thing,<note place="margin">We muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing.</note> wyll come &amp; geue vs a matche, too kindle fire in vs, thus I woulde indeede that that were mine. The thing ſurely in it ſelfe, cannot be tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but yet the Diuell blindeth vs there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:92"/> to deceyue vs, if it were poſſible. When a man ſhal looke vpon a woman, he may indeede beholde her, (howe faire and bewtifull ſo euer ſhe be) with a chaſt eye: but the deuill will ſtirre vp thereby a meane, to draw a man to luſt, and whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. To be ſhort, the creatures of God, howe many ſo euer of them there be, both high and low, of them ſelues cannot hurt vs, naye they are profitable vnto vs: but the deuill maketh vs to ſtaye and ſtande vppon them,<note place="margin">Men muſt be heedle, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the vſe of Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> to the ende wee may abuſe them: inſomuch that theſe things which are profitable for vs, and which we ought to vſe, as the ſingular bleſſinges of God, are ſo many baites and ſnares to bryng vs to deſtruction: euen as the Sunne was worſhipped of the Pagans and Gentils. It is certainly a very glorious creature, and ſo profitable, as nothyng more: for we know that the Sunne giueth vs light and hath ſuch force in it ſelfe, that it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the earth to bryng foorth all fruites for our ſuſtenaunce and nouriſhment: and yet men haue made thereof an idoll. Behold howe the deuill, by his ſubtleties
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:22757:92"/> and craftes, draweth men to deſtruction. Nowe the other temptations,<note place="margin">Inward temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</note> of which mention is made in this place, are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and they are theſe wicked appetites and luſtes, which the deuill kindeleth in vs: for mans harte is as it were a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace: Let men put coales into a furnace and afterwardes blowe, behold fire ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and kindled. Euen ſo muche may be ſaide of vs, for wee are readie to receyue all wicked affections, which are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny coales,<note place="margin">Howe ſinne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth in man.</note> and then beholde the deuill he commeth and bloweth thereupon, and then the fire is in good earneſt and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly kindled. This concupiſcence and luſt then, which the deuill doeth in ſuche ſorte put into vs, when that it prouoketh vs and leadeth vs to euil, theſe are I ſay, the temptations, ſpoken of in this place. So then, when wee pray vnto God, that hee leade vs not into temptation, let vs well marke, that wee haue neede to bee warranted and defended from all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptes of the deuill:<note place="margin">The great blindnes of mans heart to good things before regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> otherwyſe we ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee ſodeinely caught, and deceiued at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye turne. It is ſo indeede, for wee are inclyned and readye too euyll,
<pb facs="tcp:22757:93"/> and as for good, wee knowe not what it meaneth, vntyll ſuche time as God haue renewed vs, and chaunged vs, as wee haue already declared. But nowe wee demaunde and aſke further?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>But wherefore aſkeſt thou of GOD that hee leade thee not into euill, ſeeyng that that is an office belonging properly and peculiarly to the Diuell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>As God through his mercy preſerueth his faithfull people, and ſuffereth not the Diuell to leade them out of the way, nor ſinne to ouercome them: ſo theſe whom he wyll puniſhe, he doeth not onely caſt of and withdrawe his grace from them, but alſo deliuereth them to the Diuell, that they may bee ſubiect to his tyranny, yea he ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them with blindnes, and giueth them vp into a reprobate minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>Behold here a very hard queſtion: for it ſeemeth that this requeſt or petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not agreeable to reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: We demaund of God, that hee place vs not in temptation
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:22757:93"/> and doe wee pray hym that hee woulde not make vs murderers or whooremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers? and yet that belongeth vntoo the Diuell.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.44.</note> It ſeemeth then that in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt there is manyfeſt abſurditie, and that wee attribute that vnto God, which is rather proper vnto the Diuell: for he is the father of lying the prince of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and the author of ſinne. But this agreeth not to God: and yet it ſeemeth that men impute euen the very fault ther of vnto him. Saint Iames ſayth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.13.14.</note> that we neede not to goe ſeeke that without vs, which is within vs: for no man is temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but by his owne concupiſcence and luſte. To bee ſhorte,<note place="margin">A fit compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> there is then the furnace, as I haue ſayde, and the fire: that is to ſay, that wee are the furnace: or concupiſcences, &amp; luſts are the walles, and the Diuell kindleth them. And wherefore is it, that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte teacheth vs to pray on this faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God his father, <hi>Leade vs not intoo temptation?</hi> This altogether gaineſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his righteouſneſſe. True it is, that at the firſt ſhewe this maner of ſpeache ſeemeth harde: but wee muſte come too
<pb facs="tcp:22757:94"/> Gods ſecrete iudgements,<note place="margin">Gods ſecrete iudgements muſt be reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced.</note> which (to bee ſhort and to conclude) we muſt adore and reuerence, ſeeyng we can not atteyne to a full and perfect knowledge thereof: for this is ſufficient, that we knowe in part, that which belongeth to our ſaluation, and that God reſerue with him ſelfe the reſt vntyll the laſt day, wherein wee ſhal beholde him face to face.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</note> Nowe we ſee, howe God keepeth his faithfull people, and euery one feeleth the ſame, by his owne experience. And wherefore is it, that we ſtande vpright againſt the deuill and his aſſaultes? It is, becauſe that we are vpholden by God, for our victorie commeth from thence, as I haue already ſaide. Beholde then it is God, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth vs from the deuils temptations. And on the other ſide,<note place="margin">How &amp; whom God leadeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptation.</note> he leadeth them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptation, whome hee hath reiected, and whom he will not receiue or take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his protection and ſauegard. And this is the reaſon alſo,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18.</note> wherefore it is often ſaide, that God hardeneth a peruerſe, frowarde, and obſtinate harte. At the firſt bluſhe and appearaunce theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſeeme ſtraunge. And alſo there are
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:22757:94"/> at this day varlets and fantaſticall men, who blaſpheme, when ſuche thinges are ſpoken, and would that all this were blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the holy ſcripture, &amp; vexe them ſelues when we reade that God blindeth men, after that he ſeeth that they are har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened. And is it ſo? yea indeede: but that is attributed to God, as to a iuſt Iudge. As if a Iudge ſit in his ſeate, and ſay:<note place="margin">A familiar and plaine example.</note> To<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morowe I will cauſe a whoremonger to bee puniſhed if hee amende not: and yet notwithſtandyng hee letteth hym goe on forewarde in his vilainie. If a Iudge ſay ſo, what reaſon is there agaynſt it? So then wee ſee that there is good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that God ſtryke them with blindnes, that are reprobate and reiected from him: wherefore let vs not any longer thynke this petition ſtraunge, which we make: to witte, that God leade vs not into temptation.</p>
               <p>It is true, that at the firſt ſhowe, this goeth beyonde our capacitie and reaſon as I haue alreadie ſayde: but wee muſt come thus farre, that Gods iudgements are bottomeleſſe depthes, and ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:22757:95"/> God leadeth into temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thoſe whom it pleaſeth him.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33.</note> And after what ſort doth he performe this? not onely becauſe that euill proceedeth from vs, but alſo becauſe he condemneth them, whom he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, and reiecteth them, that they may be ouercome of all temptations. He deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth them to Satan, as the hangman appointed to put them to death, and the executor of his iuſtice. Euen as a Iudge hauyng pronounced his ſentence againſt an euill doer, wil deliuer him afterwards into the handes of the executioner: So doeth God deale in this behalfe. Behold then howe hee leadeth into temptation thoſe, that are not of the number of his children, and whom hee hath not in hys guiding and gouernment. And therefore let vs marke, that if it pleaſed God to vſe rigor againſt vs, it is certaine, that after hee hath taken his power from vs, hee ſhould not onely leaue vs for ſuche as we are, but hee ſhoulde deliuer vs into the hands and power of Satan. As it is ſaid, that he will ſende ſtrength of errour, and ſtrong deluſion. That word is very meet to be weighed,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11.</note> for Saint Paul ſaith not,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:22757:95"/> that he will onely giue vs ouer to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, that hee may abuſe and deceiue vs, but he ſayth, that he wyll ſende ſtrength of errour, inſomuch that he ſhalbe able to execute his pleaſure in vs, by his errours and illuſions, ſo that wee ſhall be, as it were bruite beaſtes.<note place="margin">The corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of euill.</note> And after that wee ſhalbe ſo blinded in our vnderſtandings, he wyll drawe vs to vnruly and diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red paſſions, and make vs doe this and that, yea we ſhall runne after it, and that ſo farre, as wee ſhalbe caſt downe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. And howe doeth he this? It is true that the beginnyng heereof, commeth from the corruption of our nature, which wee bryng with vs from our mothers wombe. And then there is the deuill, who kindleth the fire of our luſtes: but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be, yet ſo it falleth out, that God woorketh withall:<note place="margin">How God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the deed of ſinne, and yet no ſinne to be imputed to him.</note> not that ſinne or euill ſhould any maner of way be imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, but becauſe that by his incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible iudgements, he is able to blinde theſe men, that are not of the number of his people and of his Church: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt needs be, that ſuch men ſhold be vnder the tyranny of the deuill, that he
<pb facs="tcp:22757:96"/> poſſeſſe them, and pull them euery way, on euery ſide, and in euery place, where hee ſhall thinke good him ſelfe. Now we demaund further yet,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>What meaneth this clauſe which fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: For thine is the kingdome, and the power, and the glorie, for euer and euer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>To put vs againe in remembrance, that our praiers be rather grounded vpon God, and vpon his almightie power &amp; goodnes, than vpon our ſelues, who indeed are not woorthie to open our mouthes to call vpon him. And alſo to teach vs to conclude and ſhutte vp all our prayers, in the prayſing of his power and goodnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>When wee haue prayed vnto God, that he leade vs not into temptation, the meane and way is added, as I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready touched: that is, that he deliuer vs from euill, or from the euill one. For as we haue alledged out of the eight Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:22757:96"/> of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to Saint Iohn,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.44.</note> if hee deliuered vs not, we ſhould alwayes remaine in this miſerable bondage of his. Nowe this hath beene declared in the firſt place, that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt hath acquyted and diſcharged vs before God his father: and next,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3.4.</note> that he died (ſaith Saint Paul) to the end that wee might liue, that hee was buryed and roſe againe, to the ende that wee might folowe him to the graue, that is in the death of ſinne in vs, &amp; laſtly in a better lyfe than heretofore wee haue lead. But it behoueth vs daily and deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thinke vpon this leſſon, and that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt make vs feele the fruite of his death and reſurrection,<note place="margin">Our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall.</note> and that hee continue to redeeme vs ſtill, to wyt, out of the power of ſinne and Satan. Nowe when wee make this prayer, wee ſay for concluſion, for thine is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the power and the glorie, for euer, and euer. Hereuppon wee aſke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this concluſion is added. And there are two reaſons or cauſes of it put down in the anſwere.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22757:97"/>
               <p>The firſt is: that it is don, to proteſt and declare that all that we haue prayed for before,<note place="margin">Our prayers ought to be grounded vpon Gods glorie, goodnes, and power.</note> is not grounded vpon any thyng but the glorie of God, his iuſtice, and his goodnes, and laſtly vpon his ſoueraigne rule and authoritie. And now it behoueth vs to declare this, as it were by peece meale and particularly, to the end it may be better vnderſtood. Let vs put the caſe that this were not added, to this forme of prayer, euery man might doubt, ſaying, Alas: ſhal I be heard of him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue aſked of him myne ordinarie and dayly bread, the forgiuenes of my ſinnes, and that he would guide me by his holy ſpirit? yea ſeeing that I haue craued more high and excellent thinges of him, to wyt, that his name may be glorified, that his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may increaſe and multiplie daily more and more, tyll it come to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, fulfilling, and perfection ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: theſe thinges ſurmount and exceed all that man hath. And howe may I be ſure that I ſhalbe heard? Should we doubt of it. But our Lorde declareth vnto vs that our requeſts and prayers are not groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon that which wee bring with vs:
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:22757:97"/> for who or what are wee? And what is it that we bring with vs. And though that wee were the beſt diſpoſed people in the worlde to pray, yet certaine it is, that a man may beholde vs continually altered and chaunged in a minute of an houre.<note place="margin">Two good ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe howe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual praiers are, which are grounded vpon men.</note> So our requeſt and prayer ſhould bee very weake, and indeede nothing els but ſmoke, or as a winde that vaniſheth (as men ſay) if it had not an other more ſtrong and aſſured fundation. And this is the cauſe, wherefore wee are ſent backe, as it were, to Gods glory, to his infinite power to his might, and to his euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting rule and gouernment. If then wee woulde bee well aſſured, that our prayers haue not beene vayne, and that we haue not been fruſtrated of our hope, but that we haue obteined all that which we haue demaunded, let vs come hither. Nowe haſte thou prayed to God?<note place="margin">Prayers right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made ſhal not want theyr ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</note> euen thus, I confeſſe that hee is almightie, that all power belongeth too him, that my requeſtes being grounded thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall not bee without hauing their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and accompliſhment. And thus much for the firſt reaſon which is allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:22757:98"/> in this place.</p>
               <p>Now the ſecond is, that we learne alwaies to conclude and ſhut vp our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with thankſgeuings.<note place="margin">Prayers made and not Gods glory onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected therein are vayne.</note> Wherfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee haue to pray vnto God, let vs make continually this final concluſion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God may be glorified. For without that, all our prayers ſhalbe nothing but puffes of winde, neither ſhall there be any order therein, or marke whereon a man ought to ſtay himſelf. There ſhalbe nothing founde therein, but a light and flying affection, vnleſſe wee pray to God, that it woulde pleaſe him, alwayes to ſhewe vs this grace, that we may deſire, that he may bee honoured, and that ſuch prayſes may be yeelded vnto him,<note place="margin">The confeſſion and feeling of our ſins ſhould not hinder vs from prayer, but rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vs therto.</note> euen as hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth. And thus much concerning the ſeconde reaſon, whiche wee haue to mark out of this ſpeach, where it is ſaid that the kingdome belongeth vnto god, &amp; the glory for euermore, to the ende that in confeſſing alwaies, our pouerties and our faultes, wee leaue not for all that, whatſoeuer fall out, too pray vnto him. And why ſo? becauſe that if wee enter into our ſelues, wee ſhall deſire nothing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:22757:98"/> but that Gods kingdome may increaſe, that his power may be known, that his will may bee doone, that his glory may ſhine foorth in the midſt of vs, &amp; we may comfort our ſelues in his goodneſſe, in his righteouſneſſe, and in his mercy. Otherwyſe there is no doubt, but that wee ſhalbe worſe then bruite beaſtes, or like vnto poore fearefull and aſtoniſhed people, that is, nothing elſe but crie and houle, and yet knowe not wherefore: but that wee may thruſt forwarde our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers continually to this marke, that God may be glorified, and praiſed: for when wee ſhall ſeeke the aduauncemente of his kingdome, that is to ſaye, that hee may haue rule and authoritie ouer vs, and that wee may yeeld him the homage and ſeruice,<note place="margin">How and when our praiers bee well ordered &amp; framed.</note> that he deſerueth and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, then ſhall our prayers be rightly ruled and ordered.</p>
               <p>Now we wyl fall down before the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of our good God, acknowledging the infinit faults and offences, for which wee are blame woorthie: praying him alſo to make this doctrine ſo effectuall and powerfull in vs, that it may make
<pb facs="tcp:22757:99"/> vs alwayes to ſubmit our ſelues too his ſeruice and obedience,<note place="margin">Two generall ends of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of God.</note> and that it may ſtande vs in ſteede to confirme in vs the grace of his adoption, which hee hath wrought in vs, that ſo we call vpon him, as our father, in more greater boldneſſe then heretofore, and ſhew, that it is not in vaine, that wee demaunde that he leade vs not into temptation, neither geue vs ouer to Satan: but that he wold gouerne vs by his ſpirite, and geue vs ſtrength and power to reſiſt, yea to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Diuell, and the luſtes of our owne fleſh. And that hee woulde not onely ſhewe this grace and fauour to vs, but to al the people and nations of the earth. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <closer>
               <hi>God be praiſed nowe and <hi>euer, So be it.</hi>
               </hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:99"/>
            <head>I pray thee (gentle Reader) to haue an eye to the Marginall notes, and referre them to their right places: and alſo to correcte thy booke from theſe faults following, and afterwardes to reade with iudgement too thy profite and comfort.</head>
            <p>Follio <hi>6.</hi> Pag. <hi>2.</hi> Line <hi>12.</hi> For abroade, reade aboade. Fol. <hi>9.</hi> b. line <hi>22.</hi> For vve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reade vve must not then. Fol. <hi>13.</hi> b in the margent, for de ſacro Baſil, reade de ſacro Baptiſt. Fol. <hi>18.</hi> b line <hi>6.</hi> for it ſaid, reade it vvas ſaid. Fol. <hi>20.</hi> b. line <hi>22.</hi> for accept, reade except. Fol. <hi>23</hi> a. line <hi>19.</hi> for imperfection, reade perfection. Fol. <hi>24.</hi> b. line <hi>3</hi> for vvinne, reade conuince. Fol. <hi>29.</hi> b. line <hi>18</hi> for confirme, reade conforme. Fol. <hi>31.</hi> b line <hi>8</hi> for crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, reade nation. Fol. <hi>34.</hi> a laſte line, for ſufficiently, reade ſtifly. Fol. <hi>39.</hi> a. line <hi>25.</hi> for ſinnes, reade ſinnner. Fol. <hi>39.</hi> b. line <hi>9.</hi> for vvorde, reade, corde, Fol. <hi>40.</hi> b line <hi>19.</hi> for debated, reade caſt dovvne. Fol. <hi>41.</hi> a. line <hi>3.</hi> for makers, reade vvoorkes. Fol. <hi>41.</hi> a. line <hi>12.</hi> for one, ceade do one. Fol. <hi>42.</hi> b. line <hi>24.</hi> for beastly, reade beaſts. Fol. <hi>50.</hi> b. line <hi>10.</hi> for at time, at that time. Fol. <hi>59.</hi> a line firſt, for dead, reade death. Fol. <hi>63.</hi> a. lin <hi>22.</hi> for his reade this, and b. line <hi>23.</hi> for in it, reade in vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:100"/>
            <p>Imprinted in London <hi>at the three Cranes in</hi> the Vintree, by Thomas <hi>Dawſon, for George</hi> Biſhop, 1580.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22757:100"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
